<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>gopher://rawtext.club:70/1/~xiu/phlog/</title>
<link>gopher://rawtext.club:70/1/~xiu/phlog/</link>

<item>
<link>gopher://rawtext.club/1/~xiu/phlog/2023-12-29-last-quarter-catchups-2023.txt</link>
<title>2023-12-29 Last quarter catchups of 2023</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
# Last quarter catchups of 2023
---
rawtext.club:70/~xiu
2023-12-29
Boorloo/Perth, Western Australia
---

Long time no see, gopherfriends.

Over the last three months, my time online has become very
deliberate, with very little of it spent on leisure or idleness. If
I&#x27;ve not got a specific purpose for being on the computer, then
I&#x27;ve got my nose in a book, my face glued to Baldur&#x27;s Gate 3, or
I&#x27;m doing some other offline or non-internet thing.

It&#x27;s been nice. I feel like some old habits and compulsions are
ebbing away at last. A morning journaling habit means my phone can
return to my bedside without it being the first thing I reach for
when I wake up. The urge is still there, but it&#x27;s the analog
notebook I reach for instead.

My novel launched and is now in a local specialty bookstore in my
city, and there&#x27;s talk of doing a book signing event next year.
Something I, at one stage, thought I would never have it in me to
do. Well, here&#x27;s hoping it all works out. I&#x27;ve decided I need to
put my big brave pants on and face my fears.

I did face my fear of going for my first solo bike ride. Sod&#x27;s Law:
my journey was along a busy road where the bike path abruptly stops
part of the way. That was unexpected, but I was lucky traffic
wasn&#x27;t as busy as it usually is, and a friend with mini-pies and
sausage rolls was waiting for me at my destination ^_^

This last quarter of 2023 has felt like a turning point for me.
Life isn&#x27;t perfect. There&#x27;s red flags scattered all over the place,
but I&#x27;m in a better place than last year, and certainly the year
before. On top of not having Christmas COVID this time around. I
feel very grateful for the people who share vital ideas, and very
relieved for having stumbled upon them and learned stuff that
helped me improve my approach.

I make no promises to update more in 2024. Que sera sera.

Happy new year, everyone!
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://rawtext.club/1/~xiu/phlog/2023-09-03-trip-book-workaholism.txt</link>
<title>2023-09-03 Little trip, finishing my book, workaholism relapse</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
# Little trip, finishing my book, workaholism relapse
---
rawtext.club:70/~xiu
2023-09-03
Boorloo/Perth, Western Australia
---

As I type this, my partner is playing the new robot
souls game by From Software. It&#x27;s funny listening to
a mysterious voice talk about a very serious
military project called &quot;Project Ibis&quot; because here
the nickname for ibis birds is &quot;bin chicken&quot; XD

Heaps has happened since my last update back in
June. Here&#x27;s my attempt to round it all up and
hopefully not waffle too much:

# A short trip to an eco resort

We took a short trip to Tasmania to stay at an eco
resort. It was so lovely and so quiet. There was NO
WIFI and patchy mobile access, which meant all we
could do was enjoy the beautiful forest surrounds,
read books, play board games, eat the complimentary
snacks, and occasionally interact with other guests.

Coming home, re-immersing in the chaos and the faff,
made me think about what I enjoyed most, what I love
and want to work harder at, and what I need to work
on changing pronto.

# Creative crisis and finishing my book

I feel so much better about the creative crisis
thing[1] after reading BIRD BY BIRD by Anne Lamott.
It&#x27;s an unexpectedly brilliant book that talks about
the mindset and emotional toil of writing. It helped
me contextualise my anxieties and get through the
final throes of this project I&#x27;ve been working on
for the last year and a half.

The writing group I joined a few months ago has been
invaluable in helping me understand what I do as a
writer, and helping me consolidate my knowledge and
experience by helping local SFF writers yet to
publish their first book.

So I have a novel that&#x27;s on track to launch near the
end of this month. As soon as I received my proof
copy of the paperback, a weight just lifted off my
shoulders. I&#x27;m feeling connected to a local creative
community of peers, and comfortable with the choices
I&#x27;ve made for publishing and distribution. It&#x27;s the
best I can do with what I&#x27;ve got, and that&#x27;s gotta
be good enough ... for now.

# Workaholism relapse

For most of the year, I&#x27;ve been developing a
healthier approach to work to prevent future burnout
and recover from all the burnout debt I&#x27;ve
accumulated for much of my adult life.

After we got back from Tassie, I threw out the
playbook and began a several-week crunch to meet all
my deadlines. It was not good. I met the deadlines,
but with enough time to spare that I realistically
could have finished the work without stressing so
much, had I just trusted in the new system.

It has been very hard to shake the crunch mentality,
perhaps it&#x27;s been so ingrained for so many years.
Would this be &quot;falling off the wagon&quot; in a
workaholic context? I must say: it sucks

BUT, on the bright side, it tells me my new system
can work.  Attempts to get back into it in the last
few days have yielded positive results.

# What next?

Once I work up the nerve, I&#x27;ll approach local
bookstores about consignment. I plan to take some
time off at the end of September after the book
comes out, or maybe the whole of October idk. Just
to re-center, catch up on chores and house stuff,
planting new things in the garden, and stuff like
that.

[1] gopher://rawtext.club/0/~xiu/phlog/2023-04-02-crisis-of-creative-existence.txt
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://rawtext.club/1/~xiu/phlog/2023-06-11-garden-update.txt</link>
<title>2023-06-11 Garden update: 11 June 2023</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
# Garden update - 11 June 2023
---
rawtext.club:70/~xiu
2023-06-11
Boorloo/Perth, Western Australia
---

I&#x27;m failing a bit at keeping a dedicated garden log. I
guess it&#x27;s just easier to update a single phlog, even if
it means everything goes into one mish-mash &#x27;stream&#x27; of
updates. At some point, I&#x27;ll probably move everything
time-based from there to here and keep the garden &quot;log&quot; as
a collection of random gardening notes.

It is wintery here, but in that Perth kind of way. In the
last week or so, we&#x27;ve had rain, hail, chilly wind, and
just wet chilliness all round. My garden is loving the
water, but I am freezing my bloody arse off.

# Sqft catchup: summer and autumn (Birak, Bunuru, Djeran) 

Our brown onions were a fail. The nasturtium looks like it
wants to take over the world, and we&#x27;re not sure anymore
that we want to make pesto from it. Maybe it&#x27;ll bloom at
some point and we can hold out for nasturtium capers? We
have not harvested much garlic chive, as we have no idea
what to do with it.

Strawberries still have not fruited. We are done with
tomatoes, and I&#x27;m not sure I want to grow them again --
although I would consider a native bush tomato if we can
get our hands on a plant. We are also done with the
chillies, but instead of uprooting and composting the
plant, we&#x27;ve stuck it elsewhere in the garden to see how
it fares.

Same with both our basil plants -- one ended up getting
buried under a new compost pile. The other seems to have
taken root behind the square foot garden and has not yet
succumbed to the cold.

# The compost pile

Shortly after taking over this space, we set up a compost
pile in a spot the size of a picnic blanket, which I&#x27;ll
call the North Wing. I was surprised at how quickly stuff
broke down. We had lots of browns (lupin mulch, cardboard,
some newspaper) and a fair whack of greens (fruit &amp; veg
scraps) going in at a steady rate. We&#x27;d water it a little
every time we watered the Sqft bed and turn it every
couple of weeks, finding the undersides nicely blackened
and rich. It had that lovely smell of damp earthiness, and
not the stink I feared would upset the neighbours.

We spread it out across the surface of the North Wing in
early April. Lots of little weeds and the occasional
mushroom have come up since the rains started in earnest,
which means our &quot;forest floor&quot; is off to a good start.
I&#x27;ll expand on this another time. For now, we&#x27;re letting
the weeds do their thing. I don&#x27;t know what the majority
weed is (but I&#x27;ll have to look it up), but there&#x27;s also
some Sow Thistle and a few scattered blades of something
that looks like our garlic chive but doesn&#x27;t have a smell.

We also planted a dichondra (a native ground cover
sometimes used as lawn replacement), which we&#x27;re hoping
will become a dominant species across the whole garden
bed. But slowly and all in good time.

# A second compost pile

There&#x27;s a second compost pile in a smaller section I&#x27;ll
call the East Wing. It&#x27;s a sandier spot that&#x27;s a bit less
stable, but I think we can build it up over time.

Without the scumbag summer sun to bake our kitchen scraps,
I expect it&#x27;ll take longer for this compost pile to ripen.
Overall, I think the East Wing will need more care to make
it come good, but I have fantasies of growing a midyim
berry (native shrub with white speckled berries that taste
a little like gingerbread) and possibly some muntries
(native groundcover with currant-like berries) there.

# Misc...

That&#x27;s it for now. Tbh, I haven&#x27;t felt very motivated in
the garden because of the cold, even though these wet
months are the best time to plant things in Perth. Maybe
the drive will return once we&#x27;re into the new financial
year, old tasks have been closed off, etc. etc. For the
time being, I&#x27;ll just fantasise about all the lovely
plants we might be able to squeeze into that space one
day, once this first preparatory stage is done.
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://rawtext.club/1/~xiu/phlog/2023-05-25-my-ereader-compromise.txt</link>
<title>2023-05-25 My e-reader compromise</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
!My e-reader compromise
---
rawtext.club:70/~xiu
2023-05-25
Boorloo/Perth, Western Australia
---
The kindle jailbreak[1] is a no-go. I spent half a day
taking it apart, tooling with it, fiddling with
jumper cables until my hands cramped, rebooted until
I was sick of the bright startup lights.

As much as I dream about being a cyberpunk hacker, I
just don&#x27;t have the know-how or patience right now
to make it happen. Might need to cut my teeth on
something easier like repairing the button on our
car beeper. Hey, I changed the battery in one of our
remote controls last week, so anything could happen.

Anyway, having to relent on the jailbreak left me
grumpy about closed-source and proprietary tech. It
didn&#x27;t help that while comfort culling my bookmarks
I found a now-lost mastodon thread along the lines
of, &quot;If you think today&#x27;s big platforms are too big
to fail, just remember that AOL and Yahoo were once
the Internet.&quot; (Or something like that.)

It inspired me to keep looking for something at
least a little bit open-sourcey and free-er for the
books I can&#x27;t JUST get physical copies of, according
to my persnickey book policy[2].

Here&#x27;s what I landed on:

epy[3] is a CLI ebook reader available under a
GPL-3.0 license. It&#x27;s written in python and
maintained by wustho (Benawi Adha), an Indonesian
software developer. It&#x27;s snappy, intuitive, easy to
pick up, and has bookmarking capabilities among
other features. And it runs happily on the
Vivobook[4] as well as my Big Internet machine.

There are people in my writing network who publish
exclusively on the Zon, but I guess I don&#x27;t need
kindle hardware to read their work. I can just run
the kindle app on my phone or Big Internet machine.
Makes more sense to donate the device to someone who
can appreciate it more fully. I&#x27;m not that person
anymore.

Otsukaresamadeshita, little paperwhite. I&#x27;m grateful
for the time we spent together, and for how we now
part ways.

[1] gopher://rawtext.club/0/~xiu/phlog/2023-03-18-nophone-projectfail-birdstuff.txt
[2] gopher://rawtext.club/0/~xiu/phlog/2022-11-25-persnickety-paper-books.txt
[3] https://github.com/wustho/epy
[4] gopher://rawtext.club/0/~xiu/phlog/2023-01-15-permacomputing-manjaro-i3-asus-vivobook.txt
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://rawtext.club/1/~xiu/phlog/2023-05-04-the-phone-barrier.txt</link>
<title>2023-05-04 The phone barrier</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
!The phone barrier
---
rawtext.club:70/~xiu
2023-05-04
Boorloo/Perth, Western Australia
---
I&#x27;m not sure when my aversion to phone calls began. I
remember chatting for ages with friends on the phone when
I was in highschool. And then tolerating phone calls from
guys who&#x27;d call up and have nothing to talk about but
still want to hang out on the line, and there was no way
to cut it short without being rude (and also because,
I&#x27;ve been informed, my autism probably meant I didn&#x27;t
have a sense for how). Maybe that planted the seed of
dislike, idk.

Something definitely changed after I got a mobile
phone--I think all the talk of radiation and brain cancer
must have moved it along somewhat. Then later as texting
and non-SMS-based messaging got cheaper and easier, and
the audio quality of phone calls got crunchier, I guess
my phone-call senses just atrophied. Extroverts,
intrusive people, and those of a phone-faced disposition
making a big deal probably contributed some weight too.

Over the years, the aversion became an anxiety.

However, one time in my 30s, despite this anxiety, I
decided to call my grandma just to say hi. The call was
really short, which was fine, but I think she worried she
gave off the impression she didn&#x27;t know how to talk on
the phone. I get the sense it became a bit of a family
joke, and the next time we spoke on the phone, the call
went for a little longer lol. But one of my cousins tells
me she&#x27;d mention that first phone call from time to time.
For months, maybe years, I gather. It must have meant a
lot to her, even though my cousin would call her all the
time. After she passed away, it feels like that one
little phone call, and the subsequent call that proved
she knew how to talk on the phone (lol), had a lot of
something loaded onto it. Something: love, meaning,
intention, effort, care, the unspoken energy that binds
you to someone regardless of transient factors like
distance and circumstance.

This morning, I emailed my auntie to wish her a happy
birthday. The email bounced. I tried texting, but who
knows what the deal is with international SMS in Old
Country. WhatsApp is THE communication medium over there,
and I stopped and had a good think about connection to
family versus excising Meta from my life as much as I
can. And then I remembered the phone.

And then I called my auntie. It&#x27;s her 70th birthday
today. She had a chuckle over cheeky plans for spending
it how she wants to. It was so good to hear her voice.

And then I called my sister, because it was easier to
talk rather than type, and I knew she&#x27;d be fine with a
short call. (Tho we ended up talking for 3x as long as I
expected cos there was so much to say lol.)

I can almost see a future without this phone barrier in
it, perhaps even without some of my long-held social
anxieties too. Maybe all I need are rules and boundaries
that radiate outwards from myself, rather than inwards
from social expectation or easy digital workarounds.

All I have to do is set those rules and stick to them.
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://rawtext.club/1/~xiu/phlog/2023-04-29-screen-time.txt</link>
<title>2023-04-29 Screen time</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
!Screen time
---
rawtext.club:70/~xiu
2023-04-29
Boorloo/Perth, Western Australia
---
I get a lot of screen time by virtue of my work and
hobbies. So when a day like yesterday comes along, where
I&#x27;m just hanging out with my mum, window shopping, thrift
shop shopping, chit-chatting and barely looking at my
phone, I feel quite good by the end of it. My eyes don&#x27;t
feel as tired as they do on other days.

The rest of me still feels pretty tired. I have a bad
habit of forgetting to snack and hydrate when I hang out
with my folks, but that&#x27;s something to work on next.

Generally, I&#x27;ve been minding the time I spend with a
screened digital device. Not necessarily to cut back,
more to raise the bar for what makes it worth having all
that light blasting my retinas. Gaming is of value, but
not just any game, and even if a game is deemed worthy,
it&#x27;s only worthy for a time -- when it no longer sparks
joy, I thank it for its service and exit the program.

Lovely personal emails are of value, but once they cross
a certain threshold of lovely and personal and regular
and interesting, I&#x27;ve been getting the urge to go
analogue, write and send by hand and post, instead of by
keyboard and cable. My beloved Kaweco Perkeo and newly
beloved sharpened 2B pencils are a sensory joy to write
with. Until the hand cramp starts, but still!

Reading on a screen isn&#x27;t so bad, but since returning to
paper books[1], I&#x27;ve much preferred this way to consume
words. So much so that I still have not felt motivated to
hack my ebook reader[2], since there are so many nice
physical books to pick up. I have been going around
buying books at library and charity sales, swapping books
at little free libraries and &quot;take one, leave one&quot;
baskets in local stores and cafes. There are so many
here. I wonder if this neighbourhood has other people
like me who do this, or if it&#x27;s only hashtag-authentic.

But yes, my book piles are growing. &quot;Date night&quot;
sometimes consists of a big feed and a trip to a local
bookstore. I could not have afforded this in my 20s and
30s (for reasons other than avocado toast, thanks), but
being older, partnered, and living at a calmer pace means
a bit of both pennies and mental bandwidth to let more
books into my life. Having physical book reading as one
of my default hobbies has been very helpful for becoming
less of a screenface.

I feel like it would be good to have another 1-2
screenless hobbies set aside as well, especially when
games can exert such a heavy pull at times. Such
obsessions are short-term for me, so it&#x27;s fine (and often
useful) to ride it out, but it feels risky to take this
for granted without a bit of exploration first. What is a
hobby that offers similar obligation-free engagement?
Everything on the NoSurf Activity List[3] seems like more
work (I have enjoyed most of those hobbies in the past
and can confirm they do feel like work lol).

Today it occurred to me that maybe housework could be
fun. Let me explain...

Housework is just tasks. Repetitive tasks like games are,
except they become &quot;work&quot; by virtue of the pressure we
put on ourselves to do them when there are other things
we feel like doing instead. &quot;Feel like&quot; is a loose term;
it can mean wanting to or feeling like you have to. With
gaming, recreation and entertainment positioned as a
normal way to relax and unwind, of course housework seems
like a chore. We are obliged to relax in sanctioned,
normalised ways. Housework is the obstacle.

So, then, what happens if you flick the psychological
switch that says you can relax however you bloody well
want to? If you take the pressure and obligation away
from housework, and remove the normalisation of only
certain activities counting as relaxation, could you make
a game from the mundane upkeep of life? It&#x27;s less sexy,
but then so is OpenTTD compared to League of Legends, but
I&#x27;d argue OpenTTD is still more enjoyable to play.

So, recreational housework then. Maybe that&#x27;s a hobby
worth exploring.

[1] gopher://rawtext.club/0/~xiu/phlog/2022-11-25-persnickety-paper-books.txt
[2] gopher://rawtext.club/0/~xiu/phlog/2023-03-18-nophone-projectfail-birdstuff.txt
[3] https://nosurf.net/activity-list
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://rawtext.club/1/~xiu/phlog/2023-04-07-five-questions.txt</link>
<title>2023-04-07 christyotwisty's Five Questions April 2023</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
!christyotwisty&#x27;s Five Questions April 2023
-
rawtext.club:70/~xiu
2023-04-07
Boorloo/Perth, Western Australia
-
Answering christyotwisty&#x27;s Five Questions[1] for this month:

1. What is your most memorable recent dream?

Recently, I dreamt I was about to eat a delicious cake
made of ham, but of course woke up before getting to
taste it. Food dreams are so disappointing in that way,
but leave behind nice memories of what could have been.

2. What instantly improves a sub-par day?

Nothing quite like solutions to the problems causing
sub-parity, but if there&#x27;s nothing to be done about them,
I like a nice dinner, nice cup of tea, good book or game,
and a cuddle.

3. Is there an uncommon, little-known, wellness or beauty
   hack you use?

I don&#x27;t know if there&#x27;s a proper term for it, but I call
it &quot;wet breathing&quot;. It&#x27;s helpful when you feel that
uncomfortable itch/tickle in the roof of your mouth that
often precedes a sinus infection or head cold.

Imagine you&#x27;re snoring/snorting, but breathe out slowly
and gently, pushing warm wet air through your sinuses. It
helps keep the sinus cavity humid, which I guess helps
maintain the protective lining that keeps out bad bugs.

It&#x27;s not a fix-all, but I&#x27;ve often avoided getting sick
with this trick. I think of it like a little buff that
tips the odds in your favour if you&#x27;re borderline during
dry air season.

4. What is something that feels embarassing but
   shouldn&#x27;t?

Being corrected in public. It shouldn&#x27;t feel embarassing,
but it triggers the physiological responses even when I&#x27;m
rationally fine with it. Based on discussions in therapy,
I suspect this kind of thing can stem from hypercritical
parenting or from spending too long in environments where
one lacks a safe space to make mistakes and learn from
them. It&#x27;s funny how our minds and bodies get shaped by
the experiences we have, and yet we still place so much
pressure on ourselves to be less X or be more Y.

5. If you live in a small space, how do you responsibly
   discard or recycle excess items?

Up until recently I lived in a tiny apartment for
several years, during which time I would try to rehome as
much as I could. Hand-me-down tech to family and friends
who could get value out of them. Worn-out clothing would
get recycled into cleaning cloths or remade into other
clothes. Household items, especially unusual things,
went to my local area&#x27;s Buy Nothing FB group. A lot of
stuff also went to goodwill.

[1] gopher://sdf.org/0/users/christyotwisty/phlog/2023-April-Five-Questions.txt
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://rawtext.club/1/~xiu/phlog/2023-04-02-crisis-of-creative-existence.txt</link>
<title>2023-04-02 Crisis of creative existence</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
!Crisis of creative existence
-
rawtext.club:70/~xiu
2023-04-04
Boorloo/Perth, Western Australia
-
Sometimes I think I don&#x27;t want to write anymore. Seven
years ago, I wanted to write stories and publish books
and settle into a long-term creative career. But now that
I&#x27;m a little ways in, some things don&#x27;t feel like they
fit. This job comes with certain practicalities that
complicate the work -- like contracts, marketing,
sensitivity readers, beta readers, public discourse.

I&#x27;m not opposed to any of these things, but they do make
me question if the feeling of reward I get at the end of
it all is worth the energy I spend on it. And if I do a
decent job of it, what difference does it really make to
anyone?

I feel the &#x27;greater purpose&#x27; of creative work and
knowledge work are two-fold:

1. To soften the edges of the human condition, and
2. To proliferate ideas and attitudes that motivate us to
build a world that&#x27;s better than before.

During the COVID heyday, my &quot;purpose&quot; as a writer was to
help shift the narrative towards compassion, community
and nuanced thinking. The villain is the system that
treats people like pawns or possessions. On-page
antagonists reveal at least a smidge of humanity and
struggle. Relationships are complex, emotions are
nuanced, happy endings are about hope and perseverence
rather than something to take for granted.

But honestly, what difference does it make? The industry
is full of writers who write this way, and do it way
better than I do. Heck, I read their work and love it,
and they probably feel amazing when their books finally
launch after all the hard work they put in.

I don&#x27;t know if I write that well. I don&#x27;t know if I feel
that amazing after crossing the finish line. It feels
nice absolutely... but does it feel nice enough?

I love writing. I love crafting words and shaping
stories. I love playing with book cover designs and
typesetting my ebooks. I love doing illustrations and
building dinky microsites for webfiction and all those
other little fun buildy constructy things.

Maybe it was a mistake to try doing any of those things
&#x27;professionally&#x27;. Not a mistake for others, but a mistake
for me. The process doesn&#x27;t shine the way it used to, and
having to prepare it for public consumption --
especially the consuming public of today -- stokes a
weird kind of emptiness inside me.

And it just gets worse when I think about the
environmental impact of all this. My ebook -- and every
redundant cloud-stored copy of it -- will live in an
air-conditioned data centre until potentially the end of
time. Hooray for recyclable, somewhat-compostable
paperbacks where the carbon is already captured (maybe!),
but then shipping, production, and all of that.

I got this same feeling when I thought I wanted to paint
on canvas, or sew accessories, or crochet clothing and
toys, or make websites for a living. I follow the
aspirations to their logical end and can&#x27;t help but see
myself as yet another widget factory in a world already
full of widgets. Just because some economic system
decided this is how we shall live.

Writing and creative work does bring me joy, but maybe
not the flavour of joy that&#x27;s right for now. But then,
what if this is just fear talking while I&#x27;m in the midst
of testing and revision for my next book?

The point is I don&#x27;t know. But I&#x27;ve been doing this long
enough now that I have enough experience to weigh up
against some of my ideals. Might make some time soon to
think about it properly.

There aren&#x27;t many people in my life and professional
circles I can talk to about this, so thank you for
reading.
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://rawtext.club/1/~xiu/phlog/2023-03-18-nophone-projectfail-birdstuff.txt</link>
<title>2023-03-18 No-phone bedtime, project setback, bird stuff</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
!No-phone bedtime, project setback, bird stuff
-
rawtext.club:70/~xiu
2023-03-18
Boorloo/Perth, Western Australia
-
# Going to bed without my phone

Lately I have been going to bed without my phone on the
bedside table and it has been great. Except sometimes it
is not. I miss having easy access to the time and my
crosswords app, and it used to be nice to wind down by 
reading stuff on gopher and gemini.

But whether or not it&#x27;s something I&#x27;m happy with,
I feel it&#x27;s useful to stick with this awhile longer in
order to weaken the synaptic connections driving my
habits and urges, so I can decide with clearer
perspective whether this is something to continue.

It has been harder to fall asleep at night. Not sure if
this is related or just a coincidence. I&#x27;m thinking
coincidence, as we are in an equinox season now, which
always seems to fuck with my sleep. It seems there&#x27;s
never a good way to properly experiment with stuff
because there always so many factors involved and
conditions always seem to be changing. Oh well! I&#x27;m not
a labcoat person doing labcoat stuff. Whatever is working
is working for now.

## Project setback: Kindle dumbification

My Kindle dumbification[1] is not off to a smooth start,
because I&#x27;m on the 5.14.3 firmware. Last year, Amazon
released an update that would make &quot;fix the
vulnerabilities&quot; allowing &quot;hackers&quot; to jailbreak their
device.

Imagine making your hardware less customisable for the
people who paid good money to own it. Then imagine
referring to those people as if they&#x27;re filthfolk trying
to do something shady, just because they want to
customise the way they use their personal property. Now
imagine what kind of bhole company actually does this in
real life.

In the interest of making lemonade from lemons, I&#x27;m
working up the courage to try two things: 1) a different
software method that claims to work on any firmware, and
2) some hardware hack with the whole soldering and
rooting shebang. Can I admit now I have a fear of
soldering irons and heated tools, which stems from a fear
of fire I&#x27;ve had since childhood?

## Bird stuff

This morning there was a flock of New Holland honeyeaters
flitting and twitting outside our house. I love hearing 
the crazy birdsong where we live. It&#x27;s so grounding
and reminds me that life is more than internet and tasks
and greedy corporations and the hellish screaming of a 
cat who can&#x27;t tell how loud she&#x27;s being.

When I can slow down and broaden my scope of focus, I
feel a lot more capable and less heaped-upon, and
grateful for what I do have. Not complacent. Complacency
happens when I am too overloaded to care. But those
precious, fleeting, stop-and-smell-the-roses moments
leave me recharged and with capacity to go and do the 
next thing that must be done.

Yeah, I love birds. They&#x27;re so weird and cute and smart
in ways I can&#x27;t fathom. You know that silly question 
that often comes up: &quot;What&#x27;s your ideal date?&quot; I think 
mine would be a nature birdy walk--binoculars, field 
guide, packed sandwich, and such--followed by a quiz 
night and small batch stout/IPA at a pub. Then, you 
know, home for computer games because the contrast and 
balance keep life interesting.

[1] gopher://rawtext.club:70/0/~xiu/phlog/2022-12-19-projects-not-goals.txt
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://rawtext.club/1/~xiu/phlog/2023-03-11-cal-newport-slow-productivity.txt</link>
<title>2023-03-11 Cal Newport's "slow productivity"</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
!Cal Newport&#x27;s &quot;slow productivity&quot;
-
rawtext.club:70/~xiu
2023-03-11
Boorloo/Perth, Western Australia
-
I&#x27;m a new but pretty keen follower of Cal Newport&#x27;s work.
His book DIGITAL MINIMALISM caught me at a particularly
strugglesome time last year. It was weeks after I began
my departure from social media[1], I had just about dealt
with the initial jitters and weird physical reactions to
quitting, and just finished Oliver Burkeman&#x27;s FOUR
THOUSAND WEEKS: TIME MANAGEMENT FOR MORTALS.

Anyway, before the smolweb helped me think long-term
about what I wanted to learn and accomplish, DIGITAL
MINIMALISM helped me reshape my relationship with my
phone, the internet, and other technologies. I&#x27;ve been a
fan of Newport&#x27;s work ever since and am very excited
about the book he&#x27;s currently working on, called SLOW
PRODUCTIVITY.

In a video[2] on TheDeepLife.com[3], he suggests slow
productivity is comprised of a three-pronged approach to
work:

1. Do fewer things
2. Work at a natural pace
3. Obsess over quality

He looks to hunter-gatherer communities to understand
what productivity meant to our ancestors[4], and found
that they tended to perform highly skilled work at a
natural pace with breaks throughout the day (such as
hunters resting through the hottest part of the day,
which coincided with when animals would be resting).

The idea is that adopting a slowly productive lifestyle
means we can still satisfy our creative human urges
while operating at a healthy pace and producing high
quality output.

This really appeals to me as someone who has lost count
of how many times I&#x27;ve hit burnout, the consequences of
which are notably amplified by being on Team
Neurodiversity[5].

Admittedly, there are times I wonder whether it was
better when I didn&#x27;t know about ND and all the things
that come along with it, but I was also younger then and
more ready/able to carry on like everything was fine.

But they weren&#x27;t fine then and they&#x27;re not fine now.
Society in general has a problematic relationship with
productivity. It&#x27;s sometimes tempting to think of it as
an &quot;American hypercapitalism&quot; culture problem, but
Australia&#x27;s got its own flavour of it too. The culture of
&quot;soldier on&quot; and even that bit of workplace martyrdom
probably stems from the same rhizome.

The notion of slow productivity seems from the outset
like a possible solution to burnout, a way to have fun
and do meaningful stuff without killing oneself over it.
So, yeah, don&#x27;t take this as a sales pitch, but damn, I
am excited to read this book whenever it comes out.
Sounds like it won&#x27;t be for ages, thought, which is
rather appropriate when you think about it.

[1]
gopher://rawtext.club/~xiu/phlog/2022-08-30-archive-weaning-off-social.txt
[2] https://invidious.esmailelbob.xyz/zZwPyB20lxg?rel=0&amp;autoplay=1&amp;t=1
[3] https://thedeeplife.com
[4] https://www.newyorker.com/culture/office-space/lessons-from-the-deep-history-of-work
[5] https://www.removepaywall.com/https:/www.nytimes.com/2021/09/03/well/live/autistic-burnout-advice.html
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://rawtext.club/1/~xiu/phlog/2023-02-28-little-wins.txt</link>
<title>2023-02-28 Little wins</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
!Little wins
-
rawtext.club:70/~xiu
2023-02-28
Boorloo/Perth, Western Australia
-
Some little wins I am quietly celebrating in my head.

# Finding a refurbished bookshelf

When we decided we needed a bookshelf to store our stray
books, I was worried we&#x27;d end up buying a drab behemoth
from a retail outlet at the end of a don&#x27;t-care supply
chain. Instead, we stumbled into a local shop run by two
guys who restore old furniture, and purchased a shelf
that was handmade in the 1960s right here in WA. It was
designed and crafted with love, and refurbished with
care. It comes from the circular economy and I am happy
we were able to do this.

# Getting a boomer end-user onto FOSS software

A boomer-aged person in the family is in the midst of a
career pivot, and Microsoft Office is an expense they&#x27;d
rather not have to cover. So I sent them a link to
LibreOffice, which they immediately adopted into their
workflow. I&#x27;m very chuffed about this because this person
is a non-technical but very enthusiastic end-user of
technology. This is a needs-must problem that FOSS
software is solving[1]. I hope it helps shift the attitude
away from Big Tech brands being the be-all-and-end-all of
software options.

# Drafting again after a break

Our trip to Eora/Sydney[2] meant a big break from the
manuscript I&#x27;m working on. I was worried after
yesterday&#x27;s distractable and abysmal return to the task
(only 300+ words), but decided to be kind to myself and
attend to my &quot;energies&quot; as per the &quot;Full Engagement&quot;
approach to work. Today, I smashed out 1000+ words in two
sessions without having to try too hard. All I needed was
a little clearway so I could focus without so many noises
in my head. Night Traveler&#x27;s album[3], DREAMS YOU DON&#x27;T
FORGET, was my soundtrack. It was perfect.

# Questions

What wins have you had recently?
What do they mean to you?

[1] gopher://rawtext.club:70/0/~xiu/phlog/2022-10-12-pondering-desires-choices.txt
[2] gopher://rawtext.club:70/0/~xiu/phlog/2023-02-16-vivobook-on-the-road.txt
[3] gopher://rawtext.club:70/0/~xiu/phlog/2023-02-27-just-gopher.txt
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://rawtext.club/1/~xiu/phlog/2023-02-27-just-gopher.txt</link>
<title>2023-02-27 Just gopherholing now</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
!Just gopherholing now
-
rawtext.club:70/~xiu
2023-02-27
Boorloo/Perth, Western Australia
-
Recently, I made a list of all the projects and regular
tasks I am minding. By &quot;all&quot; I mean &quot;not all&quot; because
it was restricted to work-related activities.

There are too many things. AKA. there are many things
that could be merged so there are fewer things.

Tonight, I moved my smol.pub[1] gemlog entries to this
phlog[3]. I like reading stuff on gemini, and really like
smol.pub, but don&#x27;t need to maintain two logs on the
small internet. Just this quiet nothing-nobody gopherhole
is perfectly fine.

## Miscellaneous life notes

* I have started buying music instead of just streaming
  it. It feels good for a bunch of reasons, not least of
  which feeling less dependent on a subscription-based
  service that I&#x27;ve just learned doesn&#x27;t pay artist
  royalties very well.

* Finished CHOKEPOINT CAPITALISM by Rebecca Giblin and
  Cory Doctorow last week. Totally blew my mind how big
  business has all but imprisoned our culture. Definitely
  worth a read for anyone who creates art, written works,
  music, and video.

* Warm today. Max 37, min 21. Still light after 7pm in
  late February.

[1] gemini://xiu.smol.pub
[2] gopher://rawtext.club:70/1/~xiu/phlog/2022
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://rawtext.club/1/~xiu/phlog/2023-02-21-shopping-guilt.txt</link>
<title>2023-02-21 Shopping guilt</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
!Shopping guilt
-
rawtext.club:70/~xiu
2023-02-21
Eora/Sydney, New South Wales
-
Walked through Sydney yesterday with the objective of
doing some &quot;utility shopping&quot;. AKA our attempt at doing
laundry failed and some stocks of essential clean clothes
may not last us until we make it home.

In recent years, spending time in retail precincts,
especially when surrounded by big-name single-brand
stores, has been giving me a deep sense of discomfort. A
sibling recently revealed they get this too, so I don&#x27;t
feel as weird about it as I did in the early stages of
noticing the feeling.

Surrounded by shelves of nice things that used to bring
me joy, a little non-hallucinatory voice in my head
asks all sorts of unnerving questions:

 * How well fed was the person who made this product?

 * How much carbon did this cost?

 * What is the nicely copywritten &quot;made with traceable
   cotton&quot; label not telling me?

 * Other than adding a rainbow to their marketing, what
   is this brand actually contributing to the LGBTQI+
   movement?

This probably comes across like one big virtue signal,
but maybe it doesn&#x27;t matter. It&#x27;s on my mind and it&#x27;s
troublesome, but I&#x27;d rather think on it than not.

Except that thinking about it so much in the store made
me forget to buy undies and so here we are.
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://rawtext.club/1/~xiu/phlog/2023-02-19-offline-love-fear.txt</link>
<title>2023-02-19 Offline loves and fears</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
!Offline loves and fears
-
rawtext.club:70/~xiu
2023-02-19
Eora/Sydney, New South Wales
-
Today we went for an almost three-hour hike on elevated
country. I&#x27;ve not had an easy way to charge my fruitwatch
while on this trip, and have been quite happy to leave
home without it even though it means not having hike
stats afterwards. It wasn&#x27;t my Siri piping up every now
and then with unsolicited &quot;split pace&quot; reports, which I
felt a bit smug about -- promise I&#x27;m not judging
anyone here; I just feel a little accomplished about
having overcome a habit.

I realised when we got home that my phone had gotten
stuck in Panorama camera mode while in the backpack. It
was hot to touch and the battery was nearly flat, so I
left our Airbnb without it. It&#x27;s concerning how weird it
feels to go out without a phone. We just went for dinner
and a movie, but over the course of the evening, these
were the feelings I registered:

 * The urge to pick up my device and text my mum.

 * Guilt at not responding to new texts in group chat.

 * An overall fear that people are generally mad at me
   for not replying to texts more quickly.

 * Relief at the futility of this guilt/fear because it&#x27;s
   not like I could do anything about it in the moment
   anyway.

 * Frustration at being trapped in a culture that sees us
   so tied to our devices and being &#x27;always on&#x27;.

 * Paranoia that without this culture, I would lose
   connection to my loved ones.

Complicated, no?

Being offline-first while on this trip has been lovely. I
don&#x27;t feel overwhelmed by the amount of things to check
and read, even though I have a full-to-bursting inbox,
loads of articles in my feed reader, and oodles of
noodles in offpunk[1]. Something has taken the edge off
the old sense of urgency, at least for the time being.

At the same time, I realise it&#x27;s a bit of a cheat to call
this being &quot;offline-first&quot; because my travel companions
are all very online and I can just turn around and ask
them stuff. Perhaps it&#x27;s more correct to say
&quot;offlineish&quot;.

Speaking of which, it&#x27;s time to wind down before bed.
Good night, smolweb.

[1] gemini://rawtext.club/~ploum/2022-11-15-offpunk17-sourcehut.gmi
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://rawtext.club/1/~xiu/phlog/2023-02-16-vivobook-on-the-road.txt</link>
<title>2023-02-16 Vivobook on the road</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
!Vivobook on the road
-
rawtext.club:70/~xiu
2023-02-16
Eora/Sydney, New South Wales
-
Offline multiple-IMAP Mutt is finally up and running on
my little Vivobook[1]. It&#x27;s not exaggerating to say I was
anxious about setting it up. Although I am willing to
tweak and play with tech, I get nervous about bricking
devices. Possibly an irrational fear from having spent so
much time with devices by manufacturers who&#x27;d rather
people don&#x27;t look beneath the chassis.

Anyway, the need to travel arose, so I put my big bitch
pants on and made it happen. My setup is isync/mbsync +
msmtp + folder-hooks, and I&#x27;m proud of not just following
verbatim a bunch of tutorials. I actually exercised some
critical thinking and adapted the steps to my own
situation. Enduserness--; Confidence++

This little project did good things to my brain. I
remember learning this is how email works back in the
good old days of POP3 and Eudora. But over the many years
of using Outlook, Gmail, webmail and mobile devices
designed like toys, I&#x27;d just... forgotten.

Beyond the protocols, email is just text and files and
the programs that read them. It&#x27;s not some untouchable
proprietary magic -- even though it sounds like some Big
Tech players are trying to turn it into that.

Oh, and while this was in the works, I also stumbled upon
how to customise the little status bar at the bottom of
the screen. Yeah, okay, OLD NEWS to anyone reading
this, but I didn&#x27;t expect something as modular as
i3status to even exist let alone be so straightforward to
customise. So, I was impressed. Is this just what Linux
life is like? I feel so empowered!

Anyway, here we are in Eora/Sydney for a few days. This
laptop is an 11&quot; banger and under 1kg. My backpack feels
SO LIGHT, even with three paper books in there (a
journal, a planner, and a novel) as well. So I&#x27;m like,
double-stoked.

Okay, it&#x27;s only day 1 on the road with the Vivobook.
Things could still go tits up. But tonight, I&#x27;m feeling
pretty good about it.

[1] gopher://rawtext.club/0/~xiu/phlog/2023-01-15-permacomputing-manjaro-i3-asus-vivobook.txt 
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://rawtext.club/1/~xiu/phlog/2023-01-28-book-release-concerns.txt</link>
<title>2023-01-28 Book release concerns</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
!Book release concerns
-
rawtext.club:70/~xiu
2023-01-28
Boorloo/Perth, Western Australia
-
In Q4 of this year, I&#x27;ll be releasing my first
novel-length book. This is the time where a writer 
in my position should be thinking about how to
effectively promote their product and make sales.

But I read about the carbon costs[1-3] associated with
ebooks (device manufacturing, data storage), the carbon
costs associated with physical books (production,
shipping), the general climate impact of e-commerce and
digital marketing, and so on and so forth... And it now
feels like someone&#x27;s taken an ice-cream scoop and dug out
the part of me that would normally get excited about an
upcoming launch.

[1] https://theconversation.com/weighing-the-environmental-costs-buy-an-ereader-or-a-shelf-of-books-8331
[2] https://bookriot.com/carbon-footprint-of-publishing/
[3] https://theecoguide.org/books-vs-ebooks-protect-environment-simple-decision

I&#x27;m sure the conventional worries around my book not
selling also make it easy to cling to that sortof
narrative as well, as a way to avoid having to think
about it. It&#x27;s kind of like experiencing fear at both
ends of a spectrum. If my book doesn&#x27;t sell, I will be
sad. If my book does sell, I will be sad.

One thing I don&#x27;t want to do is shut out the
environmental stuff on the basis of living in a
capitalist society. While this is true, and so it
wouldn&#x27;t be right to begrudge anyone poorer than a
billionaire making less environmental decisions on this
basis, one of my personal foundation stones is to explore
how someone might do things differently and what
conditions might make that work.

This matters to me. I&#x27;m buying into the idea that small
shifts in behaviour, en masse, can lead to bigger shifts
further down the track. Maybe that&#x27;s a bit of magical
thinking, since I&#x27;m not sure how. But it&#x27;s not too hard
to imagine, say, figuring out an approach that might do
less damage. Something one&#x27;s peers can adopt, thus as a
group multiplying the damage reduction overall.

# A potential strategy?

Something I&#x27;d like to try for this book is putting more
effort into making it available in libraries. This would
potentially maximise the use of any physical copies, and
make digital copies more easily affordable.

There&#x27;s a system here in Australia where writers and
publishers can register the lending rights for their
books and recoup a small royalty every time someone
borrows one of their titles from a public library. I
assume it&#x27;s a lot less than the royalty on a sale, but
what if it&#x27;s enough under the conditions I&#x27;m working
with?

I like the idea of finding out, and probably learning
something new.

# The &quot;maybe nots&quot;

Printing to inventory -- aside from this being way out
of my budget, print on demand seems like a more
economical and less wasteful option.

Social media advertising -- feels akin to giving
someone money to go and make someone else miserable.
That said, I&#x27;d still promote through indie networks that
include people who post on social media.

</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://rawtext.club/1/~xiu/phlog/2023-01-19-updates-pendings.txt</link>
<title>2023-01-19 Random updates, notes and pendings</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
!Random updates, notes and pendings
-
rawtext.club:70/~xiu
2023-01-19
Boorloo/Perth, Western Australia
-
I have been absent. Behind on emails and due to being
distracted with the Vivobook setup[1], returning to work,
migrating my files to something cheaper and more local,
and general life admin.

fluxion[2] talked me through an email setup recently,
which I plan to try as soon as I gather the courage to
try Mutt. Not having done so yet is pretty much the
reason for being behind.

I love the look of gef&#x27;s new digital garden[3]. It&#x27;s
so nicely realised even at such an early stage. Ps. Thank
you for the shoutout[4], gef.

Currently reading SUNBURNT COUNTRY by Joelle Gergis, all
about the history of Australian climate. TIL that the
Bibbulmun Noongar of Western Australia include an oral
record of the last Ice Age in their stories. That&#x27;s
pretty freaking amazing, though not a surprise for one of
the oldest continuing peoples in the world. 

Live and learn: The last two Royal Gala apples I&#x27;ve
bought have been not quite right on the inside. I wonder
if mid-January is already too late in the season for this
type of apple.  Pink Lady and Granny Smith have still
been nice.

My theme for this year is Deep Life and Slow
Productivity, and simply accepting that I will fall
behind on some things. Life goes on until it stops.

[1] gopher://rawtext.club:70/0/~xiu/phlog/2023-01-15-permacomputing-manjaro-i3-asus-vivobook.txt
[2] gemini://fluents.xyz
[3] gopher://sdf.org/1/users/gef/./garden/
[4] gopher://sdf.org/0/users/gef/./reflections/structure
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://rawtext.club/1/~xiu/phlog/2023-01-15-permacomputing-manjaro-i3-asus-vivobook.txt</link>
<title>2023-01-15 Permacomputing: Manjaro/i3 on an Asus Vivobook 2020</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
!Permacomputing: Manjaro/i3 on an Asus Vivobook 2020
-
rawtext.club:70/~xiu
2023-01-15
Boorloo/Perth, Western Australia
-
My second intentional permacomputing[1] project and first
proper Linux learning project[2] is getting Arch Linux on
a refurbished Asus Vivobook 2020.

This project has been a weird ride with lots of
metaphorical running into walls, but I don&#x27;t hate it and
every tiny bit of progress has felt very rewarding.

Pain points were (*still are):

 * Figuring out if Arch was the right choice
 * Getting my head around window manager vs desktop env
 * Removing default apps, installing my own
 * Figuring out how to copy files from my main machine
 * Configuring my environment
 * Making programs open without locking up my terminal window
 * Connect to Rawtext.club

Here&#x27;s how it went:

1. Arch turned out not to be the right choice. I found
   out what &quot;rolling release&quot; actually means, and realised
   I&#x27;m just not technical enough to deal with untested
   updates. Manjaro popped up as the tested-updates version
   of Arch, and it comes with a community-built package with
   the i3 window manager[3] instead of a full DE.

   To be honest, I still don&#x27;t understand the difference. i3
   has a bottom bar with the time, date and other info like
   the OSX status bar. There was a wallpaper background that
   loaded by default. And when I type mod+d, it opens
   something called a dmenu (?) where I can search for apps
   the way OSX&#x27;s mod+space let me do. So it&#x27;s still
   spiritually the same thing, kinda. Am I a heathen for
   saying this, or is it actually good news from an end user
   perspective because switching would be less of a leap?

   Note: I wanted something Arch-based because I really like
   their wiki. Yeah, that&#x27;s probably silly, but it&#x27;s really
   nice having good documentation while trying to learn.
   There aren&#x27;t a lot of people I can ask for help with this
   stuff, so accessible self-study materials is important to
   me.

2. Manjaro/i3 comes with the Pale Moon browser and
   configs for other browsers that aren&#x27;t installed. It took
   me awhile to figure out how to use the AUR (Arch User
   Repository)[4], how to avoid haivng to use the AUR
   directly by installing a helper called Yay[5], then
   getting my head around the difference between building a
   package and installing a binary. That&#x27;s ten minutes of my
   life I&#x27;m never getting back, but now LibreWolf is
   running just fine instead of Pale Moon.

3. Copying from OSX to Manjaro is a poo. My short-term
   solution was to reformat a thumbdrive to FAT32. My
   long-term solution has been to sign up for a pCloud
   account and use their folder sync feature.

4. Configuring my environment and making programs run the
   way I want them to is a work in progress. So far, I&#x27;ve
   managed to:

   * Change my terminal style by editing ~/.Xresources
   * Remove the default wallpaper (but forgotten how)
   * Make pCloud open on startup using an `exec` call in
     ~/.ie/config with --no-startup-id (no need to open
     terminal)
   * Manually run a program from terminal, but have it
     open in the background so I can keep using that
     terminal window: `&lt;app_path&gt; &gt; /dev/null 2&gt;&amp;1 &amp;`

5. The experience of trying to connect to Rawtext.club
   was painful. For starters, I couldn&#x27;t just ssh-add my key
   like on OSX, I have to `eval &quot;$(ssh-agent)&quot;` first for
   reasons I still don&#x27;t get. Only then can I ssh-add.

   Then after connecting, I couldn&#x27;t run certain functions
   because RTC couldn&#x27;t recognise my terminal. Turns out
   when you SSH to a server, the server uses info about your
   terminal to figure out how to render stuff (or something
   like that), and Manjaro/i3&#x27;s default URxvt wasn&#x27;t being
   picked up. Eventually after a lot of confused
   best-guessing of search keywords, I landed on adding
   `export TERM=&#x27;xterm-256color` to my profile dotfile on
   the remote server. RTC worked a treat after that.

So, why a second laptop, you ask? My partner has taken
over the Bodhi machine with plans to learn Linux too.
They are otherwise very embedded in a BigTech ecosystem,
so this feels like a win for broadening horizons.

I&#x27;m very happy with an 11&quot; machine. At just under 1kg,
it&#x27;s comfortable to carry around and fits nicely on my
lap. Manjaro runs very snappy, although to be fair when I
first booted up this machine, Windows 10 ran pretty
snappy too. We&#x27;ll see what happens as it ages and
accumulates more cruft.

[1] gopher://rawtext.club:70/0/~xiu/phlog/2022-09-23-permacomputing-early-thoughts.txt
[2] gopher://rawtext.club:70/0/~xiu/phlog/2022-11-19-new-machine-thoughts.txt
[3] https://i3wm.org
[4] https://aur.archlinux.org
[5] https://github.com/Jguer/yay
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://rawtext.club/1/~xiu/phlog/2023-01-04-five-questions.txt</link>
<title>2023-01-04 christyotwisty's Five Questions January 2023</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
!christyotwisty&#x27;s Five Questions January 2023
-
rawtext.club:70/~xiu
2023-01-04
Boorloo/Perth, Western Australia
-
1. What are you grateful for from 2022?

  2022 was the year I reviewed my relationship with
  digital technology. I quit &quot;social media&quot; and sought to
  explore and nurture my friendships and relationships
  away from the platforms where they&#x27;d developed.

  Where too-easy communication may leave one unsure if a
  friendship is real or simply convenient, moving to a mode
  of higher friction not only tests and distinguishes,
  but also seems to strengthen genuine bonds.

  I am grateful for the connections that proved true.

2. Has the internet changed the way you think?

  Yes, and I&#x27;ll stick with a short answer for now,
  because there&#x27;s a lot to unpack and I&#x27;m not ready for it.

3. What do you believe is true though you cannot prove it?

  That capitalism has been an experiment gone wrong and
  is making us miserable. I feel we can still have nice
  things that resemble parts of capitalism, but the way
  it&#x27;s set up right now is very broken. I can&#x27;t prove
  this and I don&#x27;t know enough to go into detail; it&#x27;s
  just a sense.

4. What have you changed your mind about and why? If
possible, use an example from 2022.

  That the world is a dreamy, lovely place and the stuff
  that&#x27;s wrong with it are just blips that will sort
  themselves out in the end.

  I realise now that while the world can be dreamy and
  lovely, the bad stuff is an ever-encroaching entropy.
  Lovely is not assured and we are not entitled to it.
  We must exercise custodianship of it.

5. What would you like to return to?

  Guaranteeing no creepy monkey-hand backfire
  implications here, I wish I could return to five years
  ago and reassure myself not to lose faith in
  homesteading just because we moved to a shoebox
  apartment. We have a garden and proper kitchen now, and
  I feel the part of my brain that once appreciated this
  has atrophied. It will take a lot of work to
  neuroplasticise a way back there.

BONUS: Things to love in life

  1. The smell of a village high street lined with
     eateries at dinner time.

  2. Hyperfocus on the preparation of caraway-spiced
     coffee in a French press.

  3. The gentle brush of a rain-drenched rosemary sprig
     across one&#x27;s cheek.
</pre>]]></description>

<item>
<link>gopher://rawtext.club/1/~xiu</link>
<title>^back to ~xiu</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
~xiu@rawtext.club
:*~*:._.:*~*:._.:

Writer. Recovering coder/designer/biginternetter. 
Likes long walks through musty bookshops and cats 
who attach themselves to your hip in the wee hours
of the morning.

Email x1v at posteo dot net
or ~ me at the Midnight Pub.

&lt;a href=gopher://rawtext.club/1/~xiu/phlog/&gt;a stitch in time (my phlog)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=gopher://rawtext.club/1/~xiu/garden/&gt;garden notes &amp; stuff&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;a href=gopher://rawtext.club/1/~xiu/pharden/&gt;Experimental pharden&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=gopher://rawtext.club/0/~xiu/reasons-to-bicycle.txt&gt;Reasons to use a bicycle&lt;/a&gt;

Mirrors:
&lt;a href=gopher://rawtext.club/0/~xiu/fivestarcottage.txt&gt;Five-Star Cottage (JL Peridot)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=gopher://rawtext.club/0/~xiu/litanyagainstfear.txt&gt;Litany Against Fear (Dune)&lt;/a&gt;

Elsewhere:
&lt;a href=gopher://gopher.judges119.me/1/&gt;Az&#x27;s Gopher Server&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=gopher://interns.scorpinc.solutions/1/&gt;Scorpinc interns CYOA&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=gopher://midnight.pub/1/&gt;Midnight Pub&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=gopher://i-logout.cz/1/bongusta&gt;Bongusta! phlog aggregator&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=gopher://rawtext.club/1/&gt;Rawtext.club&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=gopher://gopher.club/1/&gt;Gopher.club&lt;/a&gt;
___________________________________________________________________
                    Gophered by Gophernicus/3.1 on Arch/6.4 x86_64

</pre>]]></description>
</item>
</channel></rss>
