<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>gopher://tilde.club/1/~user18130814200115/posts</title>
<link>gopher://tilde.club/1/~user18130814200115/posts</link>

<item>
<link>gopher://tilde.club/1/~user18130814200115/posts/0035-the-pedantry-of-the-dutch-prolitariat.txt</link>
<title>0035-the-pedantry-of-the-dutch-prol   2025-Sep-10 11:40    10.7 KB</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
The pedantry of the Dutch proletariat
Wed, 10 Sep 2025
Language, Opinion
=====================================

Pedants can be found anywhere, and they take on a wide variety
of subjects towards which they direct their pedantry. One such
group which I have always found particularly frustrating are
Dutch language pedants. Folks who insist on `correcting&#x27;
`mistakes&#x27; made by other native speakers. While I have always
found these types frustrating, I have never spoken out against
them, as they are -- by-and-large -- well-educated and
respectable people. Now that I have finished the first half of
my masters in linguistics however, I feel both a right- and even
stronger need- to refute some of the points made by these
people.

Firstly, let me make clear who I am speaking about. I
intentionally use the term `pedants&#x27;. I do this not in an
attempt to demean or belittle this group of people, I do it
simply out of a desire to be precise. Many of those who fall
under this term might rather be called grammarians, linguists,
language-lovers, or the like, but I contend that much of what
they maintain actually has very little to do with language at
all, let alone grammar.

To make this clear, let me give an example in English. I --
personally -- use the so-called ``oxford comma&#x27;&#x27; in my writing.
This means that, when I am listing several options, I will
separate them by commas INCLUDING a comma before the `and&#x27; or
`or&#x27;.

	We have apples, bananas, and strawberries on sale today

Amateur linguists (by which I mean self-styled linguists with no
formal education) sometimes mistakenly call this a grammatical
mistake (or otherwise a grammatical choice). It is however not,
at least not in the proper use of the term `grammar&#x27;. The oxford
comma is a style-choice, a matter of convention and etiquette.

Indeed when speaking about grammar and language, linguists tend
to -- in most cases -- ignore the written word. While there
certainly is interesting research to be done about the written
word, language is the organically arising SPOKEN WORD, which can
in-turn me written down, formalized, and changed. This leads me
nicely into my first point.

Spreektaal
----------

`Spreektaal&#x27; is a Dutch term which literally translates to
``spoken language&#x27;&#x27;. At the end of this section I hope to have
convinced you that this is something of an oxymoron. After all,
as I started before, language does not arise in its written form
but rather originates in sounds and/or gestures. `Spreektaal&#x27; is
therefore just `taal&#x27;, just language.

This term is primarily used to distinguish phrases and words
typical in spoken language from those which are acceptable in
written/formal language. As such, this is a matter of etiquette,
not of language (indeed much like the oxford comma). Some folk
indeed use the term MERELY in this way, others however take the
etiquette a step further and use it to talk down to those who
use it. ``Wat een verschikelijke spreektaal&#x27;&#x27; (``What horrid
spoken-language&#x27;&#x27;) they will say to their (invariably
lower-educated) interlocutor ``You can&#x27;t speak like that&#x27;&#x27;.

Let us recall the etymology of the word `etiquette&#x27;. Coming from
the French, it means literally `label&#x27; and was used to describe
a set of rules to which only the nobility were privy. You can
tell a serf from an aristocrat because the former will hold
their fork in the right hand rather than the left, raise a cup
of tea to their lips in a manner which is most comfortable to
them rather than with their little finger raised, and they won&#x27;t
cutesy with the right leg in front and extended. Such `labels&#x27;
were of course invented because -- at the end of the day --
there is no AUTHENTIC difference between the blue-bloods and the
rest of us. Instead the difference must be simulated with
clothing, etiquette, and language.

For indeed language was a part of this matter as well. The
peasantry spoke English while the nobility spoke French. Yet
another way of setting the elite apart from the unwashed masses.

Fast-forward to today and we find a perfectly capable Dutch
speaker. They grew up in an environment where a certain term or
phrase was common. They acquired this phrase and its
accompanying grammar as we all do as infants. At some point,
they will have formed a complete language (what Chomsky calls
their I-language) and -- lo-and-behold -- they can use it to
communicate with those around them, for they have an incredibly
similar grammar and lexicon.

Then the pedant shows up to tell them that there exists this
thing called ``Algemeen beschaafd Nederlands&#x27;&#x27; (general
civilized Dutch) and that it does not allow for certain
constructions this person has used their whole life. In fact,
this use of language is WRONG because the grammarians in Holland
laid out the law that is Dutch Grammar, and YOU DO NOT ADHERE TO
IT.

Wilde / Wou
-----------

One such point is the past-tense of the Dutch verb `willen&#x27;
(``to want&#x27;&#x27;). There is a roughly 50/50 split between those who
use the irregular `wou&#x27; and the regular `wilde&#x27;. Whether a
certain verb in one&#x27;s lexicon is marked as having irregular- or
regular- conjugation is a matter of acquisition. If you grow up
in an environment where the irregular is used, then that will be
how you acquire it, that will be your language, and that will be
correct.

According to the pedant however, the correct from is the
regular, because so spoke the grammarians who -- in all honestly
-- are simply describing the grammar of THEIR individual
languages/dialects.

```Daarom&#x27; is geen woord&#x27;&#x27;
--------------------------

Okay, before I start I must admit that this is really only said
by the most-amateur of self-styled-linguists. Certainly no
self-respecting language enthusiast would ever claim something
so ridiculous. The phrase above translates to ```Therefore&#x27; is
not a word&#x27;&#x27;. Translating it into English immediately shows the
ridiculousness of the statement, but let us first see the
argument.

In Dutch the word for `why&#x27; is `waarom&#x27;, which more literally
translated to `where-for&#x27;. To answer in response to a
why-question with `daarom&#x27; (`there-for&#x27; or `because of that&#x27;),
is simply an empty meaningless response, and since words must
have a meaning, `daarom&#x27; cannot be a word.

I won&#x27;t spend too much time on this matter and instead will
simply point out the following: `Daarom&#x27; DOES have a meaning, it
is simply context dependent. We see the English are completely
capable of using their equivalent `therefore&#x27;, likewise with the
Italian `perche&#x27;, without devolving into meaningless gibberish.
Secondly, words are added to dictionaries all the time even if
their meaning is fluid or yet to be established concretely. The
BBC aired a report recently on the addition of the word
`skibbidi&#x27; to the Cambride English dictionary. A spokesperson
for the dictionary admitted that the term can be used in various
ways: as a noun, adverb, or intensifier, to indicate approval or
disdain, or simply as a joke.

Merriam Webster seems to take the route of the pedants and
chooses to talk down to those who don&#x27;t speak the `proper&#x27;
English is conformity with the etiquette:

	Skibidi: A nonsense internet term
	~Merriam Webseter Online [1]

Gender
------

Now onto everyone&#x27;s favourite topic: grammatical gender. At
first glance, Dutch appears to have two genders: common and
neutral with two corresponding determiners `de&#x27; and `het&#x27;
respectively. Some grammarians and pedants like to insist that
Dutch in fact has three genders, since this was the case in Old
Dutch.

The difference between the male and female gender -- they
maintain -- exists, though it is entirely opaque. One simply
needs to learn the genders of all the words in the lexicon. This
is -- in my opinion -- one of the most egregious example of
Dutch language pedantry as it is still a rather widespread
sentiment, even in schools. Let me be clear: If an aspect of
spoken language (unrelated to etiquette or style) cannot be
acquired during the natal process of language acquisition, then
this aspect is NOT (or no-longer) an element of the language in
question.

Yes, Dutch did at some point have three genders, and it was only
proper to say ``Let nature go HER way&#x27;&#x27; and ``The girl climbed
out of HIS window&#x27;&#x27; (technically this last one is due to a
separate rule which I will leave aside for now), but this is
no-longer the case. Children growing up in a Dutch speaking
environment now make the distinction for the use of pronouns the
animate/inanimate difference. Inanimate nouns in the common
gender receive the same pronouns as neutral gender nouns, and
animate nouns get pronouns based on the gender of the individual
in question. No longer does one need to know that the cat `de
kat&#x27; is masculine and therefore refer to a female cat as `he&#x27;.

In all fairness, it seems that most dictionaries have started
removing the masculine/feminine distinction in favour of listing
these nouns as `common&#x27; gender, so perhaps we are making
progress on in this regard.

Hen/Hun
-------

Staying on the topic of referring to other entities. Dutch
(apparently) makes a distinction in the terms used to referring
to a direct-object and an indirect-object of a sentence. For the
former `Hun&#x27; is used while for the latter `Hen&#x27; is used[2].

... Or perhaps it is the other way around. This shows
immediately the problem with this grammatical rule (for it is
actually grammar this time): Native Dutch speakers have not
acquired this rule for some time. The process behind this
language-change is rather interesting and sadly outside of the
scope of this post. But the point stands that native speakers do
not have a `feel&#x27; for this distinction, our I-languages do not
allow for the distinction between direct- and indirect-objects.
Much like it only allows for two registers of formality, while
other languages allow for several. The Dutch of a century ago
did include a feel for this difference, but this has gradually
disappeared. Leaving us now in an awkward phase where some
insist on the distinction which others simply cannot make.


All of that is to say: the next time you intend to correct
someone&#x27;s use of language -- be it in Dutch or otherwise --
consider: Whether you are actually correcting language or rather
style, Whether it is possible that your interlocutor acquired a
slightly different dialect which is misaligned with yours, and
lastly, whether the correction matters for the purpose of
communication which is -- after all -- the aim of language.

-----------------------------------------------------------------

[1]: https://www.merriam-webster.com/slang/skibidi

[2]: There are also other cases where one is used over the other
     such as in propositional phrases.

All of my writing and software projects are available free of
charge under CC-BY unless stated otherwise. I do not accept
monetary donations, but if my work has brought you value I ask
you to donate to a charitable cause or high-impact fund,
organisation, business, institute, or individual driving moral
progress.
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://tilde.club/1/~user18130814200115/posts/0034-a-fresh-coat-of-paint.txt</link>
<title>0034-a-fresh-coat-of-paint.txt        2025-Aug-16 21:41     5.2 KB</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
A fresh coat of paint
Sat, 16 Aug 2025
Technology, Meta content
========================

If you read the web-based version of this blog, you might have
noticed that it has recently received a minor makeover. Instead
of the previous formatting in plain-text, there is now ACTUAL
formatting happening, paragraphs can be re-flowed to fit on
smaller screens, lines are actually lines and not just a bunch
of hyphens, there are actual headings which are picked up by
screenreaders, etcetera. 

If you read this blog on gopher, you should have noticed...
absolutely nothing. This post is about that.

-----------------------------------------------------------------

For those unfamiliar: Gopher is a protocol much like the Hyper
Text Transfer Protocol (http) which is used to serve this
web-page to you. However, instead of transferring hypertext
(HTML) which allows for formatting, re-flowing, and all the
other nice things mentioned in the introduction, the gopher
protocol transfers mostly plain text files.

When I started this blog up again, my main intention was to
start writing as soon as possible. As I mentioned in the first
post on this blog (The return of the blog), the program I wrote
to generate the front page was incredibly simple. I did not want
to spend time to make something complicated, I just wanted
something that worked. At the same time, I wanted to support
both gopher, web, and rss as targets. To achieve this (still:
without putting in much time so that I could start writing as
soon as possible). I just formatted plain text which gopher
could sever directly and then added VERY minimal html tags to
the web version which basically told the browser: don&#x27;t do
anything with this text, just show it as it is.

This approach was great, and it served its purpose in allowing
me to write. At the same time though, it was quite a bad reading
experience on smaller devices, and it did not allow for as much
creativity in styling as I liked.

As such, since I had some time this summer, I wrote a new
indexer which (amongst other improvements) added html tags to
the plain text files that I was (and still am) writing in. These
tell the browser where the paragraphs are, what is a heading and
what is normal text. It recognizes, quotations, code-snippets,
horizontal lines. It coverts the backticks and single-quotes I
write

	``like this&#x27;&#x27;

To properly curved left-double-quotes and right-double-quotes.

``Like this&#x27;&#x27;[1]

This post is to call out to other writers who target these
platforms that writing content which is nice to read for both
gopher AND the web is indeed possible. And it is possible even
if you don&#x27;t use and off-the-shelf solution such as markdown.
The important thing is that -- whatever formatting you use --
you have to be consistent with it.

I for example underlined headers in the text version with
hyphens for main headings and equals-signs for sub headings.
This made it incredibly trivial for a program to detect these
lines and add the relevant html tags to them.

Likewise, I always indent code blocks with tabs, and quotation
blocks with The greater-then symbol.

&gt; This allows for easy detection, processing, and subsequent
&gt; styling

	Insert code snippet here

All the while without affecting the formatting seen by gopher
readers.

This consistency in formatting allowed me to code up a
completely custom parser in just an afternoon.

That being said, I did have to make some minor adjustments to
some old posts. A rather funny bug was that if I had a paragraph
immediately following a horizontal line, the whole block would
be counted as a line, and the paragraph would not show up on the
web version. I decided to leave this in as a feature and just
move all paragraphs away from the horizontal lines instead.

-----------------------------------------------------------------
I can use this to write gopher-only paragraphs after all ;)

There were some other inconsistencies In my writing particularly
when it came to lists. I decided (since it was much much easier
to program this way) that all lists should henceforth be
indented. This was a minor change since I don&#x27;t use lists overly
much.

And that is all. I hope this might be useful to some other
writers in the gopher space. If you want to check out the new
indexer/parser, you can find it on my Codeberg page[2].

-----------------------------------------------------------------

[1]: If you are on gopher, obviously you won&#x27;t see this any
     differently.

[2]: I did just notice a minor deficiency which I have not yet
     solved. Gopher can only display lines under 80 characters,
     and web-urls tend to be longer than this limit. Therefore,
     including a link to my codeberg page gets a little awkward.
     As such, please excuse the space in the following url
     between `200115/&#x27; and `pages/&#x27;:
     https://codeberg.org/User18130814200115/
     pages/src/branch/master/indexer.go

=================================================================

All of my writing and software projects are available free of
charge under CC-BY unless stated otherwise. I do not accept
monetary donations, but if my work has brought you value I ask
you to donate to a charitable cause or high-impact fund,
organisation, business, institute, or individual driving moral
progress.
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://tilde.club/1/~user18130814200115/posts/0033-fascism-in-progression-fantasy.txt</link>
<title>0033-fascism-in-progression-fantasy   2025-Aug-15 13:26    13.8 KB</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
Fascism in progression fantasy
Thu, 14 Aug 2025
Philosophy, Literature, Opinion
===============================

I read a lot, and I read a lot of different types of works. On a
typical week I will read about one novel, one non-fiction
-article, or -essay, and a handful of blog posts.

In the novel-section of my weekly digest, one may often find
books in the `progression-fantasy&#x27; genre. Books about characters
getting progressively stronger, smarter, more powerful,
etcetera. There is broad overlap between progression-fantasy and
Xianxia cultivation fantasy, meaning that it involves elements
of individualism, spirituality, religion, and so forth.

In the non-fiction-essay-section one can find various political,
philosophical, or religious texts and manifests. This week, this
included Mussolini&#x27;s[1] short essay ``La dottrina del
fascismo&#x27;&#x27;, which I -- due to my still-lacking Italian knowledge
-- read and English translation of: ``The doctrine of Fascism&#x27;&#x27;.
The Doctrine of Fascism, outlines -- unsurprisingly -- the core
tenants of fascism as a political, social, economical, and
spiritual doctrine. Also unsurprisingly, the essay is rather
unclear in many parts. Fascism is of course not known for its
rigorous philosophical basis, but I truly cannot overstate quite
how poor some of the reasoning in the work is.

It happens surprisingly often that my non-fiction reading finds
parallels, allegories, or examples in whatever fiction I am
reading at the time. Though I must admit that I was rather
surprised to find a great overlap between the tenants of fascism
and the ideas expressed in many progression-fantasy novels.

A brief disclaimer before I start: while this blog post intends
to point out similarities between the philosophies expressed in
The Doctrine of Fascism and popular progression-fantasy novels,
I do not intend for this to smear the genre or authors writing
in it. There are plenty of works of fiction wherein any number
of characters are adherents to awful systems of belief, or who
commit terrible actions and this does not make them worse works,
nor does this imply that the author adheres to-, or attempts to
glorify- these actions or beliefs. Furthermore, the
similarities are within fascisms `less&#x27; problematic doctrines
(anti-Semitism is luckily not a common occurrence in progression
fantasy nor is it actually a part of Mussolini&#x27;s fascism). 

Lastly, since I will be talking about various novels in this
post, there will be some MINOR spoilers for The mother of
learning, Defiance of the fall, and Cradle.

-----------------------------------------------------------------

The doctrine of progression fantasy
----------------------------------------

Let&#x27;s start with some frequently recurring ideas in progression
fantasy. Ultimately, in such works, the focus tends to be on
self-actualisation and -cultivation. The protagonist is trying
to become the most powerful-, smart-, developed-, version of
themselves. The path to such power is paved by hard work.
Certainly, there is often an element of luck involved, but the
protagonists of these stories succeed because they are willing to
put in the work to turn their fortunes around and to capitalize
on the advantages they receive.

This hard work usually takes the form of struggling on the brink
of death. Certainly this is not essential, but the greatest
gains are always found millimeters away from the breaking point.

Cultivation (which is how I will refer to the development of
these characters from now on) usually results in increased
physical-, and mental-, fortitude, drastically lengthened
lifespan, and higher social status. In most cases, society is
set up in such a way that the powerful rule over the weak.
``Might makes right&#x27;&#x27;, as many like to say, and if a country
bumpkin manages to reach a higher level of cultivation compared
to the emperor, then the emperor will bow down to them from that
point forward.

Cultivation tends to require a lot of resources leading to
conflicts over materials and opportunities. Those that succeed
are the ones that seize whatever they can get their hands on.
Deference, sharing, and charity have no place in these worlds.

In fact, charity is actively frowned upon. Since power is gained
by struggle, when opportunities and materials are freely given,
then recipients will not struggle for them and will thus be
(perhaps permanently) handicapped. This leads to a strong
individualistic mindset, though also to the forming of sects.

Large organisations can get their hands on materials more
easily, and the presence of a high-cultivation individual keeps
members more safe and provides them with resources (all in
exchange for contribution to the sect of course; no charity).
Since a single patriarch or matriarch can outlive generations of
dependents at higher cultivation ranks, these sects often start
out as families.

The doctrine of fascism
-----------------------

Having covered that, let me try to outline the core element of
Mussolini&#x27;s fascism as I understand them.

First and foremost, fascism is conceived by Mussolini out of a
disillusionment with the dominant philosophies from the early
20th century, namely socialism, liberalism, and scientific
materialism. This disillusionment seemed to stem (as it often
does) from a previous affiliation. During the first world war
there was an apparent schism in the Italian liberalism of which
Mussolini was a part. With one camp being in favour of the great
war (which we now call the first world war) and one camp being
against. Mussolini was in the former camp, which ended up being
the less-popular -- and therefore rejected -- path.

&gt; When the war ended in 1919 Socialism, as a doctrine, was
&gt; already dead; it continued to exist only as a grudge,
&gt; especially in Italy where its only chance lay in inciting to
&gt; reprisals against the men who had willed the war and who were
&gt; to be made to pay for it.

Fascism, therefore, is anti-individualistic, pro-war,
pro-state, and anti-well-being.

Let&#x27;s start with this first element: pro-war. Way, Mussolini
argues is the ULTIMATE occupation of any state (and the state is
all that matters as we will see shortly). War should not
necessarily be waged for any particular purpose. Indeed, I don&#x27;t
think Mussolini saw it as a very emotional excessive. War is
waged for the purposes of strengthening oneself (id est: the
state) through struggle. 

&gt; The Fascist disdains an `easy&#x27; life

The idea that any state, race, religion, etcetera is
particularly better than any other -- and therefore should rule
over the others -- is laughable to Mussolini. War is held for
the purpose of struggle, and if any one state would subjugate
all the others, then there would be no more struggle, which
would be disastrous.

Secondly, there is the pro-state mindset. The state, Mussolini
argues, is the only way for a person to fully express and
develop their moral, spiritual, and physical selves. At the same
time, the individual does not matter, in fact, they may
completely cease to exist, being incorporated entirely in the
state. This is to Mussolini the highest aim of life, in a rather
spiritual sense:

&gt; which suppressing the instinct for life closed in a brief
&gt; circle of pleasure, builds up a higher life, founded on duty,
&gt; a life free from the limitations of time and space, in which
&gt; the individual, by self-sacrifice, the renunciation of
&gt; self-interest, by death itself, can achieve that purely
&gt; spiritual existence in which his value as a man consists

The state therefore should manage everything, from religion, to
economics, as the state is the only thing which exists. On this
note, while this essay specifically suggests a roman catholic
religion and a guild-based economy, these seem to be to be
merely suggestions for the Italian fascist state in particular.
Mussolini does not seem to hold any particular affinity for
these (in fact, he actively despised catholic Christianity), nor
does he necessarily think they are any good. However, a state
should have a religion and an economy, the details don&#x27;t matter,
all that matters is development through struggle.

Coming to the anti-well-being aspect, this is tied in closely
with the anti-individual aspect.

&gt; the Fascist conception of life stresses the importance of the
&gt; State and accepts the individual only in so far as his
&gt; interests coincide with those of the State

The interests-, pleasure-, and
even life- of the individual does not matter to the state. Just
as any particular person does not care about the life of death
of a single cell in their body.

&gt; the well-being and freedom of the individuals composing it
&gt; does not seem to be in conformity with nature’s plans, which
&gt; care only for the species and seem ready to sacrifice the
&gt; individual.

The comparison
==============

I think those are enough fascist quotations for one post, let&#x27;s
move on to the comparison with progression fantasy.

To point out the obvious: growth through struggle is a core
concept (perhaps THE core concept of both ideologies). And
everything, from pleasure to well-being to life can be
sacrificed before the altar of progress.

We see this in Defiance of the Fall, where The System (the
mechanistic god of this universe) plans and sanctions entire
wars between galaxies to strengthen the victor[2]. In Cradle, we
see a society which has lived in peace and prosperity for
generations and has grown weak and feeble because of it, with a
literal child from the outside being able to best the entire
valley if they wanted to. In The Mother of Learning, we see one
character becoming an Archmage by putting in the work, using
others, and having a complete disregard for their own life,
while we watch another with greater opportunities and talents
waste his potential by investing time in social bonds, romance,
and fun.

The anti-individualism of fascism seems at first glance to not
mix well with the individualistic mindset of cultivation, though
I believe they actually align rather well. You see, individuals
at the high-levels of cultivation are states unto themselves.

We see this for example in Defiance of the Fall where
individuals who have reached the `monarch` stage of cultivation
are entire worlds onto themselves, worlds which can house many
other people. In Cradle, the sects formed by lords, monarchs,
and sages often involve the (sometimes literal) sacrifice of
lower tiered members for the cultivation of the benefit
patriarch or matriarch, id est: the benefit of the sect.

Another interesting parallel is not as common across the genre,
but I feel like it is still worth pointing out. In Defiance of
the Fall, faith is a source of power which can be accumulated,
and is actually one of the most powerful forces in the universe
partially powering the system itself. Importantly however, faith
does not need to be targeted towards an actual god. Instead,
faith can be directed practically anywhere. No faith is
particularly better or more true than any other. Instead, most
major sects will have a faith directed towards their founder
with rituals and practices designed solely for the purpose of
accumulating faith power. This rings with Mussolini&#x27;s approach
to Catholicism, where he didn&#x27;t particularly believe in the
teachings of the Bible or pope, but DID believe in the earthly
benefits of having a unified religion.

The heroes of both the progression-fantasy novel and the fascist
mythos are the Nietzschian ubermenschen. Those who have shed the
weaknesses of morality, charity, and non-zero-sum-thinking, to
become truly noble. That is: brave, and strong, and demanding
respect. In all cases: if you help others, you will only cripple
them. If you truly want to help another state/person: declare
them war, fight until you are on the brink of death, then go a
little further.

Of course, In these novels, a common theme is that the
protagonists gradually lose their humanity, and typically
authors include interpersonal relationships to keep the
characters grounded and relatable. At the same time, the
attitude of that characters seems to be that you cannot argue
with the results. They might look at the great-war and world-war
in our universe and say: ``well you all learned a lot didn&#x27;t
you? Warfare was revolutionized, the atom was split, advances
were made in medicine and science... And look at you now: Lazy,
decadent, content and deeply miserable&#x27;&#x27;.

I don&#x27;t know what to make of this. In a restrained quantity, I
think that the message that you can improve yourself by working
hard is a good one. Obviously fascist ideology goes much much
too far in this regard. Since progression fantasy is mostly
written-, and read-, by young men -- And since there are already
plenty of fascist influences on young men these days -- and
can&#x27;t help but be slightly concerned. I would like to believe
that other readers can -- much like myself -- recognize that
these are works of fiction, that the ideologies and characters
should not be idolized, and that our world is one where human
life-, and well-being- matter. But I have been let down so many
times before.

-----------------------------------------------------------------

[1]: In truth, the first part of the essay (the part which
     actually outlines the fundamental tenants of fascism was
     written by Giovanni Gentile, but name-dropping the famous
     ``founder of fascism&#x27;&#x27; gets the idea across that this essay
     described fascism as it was originally envisioned.

[2]: I should also point out that The System was created by a
     society which was also literally fascist. That they
     designed the system for their ``eternal war&#x27;&#x27; against
     another civilisation, and that they ``programmed&#x27; it
     specifically to strengthen their army through conflict.

=================================================================

All of my writing and software projects are available free of
charge under CC-BY unless stated otherwise. I do not accept
monetary donations, but if my work has brought you value I ask
you to donate to a charitable cause or high-impact fund,
organisation, business, institute, or individual driving moral
progress.
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://tilde.club/1/~user18130814200115/posts/posts</link>
<title>All posts</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
rror: File or directory not found! (null)
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://tilde.club/1/~user18130814200115/posts/posts/0028-ethical-systems-and-their-relative-strengths.txt</link>
<title>=== Ethical systems and their relative strengths ===</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
Error: File or directory not found! (null)
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://tilde.club/1/~user18130814200115/posts/posts/0029-limits-to-helping-others.txt</link>
<title>=== Limits to helping others ===</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
Error: File or directory not found! (null)
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://tilde.club/1/~user18130814200115/posts/posts/0030-a-neoplatonist-interpretation-of-post-christian-vitalism.txt</link>
<title>=== A Neoplatonist interpretation of post-christian vitalism ===</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
Error: File or directory not found! (null)
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://tilde.club/1/~user18130814200115/posts/posts/0031-insights-in-living-without-a-smartphone.txt</link>
<title>=== Insights in living without a smartphone ===</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
Error: File or directory not found! (null)
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://tilde.club/1/~user18130814200115/posts/posts/0032-switching-to-codeberg.txt</link>
<title>=== Switching to Codeberg ===</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
Error: File or directory not found! (null)
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://tilde.club/1/~user18130814200115/posts/0032-switching-to-codeberg.txt</link>
<title>0032-switching-to-codeberg.txt        2025-Jul-14 20:19     4.4 KB</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
Switching to Codeberg
Wed, 28 May 2025
Technology, Opinion
=====================

I have recently switched away from GitHub as my codeforge to
Codeberg which includes the hosting of this blog. In this brief
post, I will cover my reasons for switching and briefly describe
the process.

I have been using GitHub at least since 2016 (possibly earlier,
I was using a different account at the time, so and cannot see
exactly when I joined). Back then, I wanted to host some code I
was working on, and GitHub was (and still is) the most popular
choice for doing so. Since then however, many things have
changed, notably the acquisition by Microsoft, the increasing
social-media-lisation, and now: The AI [1].

Firstly, let me talk about the acquisition of GitHub by
Microsoft. At the time -- in 2018 -- I didn&#x27;t care much about
this change. I was still using Microsoft products occasionally
for university, and I believe I still had a Google account at
the time as well. Since then, I have increasingly switched away
from big-tech, but GitHub&#x27;s Microsoft ownership was seemingly
stored in a bit of a blind-spot in my brain, even though
migrating away from it would have been much easier than many of
the products I *did* switch away from (Such as Windows, Office,
GDrive, GooglePlay, etcetera).

Then there is the fact that GitHub is increasingly becoming more
of a social media platform. At first, many of these features
were nice. Stars give you a good idea of how popular a project
is, and following people can be a nice way to discover new
projects. However, too many *behaviours* carried over from
social media as well, such as follow-back and like-farming.
Besides, at the end of the day, I do not want GitHub to be my
social media, I want it to host my code and allow me to work
with others. When I have to star a project before my PR will be
considered,,, we have lost the path.

Lastly, there is the AI. Now, I do not refer just to AI in the
sense which it has recently taken (ie: LLMs). Rather I mean both
GitHub bots and the Copilot LLM. Popular GitHub bots such as
stale-issue bots completely mess up issue threads. They
encourage a behaviour where people periodically `bump&#x27; an issue
to keep it active. The aforementioned star-farming is made
possible with a bot. Once again, these are *behaviours* which
frustrate me, but they are *enabled* by GitHub&#x27;s features. It
also doesn&#x27;t help that GitHub -- as the most popular codeforge
-- has the lowest-common-denominator of users. When GitHub
recently introduced a LLM service which would write issues for
you, I decided it was about time to leave. I can already see the
future wherein this feature enables bad issue etiquette, and I
don&#x27;t want to be here for it[2].

So I switched. I archived all my repositories which are not
using GitHub actions, and migrated active repositories to my
Codeberg account. I have used Codeberg for some time already to
comment on projects that I used[3] and I really like the
interface and featureset (I cannot say the same for GitLab or
Sourcehut respectively). The migration process was mostly
painless, with the biggest time-sink being the archiving on the
GitHub-side.

I hope to stick around on Codeberg for a while, and perhaps to
also keep it more professional than by GitHub portfolio
(interests, standards, and personalities tend to change over the
course of a decade). In fact, this transition has occurred at
roughly the same time as my learning of the `go&#x27; programming
language which I will write about shortly and I hope to write
some larger projects in which are not convenient to write in
shell or python.

-----------------------------------------------------------------

[1]: I should also mention that GitHub being a US-based company
     also makes me less than thrilled given the current state of
     things.

[2]: In fact, this is not really a `future&#x27; at all, it has
     already been happening for some time. The difference is
     that the process is now more streamlined and sanctioned by
     Microsoft.

[3]: Notably the excellent `foot&#x27; terminal emulator

=================================================================

All of my writing and software projects are available free of
charge under CC-BY unless stated otherwise. I do not accept
monetary donations, but if my work has brought you value I ask
you to donate to a charitable cause or high-impact fund,
organisation, business, institute, or individual driving moral
progress.
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://tilde.club/1/~user18130814200115/posts/0031-insights-in-living-without-a-smartphone.txt</link>
<title>0031-insights-in-living-without-a-s   2025-Jul-14 20:19    11.1 KB</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
Insights in living without a smartphone
Wed, 16 Apr 2025
Technology, Lifestyle
=======================================

I have not used a smartphone for about 5 years on-and-off
(discounting of course the years as a child where I didn&#x27;t need
to worry about silly things like this). It started in the summer
of 2019 when by best friend gifted me his old Nokia 8110 4G
(more on this later). Since then, I only had a smartphone for
about a year. This device burnt through its charging circuitry a
month or-so ago, so I am back to the dumb-life, though now with
more insight into how to do things.

In this post, I will be sharing the insights I have accumulated
over the years. Just as a warning, the advice provided in this
post might come across as ultimately unsatisfying. While it is
definitely possible to live off of the information-grid, that is
not the type of life I can live currently. Therefore, a lot of
my insights revolve around using alternative but highly similar
solutions to having a smartphone. The main difference being that
you don&#x27;t or can&#x27;t bring these devices around in your pocket.

With they being said, let me start by covering briefly the
things which smartphones provide to us. Obviously, this list is
not exhaustive, instead only covering those things which I
personally find valuable and things which are outside of my
control.

What do smartphones give us?
----------------------------

	1. The valuable
		a. Photography
		b. Navigation
		c. Phone calls
		d. Music and podcasts
		e. Alarms
	2. The enforced
		a. Multi-factor-authentication
			i. TOTP codes
			ii. Specific apps (primarily banking and government ID)
		b. Certain communication platforms
			i. Notably Whatsapp
		c. Bus/Plane/Train/Cinema Tickets/Identification

How do we replace these services?
---------------------------------

Now we come to the interesting part: how do we replace all these
services provided to us by smartphones. For this section, I will
keep the same divide as listed above, as interesting patterns
emerge when we do so.

The valuable
============

Generally, for items in the `valuable&#x27; category, we have a
two main options: specialized technology or feature phones.

Specialized technology speaks for itself. Get yourself a camera,
map or GPS, dumb-phone, disc-or-walk-man or mp3 player, and an
alarm clock.  Obviously, this is a lot more to carry around
which will force you to be more concious with what you bring
with you. Furthermore -- while I find this highly upsetting
when it comes to the state of society -- you can get all of
these items (new or second-hand) for less than the price of a
new smartphone.

The other option (and the one I have gone with) is the feature
phone. Feature phones are a class of devices reminiscent of the
dumb-phones of old though brought into the modern world. They
typically allow you to connect to 4G networks, install apps, and
use the internet. At the same time, they are typically very
low-powered devices with traditional button-navigation. Some of
them run Android (which allows you to install all your usual
apps, though with the processing and navigation limitations
mentioned), Android-go  (Android with a reduced and simplified
library of apps), or KaiOS (A operating system based on web
technologies).

Each of these have their up-and-downsides. The android devices
are by far the most capable, though in my opinion you might as
well get an old second-hand smartphone at that point. Many of
them even have touchscreens making them just overpriced
smartphones with a built-in keyboard. The android-go devices
seem more in line with what I would want, though they are
typically not optimized for button-navigation and I have never
actually used one. That brings us to KaiOS. KaiOS is the
operating system which runs on the phone which I have used these
past 5 years (the aforementioned nokia 8110) and exists at the
nigh-perfect intersection of usable and limited. I should point
out at this point that KaiOS is more-or-less a dead project,
though that doesn&#x27;t mean that it is not still perfectly usable,
nor that there are not still exciting (though small)
developments made by the community.

My Nokia runs KaiOS. The camera is not very capable, but more
than sufficient for capturing memories. It runs a stripped-down
version of the google-maps website, sufficient for finding your
way when lost using GPS and 4G. Obviously it is perfectly
capable of phone calls and texts (even with two sim slots --
revolutionary, I know --). The built in music player app is
sufficient for my needs, though it does not allow you to make
playlists (third party offerings in the KaiStore do offer this
functionality) and there are plenty of podcast apps available.

In other words, my Nokia covers all the bases of what I find
valuable in a phone. Problem solved right? Well actually, the
`valuable&#x27; list is the easy part. Now for the elements outside
of my control.

The enforced
============

The enforced section of services is both more difficult and less
satisfying. Let me just rip of the bandage right away by dealing
with the least satisfying ones: Authentication, Identification,
and Communication.

Many services in this area simply REQUIRE an app on either
android or IOS. Banking applications, Government ID, Healthcare,
and Whatsapp all require apps to some extent. Banks occasionally
allow you request a dedicated code-device, though more the
more-modern e-banks usually don&#x27;t offer such services.
Governments and Health-insurance-providers (at least the ones
which are relevant to me) require apps to authenticate to online
environments. Lastly is Whatsapp, for those not from
mainland-Europe it might seem strange that this app is in the
`enforced&#x27; section, but here governments, public institutions,
customer-service-lines, and the public at-large all use
whatsapp. And since these services have still not been forced to
allow for interoperability with other services, I am stuck there
for now.

Now to the (rather unsatisfying) solutions to these problems.
Over the years I have found three options:
	1. Run an android container on your laptop or PC
	2. Get a tablet running android or IOS
	3. Get a smartphone that you leave in a drawer somewhere at
	   home
In other words, you will be stuck with these services (and
Android or IOS) either way, though at least these are not
services you will need to have on you at all times.
Whatsapp is perhaps an exception to this, though this depends on
your lifestyle.

Whatsapp is furthermore an exception because it doesn&#x27;t provide
an IpadOS app for some reason. Therefore, if you want to go with
the tablet-route, you cannot use and Ipad. Furthermore, while
Whatsapp does offer a web-version, you will still need to login
from Android or IOS. Personally, I run an android-emulator on my
laptop (waydroid) where I authenticate my whatsapp-web and
hardly ever look at it again. Do keep in mind that you need to
add contacts in your replacement device of choice as you cannot
do this through Whatsapp-web. Other communication platforms like
telegram are much better in this regard as they just have a
standalone web-app, though for the reasons mentioned above, I
cannot use these.

When it come to non-app-specific two-factor authentication, the
story is a lot more encouraging. Firstly, the feature phones I
mentioned before all have apps which allow for receiving TOTP
codes. Furthermore, such apps also exist for mac, linux, and
widows. Allowing you to simply authenticate with your laptop or
pc instead. Of course, if you are already getting a tablet for
the services above, then you can also use it to authenticate,
though at that point you are committing to carrying around your
tablet to most places where you might need to authenticate (such
as university, work, or public institutions).

Lastly is tickets and identification. Once again, you can carry
around a tablet whenever you need a ticket for something, though
-- especially if you use public transport a lot like I do --
this is not always feasible. Luckily, all services I have
encountered thus far still allow you to print a physical card
(for identification) or just print your ticket on paper (for
entry tickets and such). This does not necessarily mean that you
need to buy a printer though. Many libraries and universities
will allow you to print for a small fee. Some countries
(especially in southern Europe) also have many copy-shops spread
throughout their cities. The only difficulty in using the later
is somehow transferring your documents to the shop. This is
usually done on-the-spot though email, which is obviously not
accessible without a smartphone or similar device, though
luckily many places also accept USB sticks, and you can always
send your email ahead of time with an explanation that you will
come by soon.

Final remarks
-------------

The copy-shop example also leads me to one final point, that
being the ability to rely on friends and family for help. At the
end of the day, many of ditch smartphones to feel more connected
to others, and having a friend help you out with their printer
or mobile-internet-connection at the copy-shop is one such way
of connecting. The same goes for navigation. In a group, only
one person needs to have a method of navigation on them. You can
meet-up in-person instead of discussing things over text, or
just inform your friends and family that they need to call you
if they want to get a hold of you. 

Obviously, this lifestyle (if you want to call it that) can be
limiting, and it can feel especially discouraging when
smartphones are forced upon you. I have written in the past
about QR-codes and how their proliferation for restaurant menus,
ordering, locker reservation, etcetera basically forces you into
getting a smartphone (or a friend with one), and this can make
be limiting. There is almost always a way around this though
(talk with a waitress instead, see if someone around can get you
a locker in exchange for cash, etcetera), though there is not
one generalized solution (Yes, the nokia 8110 can scan QR codes
and use the websites, but I will always try to find a different
solution first.).

Ultimately, I have found not having a smartphone quite fun, and
ultimately more liberating than limiting. If you have never
tried it however, you don&#x27;t and can&#x27;t know what you are missing
(and I can&#x27;t really describe it either other than a feeling of
freedom). I would love to say ``Everyone! Just give it a try&#x27;&#x27;,
but there will be a large adjustment period and even a fair
amount of money spent in some cases.

Therefore, my final point of advice is this: If you want to try
living without a smartphone, don&#x27;t bring one the next time you
go on holidays -- provided you are traveling with someone who
does have a smartphone. In this way, you will always have the
safety of falling back on your partner&#x27;s device, while
simultaneously forcing yourself to keep the experiment up until
the end of your trip.

=================================================================

All of my writing and software projects are available free of
charge under CC-BY unless stated otherwise. I do not accept
monetary donations, but if my work has brought you value I ask
you to donate to a charitable cause or high-impact fund,
organisation, business, institute, or individual driving moral
progress.
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://tilde.club/1/~user18130814200115/posts/0030-a-neoplatonist-interpretation-of-post-christian-vitalism.txt</link>
<title>0030-a-neoplatonist-interpretation-   2025-Jul-14 20:19     6.8 KB</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
A Neoplatonist interpretation of post-christian vitalism
Sat, 25 Jan 2025
Philosophy, Ethics, Opinion
========================================================

A phenomenon I have seen going around the internet is so-called
post-Christian vitalism [1]. PCR is based on Nietzschian moral
philosophy, specifically the `master-mentality&#x27; towards ethics.
I believe this view is incredibly misguided, and will argue so
from a Neoplatonist [2] perspective.


Let us begin by exploring Nietzsche&#x27;s master-morality and the
specific interpretations of the post-christian vitalists.
Nietzsche distinguishes between two types of morality,
master-morality and slave-morality. Master morality -- he
asserts -- is the classical form of morality, where virtuous and
noble were interchangeable terms. Masters are courageous and
follow their own agenda, like Odysseus. Slave-morality instead
celebrates weakness by promoting `virtues&#x27; such as humility and
charity. Slave morality originated from... well slaves, and
non-nobles generally to give themselves some access to the
morality which the nobility had. Indeed, slave-moralists assert
that their form of morality is the only one, and that the
masters such as Odysseus are not virtuous at all.

Post-christian vitalises then claim [3] to embrace Nietzsche&#x27;s
master morality, becoming Nietzsche an super-humans and driving
froth progress in humanity. They asserts that all current-day
slave moralists are simply still under the thumb of Christian
propaganda, something which they have rid themselves of (hence
the post-christian part of the name).


Now, I think that this approach is fundamentally misguided and
indeed that it does not stand up to historical scrutiny. I might
write about this some day, but today, I instead want to asses
the PCV position from a Neoplatonic perspective. The reason this
is of interest to me is because Plotinus and Porphyry assert
that the sage indeed has no care for others. Neither does the
One for that fact [5].

This certainly seems to lend credence to the post-christian
vitalist, though, upon closer inspection, we will see that this
is not the case. Neoplatonic ethics -- much like nearly all
ancient ethics -- is built upon virtues. The four prime virtues
are Courage, Wisdom, Prudence, and Justice. For a person
starting out on their ethical journey, these virtues exist in
the ordinary (civic) sense. As one processes however, these 
virtues take on a different character and become the
intellectual (cathartic) virtues.

&gt; At the cathartic level, it is wise to ``refrain from opining
&gt; with the body&#x27;&#x27;, observing through intelligible means
&gt; rather than sensory ones. This eliminates the blindness
&gt; which sensory knowledge is inherently accompanied by.
&gt; Cathartic courage is the soul being turned away from the
&gt; concerns of the body, such as pain, fear, and discomfort,
&gt; but also death. Prudence, is the presence of desires
&gt; exclusively directed by psychic considerations, as opposed
&gt; to bodily impulses. And finally Justice, still guarantees
&gt; the cooperation of the virtues, in this case allowing the
&gt; rule of reason and intellect without opposition [7].

As the practitioner turns away from concerns of the physical
world, naturally they turn away from the suffering of others.
They regard their body with a form of indifference, and do
likewise for the bodies of others. Where the post-christian
vitalist is mistaken though is the order of operations. They see
that the noble sage has no regard for others (in the
traditional sense) and takes this to be first step. They mistake
an accident of the goal to be the means of achieving said goal.

Furthermore, while the sage has no regard for others, this
dispassion is not the same as a complete lack of care. Indeed,
the sage is said to give to others without taking away from
himself [8]. Plotinus (by all accounts a Neoplatonic sage) is
said to have taken care over the education of the young people
in his community, whist also housing several widows and orphans.
What the sage lacks is merely a passionate interest in the
affairs of others, but he does not lack other directedness
altogether[9].

-----------------------------------------------------------------

[1]: I should point out here that this term is mostly applied by
     opponents of this view, but I have not been able to find a
     better term, so this is the one I am sticking with.

[2]: When I say `Neoplatonist&#x27; in this post, I specifically
     refer to Plotinus and Porphyry and to a lesser extent
     Plato&#x27;s Phaedo (which I take to be the progenitor of
     Neoplatonic thought.

[3]: I say `claim&#x27; here for the simple reason that I sincerely
     doubt that anyone ACTUALLY thinks and acts this way. Sure,
     there are plenty of people who chart their own course and
     care little about the needs or sufferings of others, but I
     do not think that these people -- rationally -- believe
     their behaviour to be moral. Scott Alexander wrote a nice
     post about this just a few days ago [4].

[4]: astralcodexten.com/p/everyones-a-based-post-christian

[5]: ``The One&#x27;&#x27; the absolutely ontologically prior principle in
      Neoplatonic philosophy. ``The sage&#x27;&#x27;  is the person who
      spends their life in pursuit of The One in a semi mystical
      way [6].

[6]: I say semi-mystical because the term `mystic&#x27; is incredibly
     loaded. I wont go in to this now, but I have a paper
     which may be published int he next year or two which
     addresses this topic.

[7]: This section is a direct quote from my master&#x27;s
     dissertation, as I cannot currently be bothered re-writing
     it. The information contained therein is based upon
     Porphyry&#x27;s `sentences&#x27;.

[8]: This is a paraphrase based on Plotinus&#x27; statements in the
     Enneads about The One and the attitude the sage has towards
     his body.

[9]: The argument is clearly underdeveloped in this formulation,
     and while I would love to expand on it here, a blog post is
     simply not the right place. As mentioned, I have an article
     which may be published over the next few years on these
     topics. In its current form, the work is about 80
     single-spaces pages, much too long for a post I would say.
     I will of course update this blog if i ever do manage to
     get this work published. For the impatient, I recommend
     Pauliina Remes&#x27; work in the field. A good introduction is
     `Plotinus’ Ethics of Disinterested Interest&#x27;.

=================================================================

All of my writing and software projects are available free of
charge under CC-BY unless stated otherwise. I do not accept
monetary donations, but if my work has brought you value I ask
you to donate to a charitable cause or high-impact fund,
organisation, business, institute, or individual driving moral
progress.

For more information about making a moral impact, search for
``giving what we can&#x27;&#x27;, ``give well&#x27;&#x27;, or ``effective altruism&#x27;&#x27;.

</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://tilde.club/1/~user18130814200115/posts/0029-limits-to-helping-others.txt</link>
<title>0029-limits-to-helping-others.txt     2025-Jul-14 20:19     5.3 KB</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
Limits to helping others
Mon, 30 Dec 2024
Opinion, Philosophy, Ethics
===========================

In applied ethics, I believe one of the fundamental questions to
be that of helping others. Whether it is full-on charity, or
just showing someone the way to the library, it is unquotable
that these actions have a moral aspect.

A question arises however when it a person asks for help
repeatedly. In particular, I see two common situations arise.
First, there are those who abuse charity. People asking
repeatedly for handouts to ``get back on their feet&#x27;&#x27; only to
blow the assistance on matter non-conducive to bettering their
situation. Second, are those people who become reliant on your
help because they never learn to do things themselves. Instead
of learning to read a map, they become reliant on asking you (or
other helpful people) for directions. These two situations are
distinct in that the former contains an intentionally malicious
actor, whereas the second person might be seen as a victim from
some perspectives.

Unfortunately for me[1] virtue ethics does not have as clear an
answer for this problem as some other ethical systems do.
Consequentialists for example, can simply say that not-helping
is more conducive to the overall increase in good compared to
helping. Deontologists -- of the non-categorical variety -- can
say that the imperative to help others is contingent on said aid
not being misused or making the recipient dependent[2].

I believe that the virtues of wisdom, courage, moderation, and
prudence quite plainly inspire one to aid others when they are
in need. Indeed, the virtues as a whole inspire us to give to
others what we have and they do not. The virtuous way is to give
in such a way that one is personally not diminished[3].

Despite the virtue in giving, it is also undeniable that
virtuous people are responsible for the moral education of
others. Enabling immoral behaviour, or otherwise limiting the
growth of virtue in another person is not just, prudent, wise,
or courageous. Rather, such behaviour is the result of either
foolishness, pride, jealousy, insecurity, or other such vices.

How do we square this circle? How do we provide others with what
they need, without diminishing their moral progress? I believe
that answer of the virtue ethicist involves much more moral
responsibility than the consequentialist-, and deontological-
answers provided above. The answer boils down to this: As a
virtuous person you are responsible for your fellow humans. For
their material and spiritual needs, and for their moral growth.
As such, when you provide aid to someone, your responsibility in
ensuring their moral development grows proportionally to the aid
provided.

Each time you give your cousin money ``just to cover the rent
this month, I&#x27;ll pay you back next month when I land that
job-interview I swear&#x27;&#x27;, you become more responsible for
ensuring that they take their life in the right direction. In
other words, if someone abuses your charity, then this is your
own moral failing. You only took half of the steps which virtue
required of you and in doing so bred vice in another person.
Specifically, you are lacking in justice, which keeps the
virtues balanced.

Despite one&#x27;s increased moral responsibility after helping
someone, this does not imply that one gains the right to take
decisions for the recipient. Even more so, even though it is
your responsibility to morally educate this person, that does
not give you have any more right to take up their time to
lecture or berate them.

What then should you do? The answer is simple when you think
about it. You must give education simultaneously. Your aid must
come in the form of a moral lesson. Not the type where you give
someone money and a lecture on the dangers of indulgence at the
same time, but rather of the type where you teach a hungry man
to fish rather than feeding him directly. When someone asks your
for directions, show them where to find the answer. When someone
asks your opinion, show them your though process. When someone
someone asks you for money, advise them on how to spend it.

After all, at the end of the day, virtuous actions breed
virtue, and passing on what you know, do, and feel -- as a
virtuous person -- will slowly build virtue in those you help.

-----------------------------------------------------------------

[1]: As I outlined in my previous post titled ``Ethical systems
     and their relative strengths&#x27;&#x27; I am a virtue ethicist.

[2]: If you are not caught up on what these terms mean, see my
     previous post ``Ethical systems and their relative
     Strengths&#x27;&#x27;

[3]: This is mostly a Neoplatonic view on virtue, and being
     `undiminished&#x27; as such does not refer to material
     matters. Rather, the claim is that we must be generous in
     such a way that our lives are filled with just as much
     goodness DESPITE being materially diminished. Indeed, the
     early neoplatonists seem to assert that material
     diminishment is a necessary (and perhaps sufficient) cause
     for being morally enhanced.

=================================================================

All of my writing and software projects are available free of
charge under CC-BY unless stated otherwise. I do not accept
monetary donations, but if my work has brought you value I ask
you to donate to a charitable cause or high-impact fund,
organisation, business, institute, or individual driving moral
progress.
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://tilde.club/1/~user18130814200115/posts/0028-ethical-systems-and-their-relative-strengths.txt</link>
<title>0028-ethical-systems-and-their-rela   2025-Jul-14 20:19     9.2 KB</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
Ethical systems and their relative strengths
Sat, 28 Dec 2024
Opinion, Philosophy, Ethics
============================================

In the near future, I plan to make some posts about morality and
ethics. This post will simultaneously serve as a FAQ page and
declaration of affiliation. Here, I will write briefly what I
think about the major branches of Philosophical ethics, and show
where my personal affiliations lie.

This introduction should help you -- the reader -- in being a
good starting point for the coming posts. At the same tine, it
will help me, in that -- when I cam critiquing, lets say,
utilitarianism -- I won&#x27;t need to state in great detail that I
am a virtue ethicist and that this clouds my judgment of
the theory being discussed.

Consequentialism
----------------

Consequentialist theories look at the consequences of actions.
Typically, the analysis of consequences is used pick a course of
action which maximizes the presence of a certain value or set of
values at the end. Utilitarianism for example aims to maximize
utility, hedonism maximises for pleasure, Marxism for
cultivation, etcetera.

Consequentialists -- in my option -- fall into two camps: the
practical and the useless. The practical have actual means of
calculating the relevant values in a given set of circumstances.
While these calculations usually leave something to be desired
-- thereby opening up the theory to more repugnant conclusions
than most -- they are generally useful in their ability to asses
the world and potential courses of action. The useless (or
theoretical) consequentialist states that we can assess morality
by looking at the relative presence certain specific values in
consequences, but does not outline how to measure these values.
They are, in this way, much like a virtue ethicist who does not
explain what virtues are, or which virtues we should embody.

While consequentialists (of the practical type) are great at
analysing situations, assessing moral progress, and identifying
potentially high-impact courses of action, they are not
NECESSARILY great at bringing about these states. A
consequentialist world would undoubtedly be quite nice to live
in, though it is not necessary that the people in that world are
moral, nor that the society as a whole is exactly because the
means and reason of the action do not matter, only the
consequence.

Deontology
----------

Deontological theories are theories of duty where the moral
course of action is the one which is in accordance with a
person&#x27;s (or group&#x27;s) obligations. There is much debate on
whether these duties are circumstantial or categorical. If a
duty such as ``do not lie&#x27;&#x27; is categorical, then it is immoral
to lie, even if it would save someone&#x27;s life. If the duty is
circumstantial, then we may lie in certain -- well defined
-- circumstances (such as when lying would save a life).

Deontologists thus only look at actions when assessing the
morality of behaviour, not at the consequences. However, the
duties themselves do supposedly bring forth good consequences,
perhaps even maximally good ones. 

While deontologists can easily assess why a certain course of
action was wrong -- even if that action lead to a favourable
outcome -- they can not say anything against a person who
followed their duty but achieved nothing. Certainly, there might
be a duty to ``try at least *this* hard&#x27;&#x27;, but trying and
accomplishing are only loosely related. Furthermore, while a
deontological world would be full of moral actions, it would --
in my option -- not be full of moral agents, because the agents
acts in total disregard of the consequences of their actions.

Virtue ethics
-------------

Theories of virtue asses the character of people, groups, or
systems. They generally define a set of traits which are good
people (groups, or systems) embody. Importantly, good people do
not just poses these traits, as they also act them out, and do
so entirely without effort, as if it is the most natural thing
to do. Classic examples of virtues are: Courage, wisdom,
moderation, justice, etcetera.

There are many reasons as to why I am personally a virtue
ethicist, rather too many to concisely put in this post, but let
me cover some of the ways in which virtue ethics meets the
challenges of consequentialism and deontology.

Firstly -- contra deontology -- virtue ethics looks at people,
rather than mere actions. This sidesteps the problem of
deontology mentioned above, where deontological people do not
necessarily seem to be moral people. At the same time, since
virtuous people act out their virtues, the resulting actions are
also virtuous.

Secondly -- contra consequentialism -- virtue ethics&#x27; instance
on instinctive action rings more true with my intuitions on
morality than a consequentialist cost-benefit analysis. For
example, when meeting a beggar on the street, the virtuous
person -- acting in generosity, humility, moderation, or justice
-- will take action to help them. A consequentialist will need
to analyse whether any aid would increase the overall amount of
good, and whether their, effort, money, food, etcetera might be
better spent elsewhere where it would do more good.

Now a consequentialist might argue that a generous society does
not necessarily imply a society effective at eliminating
poverty, or similar evils which can be combatted with charity. A
consequents society -- they would say -- is more effective at
this because they analyse where, how, how much, and when to
give. I would counter however that, the virtues cannot be taken
in isolation. A generous person is not a virtuous person, though
a virtuous person is generous. A virtuous person is furthermore
wise, patient, and prudent, and will thus also act in a way
which is maximally beneficial, even when these benefits do not
show up on a cost-benefit analysis. Indeed, the virtuous sage
may even employ consequents theories in their procurement of
wisdom so that they can henceforth take the best courses of
action.

A deontologist might argue that, while virtues make for good
people, they do not make for good societies. A society where
everyone follows their duties is a good society, but a society
where everyone is virtuous might not be. I would retort however
that virtuous people build virtuous societies, and that these
societies run smoothly even in absence of duties. A virtuous
society provides for its citizens even if there is no duty to
``feed the hungry&#x27;&#x27; or ``clothe the cold&#x27;&#x27;. Virtuous people will
built this society and work within it exactly because there is a
unification of disposition, action, and outcome.

Personal opinion
================

As I have now mentioned many times, I am a virtue ethicist. I
(admittedly rather unoriginally) take wisdom, justice, courage,
and prudence to be the core virtues, with all other virtues
being derived from these.

I believe that the following of one&#x27;s duty and the analysis of
outcomes are useful, especially when one is still cultivating
virtue.

I belie that many religions stress the importance of these
values, and believe that self-described adherents to these
faiths too often ignore them. This is especially frustrating in
faiths which I have personal affiliations with.

For example: The bible -- to me -- seems quite clear on the
duty/virtue of generosity, inclusion, forgiveness, humility, and
impartiality. And yet, I know few Christians who actually sold
everything they didn&#x27;t need and gave it all to charity. Amongst
the Christians I know, there are many judgemental types, who
care more about who is sleeping with who, than about following
Christ&#x27;s example and lifting the world out of suffering. They
boast about their `virtue&#x27;, their `purity&#x27;, proud of how long
they have been `saved&#x27; about how often they go to church, how
long and often they fast, whether they have been baptized,
re-baptized, whether it was in a pool, a lake, in the Jordan
itself. They make claims about what type of people can an cannot
be Christians, about what behaviours are entirely incompatible
with Jesus&#x27; message all the while they adorn themselves with
cowardice, excess, foolishness, and inequity; treating the
Church as nothing but a cult of mutual benefit.

If you read this paragraph and think to yourself ``yeah he is
right, Christians are awful&#x27;&#x27;, then you have not understood
anything. If you came away thinking you are exempt from this
judgement because you are not Christian, know that the above
applies to people I have met of all religious and non-religious
persuasions.

If you have made it this far then I assume you are either
infuriated by how wrong I am, or you agree with me at least in
part. In either case, this seems a suitable place for a little
``recruitment drive&#x27;&#x27;. If you agree with me that we must act
with wisdom, courage, justice, and prudence, then I urge you to
donate to a charitable cause or other high-impact virtuous
program in any way which you are able. If you disagree with me
on morality, then prove me wrong by donating in total absence of
virtue. Perhaps because it increases overall utility, because it
is your duty, because it makes you feel good and powerful to
give to people you consider inferior. If you donate to a
credible organisation, get a receipt and send it to me at
&lt;blog.wester.digital&gt;, I will match the first 100 euros of
donations to the causes of your choosing.

For inspiration consider:
- Giving what we can
- Give well
- Giving Green
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://tilde.club/1/~user18130814200115/posts/0027-moving-to-nixos.txt</link>
<title>0027-moving-to-nixos.txt              2025-Jul-14 20:19    10.8 KB</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
Moving to NixOS
Tue, 24 Dec 2024
Highly technical, Linux, Opinion
================

Disclaimer
----------

This post will be rather more technical compared to what I
normally write about. I will be using a lot of technical jargon
specific to the Linux desktop space. If you are not familiar
with this world, then I suggest you skip this post, there are
more coming soon (tm).

-----------------------------------------------------------------

I recently migrated my (main and only) system from Alpine Linux
to NixOS. In this post I will explain why I made the switch and
why I consider Nix to be -- currently -- the best Linux
distribution available.

Nix is a project that has been on my radar of quite some time
now. It is a system designed around the principles of
reproducibility, build-isolation, and declarative design, while
also boasting one of the largest and most up-to-date software
repositories in the Linux world.

Of course, there is a lot of hype around Nix, and this tends to
be a dangerous thing. In fact, I switched away from Arch Linux a
few years ago exactly because it was increasingly flooded with
novice users drawn in by the hype who considered the forums
their personal large-language-model[1]. Aside from the hype
though, there were a number of aspects which seemed really
attractive to me. Rollbacks, Software availability, and
Reproducibility being the main ones. On their own, these were
not enough to overcome the cost of switching, that is until I
encountered some problems with my existing Alpine installation.

Alpine
------

When I initially switched from Arch to Alpine, I was very
pleased for various reasons. The Alpine Package Keeper (apk) is
-- to this day -- the most pleasant, fast, and reliable package
manager I have used, Alpine&#x27;s bi-yearly stable releases allowed
me to have a more stable system, and the installer that came
with my flavour of Alpine (PostmarketOS) allowed me to recover
from catastrophic breakages faster than with Arch.

Out of these benefits, stability and recoverability were the
most important ones. These values are important for two main
reasons.  Firstly, I only have one laptop at my disposal, and it
is an arm laptop at that. If my OS breaks in some catastrophic
manner, I will need to borrow someone else&#x27;s laptop, take out
the EMMC storage, and re-flash the operating system. A process
that could take several days if none of my friends&#x27; laptops are
available. Faster installations (that can be done from windows
or mac) massively increase the chances that I will be able to
recover my system in a reasonable amount of time. Secondly, I do
not generally have a lot of time to tinker with my system
outside of holidays. For this reason, I have gotten in the
habit of only running updates every half year or so. If I would
do this on Arch, everything would rather quickly break, and I
would likely not be able to install anything in-between because
there would be a dependency mismatch.

In other words: Alpine stable is perfect for me. There is one
problem however: I can&#x27;t use it. `Can&#x27;t&#x27; is a big word of
course, and I must admit that I could theoretically live with a
stable alpine release. But as it stands, I use a lot of software
from Alpine&#x27;s `testing&#x27; repository, which requires one to be on
Alpine Linux `edge&#x27;, the rolling-release side of Alpine. In
other words, almost the entire previous paragraph can be thrown
out. I will say that Alpine&#x27;s apk handles infrequent updates
better than Arch&#x27;s pacman, but it still is not ideal that I need
to be `edge&#x27; at all.. 

This leads us to today: the start of the winter holidays. I
tried running an update and it did not go well. Firstly, apk
updates itself, so far so good. Secondly it tried to instal
`mesa-asahi&#x27; for some reason. I have still not figured out which
program introduced this new dependency. For those who do not
know `mesa-asahi&#x27; is the graphics driver for Apple&#x27;s arm-based
macs which recently landed in alpine-testing. I do not have an
arm-based mac, and so I don&#x27;t know why this should have been
installed. The reasons are however meaningless because
`mesa-asahi&#x27; introduced a conflict with `mesa&#x27; generally (the
graphics drivers I actually need) because the former was already
on version 24.3 while the rest was still on 24.2.

I tried running `apk fix&#x27; which is generally a good idea when
you encounter a conflict with apk. This command (for some
reason) updated `qt6&#x27; and nothing else. This meant that any app
using qt6, like my web browser, document viewer, file manager,
music player, video player, tormenting client, and others, would
not work until they-too were updated.

Since I didn&#x27;t think I needed mesa-asahi in the first place (I
never installed it up to that point, and I didn&#x27;t see why I
should start now), I decided to simply tell apk to exclude the
package and update as usual. This seemed to have... weird
effects. Firstly, none of my graphical programs were working
anymore. GTK applications gave some sort or error which I cannot
at the moment recall while QT applications just segfaulted -- a
great start. Secondly, the system was incredibly slow: both in
being sluggish to use and taking three times longer to boot than
usual.

Now -- clearly -- I messed something up by telling apk not to
include mesa-asahi in the update. Indeed these problems may be
attributable to missing graphics drivers -- with the system
falling back to software rendering. However, the dependency
introduction and version-mismatch were both out of my control,
and the fact that `apk fix&#x27; updated QT6 and broke all my
graphical applications meant that I couldn&#x27;t just wait for the
version conflict to be resolved[2].

I though for some time about what to do -- re-installing
Alpine-edge might work, or I could try Alpine-stable and make-do
without half of my software -- and ultimately decided that I
could not stay on Alpine due to the simultaneous need to be on
`edge&#x27; while also needing a rock-solid system. Which brings us
to Nix.

NixOS
-----

I managed to download the NixOS installer ISO with `curl&#x27; and
install it to a borrowed USB-stick using `dd&#x27; while still on my
broken Alpine install. According to the wiki, I should just be
able to use the graphical installer on my system. Easy peasy.

This was not the case. The graphical installer does not have a
menu to select the bootloader, and nix&#x27;s default loader `grub&#x27;
does not work well on arm based systems. Luckily the wiki-page
for installing NixOS on arm single-board-computers had the
correct instructions for a manual install, and a few minutes
later I had a fresh install of NixOS.

My initial impressions of Nix were rather positive. It was
remarkably easy to learn, and there were a lot of resources
available, notably the wiki and the forums. At first I had some
trouble to get things working properly. Every time I ran an
update, the updater itself would be broken on the new
install[3]. Everytime though, I could just roll-back to the
previous version and try again[4].

I spent some time getting my usual configuration set up using
nix and noticed just how helpful the nix-rebuild command was.
For instance, when I tried to install flatpak, nix informed me
that for flatpak to be functional, I needed to enable the
xdg-desktop-portal service. After doing this, it told me that I
didn&#x27;t have an actual portal configured and/or installed. For
context. If you do this on Arch or Alpine, you are pretty much
left to your own devices in figuring out how to get these
working, especially if you are not using a pre-configured
desktop environment.

A second immediately noticeable difference was the sheer size of
the nix repositories. Every piece of software which I use, with
the exception of one[5], was in the nix repositories, and I use
a lot of niche and obscure software. The only somewhat strange
thing I noticed is that the font which I like to use for my
desktop: droid, was not in the stable repository, but only the
unstable one[6]. This didn&#x27;t matter though as nix allows me to
add just this one package from the unstable repository while
keeping my others on version 24.11.

Nix handily beats Alpine in terms of software availability. I
think this is in large-part to to the fact that alpine requries
more porting work due to its use of musl-libc and openrc, rather
than the more standard glibc and systemd Nix also beats Arch if
you look only at the main repositories. The arch user repository
still has an edge over nix in some cases, but this is not so
much as repository as much as it is a collection of build scripts
which -- in my experience -- work about as often as they do not.

Lastly is recoverability. I already mentioned nix&#x27;s rollback
feature, but even if my laptop dies in its entirety, if the
drive gets corrupted, or if I want to move to a different
system, I will be able to get back on track in no time
whatsoever. This is because an entire NixOS install is
essentially defined as a configuration file. I have this
configuration backed up in a public Github repository[7] and can
therefore recover my system in minutes, rather than hours or
days.

All in all I am loving nix so far, and I will probably keep
using it for quite some time.

-----------------------------------------------------------------

[1]: As a quick aside, I think the classic Arch-user-forum
     response `RTFM&#x27; (Read the F Manual), is harmful to the
     community as a whole, though I cannot deny that most of the
     questions raised by new uses are described extensively on
     the excellent wiki pages.

[2]: As of writing, the mesa package has still not been updated
     and the version conflict persists. It has been about a
     week.

[3]: This is 100% a case of user-error, and not a problem with
     Nix or NixOS.

[4]: I recall when I first installed Arch constantly messing
     things up and re-installing from scratch. Even on Alpine I
     once managed to remove any means of connecting to wifi and
     needing to re-install.

[5]: I can&#x27;t even blame nix for this. The program in question is
     a niche add-on to a niche program which has not been updated
     in over a year. The only reason this program is in the
     Alpine repositories is because I added it there.

[6]: I don&#x27;t know exactly what it means for a typeface
     to be `unstable&#x27;, but I believe it has something to do with
     the fact that droid is designed for small-screen-interfaces which
     are currently under heavy development.

[7]: https://github.com/user18130814200115-2/riverbed

=================================================================

All of my writing and software projects are available free of
charge under CC-BY unless stated otherwise. I do not accept
monetary donations, but if my work has brought you value I ask
you to donate to a charitable cause or high-impact fund,
organisation, business, institute, or individual driving moral
progress.

For more information about making a moral impact, search for
``giving what we can&#x27;&#x27;, ``give well&#x27;&#x27;, or ``effective altruism&#x27;&#x27;.
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://tilde.club/1/~user18130814200115/posts/0026-descartes-the-kabbalist.txt</link>
<title>0026-descartes-the-kabbalist.txt      2024-Oct-30 18:25     2.3 KB</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
Descartes the Kabbalist
Wed, 30 Oct 2024
Philosophy, Religion, Non-serious
=================================

We know from the Talmud and Torah that God is not present in his
creation. That is not to say of course that he is absent, but
rater that he permeates through it. God is reflected in every
thing as all thing are built according to the celestial
blueprint which is Adam Kamon. While all things are like God,
all things are also by necessity unlike God. For if something
would be entirely like God, then it must be God (which is
heretical) or there must be two Gods (which is HIGHLY
heretical).

We do know however of the existence of Metatron, who is called
the lesser God. Indeed this too seems heretical, yet it is in
the scriptures so it cannot be so. We must look deeper.

All things in creation are both like and unlike God, yet that
does not mean all tings under heaven are equal in the measure
with which they resemble God. Metatron namely is the entity
which is the least unlike God as is possible within Malkuth on
the highest branches of the Tree of life, Metatron represents
the slightest difference from God himself, namely only one
aspect must differ. Of course, god has no properties since God
is One, it must therefore be that at the high reaches of heaven,
Metatron is entirely like God except that he is not entirely
untied. His disunity is found in him not being God.

It should now be obvious how Descartes was indeed a Kabbalist.
Descartes explains that the soul does not reside in the body,
but permeates through it. He explains furthermore that while,
the soul permeates, there is one area which is the least unlike
the soul, that being the pineal gland. For this reason,
Descartes calls the gland ``the seat of the soul&#x27;&#x27;.

Much as how calling Metatron ``the lesser god&#x27;&#x27; is nigh
heretical, so too is it almost ridiculous to call one part of
the body the seat of the soul, as it would imply that this is
the area whereupon the soul acts. Yet what Descartes whishes to
say is that, while the pineal gland is a part of the body, it is
the part which is most like the soul (and therefore least unlike
the body).

Being properly part of the body, it must be more than half
physical. This might explain why so many fall prey to the
passions of the body rather than following the divine spark
within them upwards to its source in the God most high.
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://tilde.club/1/~user18130814200115/posts/0025-home-sickness.txt</link>
<title>0025-home-sickness.txt                2024-Sep-17 21:14     4.8 KB</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
Home (sickness)
Tue, 17 Sep 2024
Travel
================

As a child in elementary school, I -- much like most kids --
went on holidays with my parents. My classmates of course did
the same, and afterwards, when school started back up again, we
would share stories. One concept which often came up in these
stories was homesickness.

As a child, I didn&#x27;t understand homesickness. After all, what is
so great about being home? And why would you miss it when there
is so much to see.

Later in life, we would go on class trips over weekends. There
would always be kids who missed home (particularly their
parents) so much that they cried for hours. Once, again, I
didn&#x27;t really understand their sadness. I got along fine with my
parents, but the trip was fun and -- all things considered --
rather short.

Much later in life, after finishing middle school, I started
traveling back-and-forth between my parental home in The
Netherlands and the city of Frankfurt in Germany. After about a
year of doing this, I started to understand a semblance of the
pain of homesickness (&quot;homesick&quot; comes from the German heimweh,
the second element of which translates to pain). I missed
aspects of Frankfurt, the modernity and general cleanliness of
the city[1]. The great metro system, and general access to the
&quot;big city&quot; where all things I missed living in a slightly rural
town in The Netherlands with nothing but infrequent bus service
and a shopping area of about 20 stores.

However, this was not quite homesickness. I was longing for
another place yes, but this place was not home. And it wasn&#x27;t
its home-y-ness that I missed.

A few years later I moved to Oslo in Norway. Now was finally a
good time to feel real homesickness. I moved by myself and went
to live alone for the first time, I didn&#x27;t know anyone in
Norway, and I had to figure out a whole new city, country,
system, culture, and language.

Certainly, I was sad and lonely often during my first few weeks
in Norway. I was uncomfortable with figuring out how to get
around the city, needing to re-learn which stores sold what,
adjusting to a genuinely disgusting shared flat, and needing to
go out and socialize, they all weighed heavily on me. And yet,
at no point did I want to go home. In fact, I almost had to go
back as there was a problem with my paperwork, only then did I
truly feel pain, and in that moment my being alone really hit
home.

I lived in Norway never missing home, nor even feeling nostalgic
about The Netherlands nor Germany. Nor did I particularly love
Oslo either, but it was certainly the most enjoyable place I had
lived thus far. Two years passed like this and I moved to Italy,
which a brief two months of homelessness in-between.

That finally did it, the homelessness, I use this word lightly
of course. In no way was I living on the street, but I had no
place that I could call home, and that hurt. What hurt perhaps
even more is that I had no home in Norway to which I would
return. I was homesick, longing Oslo, knowing full well that I
would not be going back.

Moving to Italy, I had the same difficulties as in Norway, of
learning a new language, city, customs etcetera. Though now I
also specifically missed parts of Norway. The vast forests where
I walked on a nearly daily basis where a sore point to go
without, and each stroll I took in Italy where I was forced to
walk virtually on the highway added to my longing. I started to
(pre-emotively) miss the cold and snow (in September). I missed
my patterns: In Oslo I always knew a place where I could go. The
location of every library, gym, church, where I could go and be
more or less at home. And here I was, in a city where I barely
knew my own house, and where I hadn&#x27;t even figure out yet how to
get around save for walking.

As strong as my nostalgia and homesickness for Norway was, I
also remembered that Oslo was by no-means a perfect place. Here
there might be no woods, but at least there is sunlight.
Restaurants are affordable and the historical city center is a
delight to walk through (also: There is a historical city
center, something which Oslo lacks severely, historical or
otherwise). My apartment is larger and I pay less. I no-longer
have to use the laundromat because I have my own washing
machine. Summer is an actual season here And if nothing else, I
am closer to family.

Leaving behind a home -- not for a trip, but permanently --
hurts. And the home -- though gone -- will stay with me. In case
it was not clear, this post was nothing but a lengthily
love-letter to Norway, as well as an attempt to trick myself
into liking Italy. Though as much as I miss home, and as much as
I am sceptical about Italy, I am excited to see what home I
might make here...





[1]: I know it is fashionable to hate on Frankfurt, and these
     remarks may seem odd to some. To me however, Frankfurt was
     and remains a beautiful place.
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://tilde.club/1/~user18130814200115/posts/0024-fundamental-laws.txt</link>
<title>0024-fundamental-laws.txt             2024-Jul-23 13:45     5.7 KB</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
Fundamental Laws
Thu, 18 Jul 2024
Opinion
================

The code of Hammurabi is one of the oldest and most well
preserved legal texts and at some point supposedly governed the
ancient Babylonians. The laws of the code are inscribed onto
basalt, and while the Babylonians may have had further laws to
supplement these, it is safe to say that 282 inscribed ones were
considered most fundamental, requiring the need for inscription.

Looking at what the ancient Babylonians considered to e
fundamental gives us insight into changing attitudes regarding
what ought to be legislated. The code for instance contains laws
regarding the giving of testimony in court, laws regarding
marriage, divorce, and adultery, as well as assault, robbery,
and destruction of property. These topics are still regarded as
rather fundamental in modern society.

However, the code also contains laws regarding wages and prices
for goods and services. This sounds more peculiar to the modern
reader. Certainly, most legal scholars are not in favour of
entirely unregulated markets, though doubtless few would be in
favour of a constitutional amendment putting a fixed price on
the rent of freight vessels as the ancient Babylonians had.

We find similarly overly specific laws in the books of law of
the Torah. Here, we are told what animals to eat, how to prepare
them, what cuts are suitable for sacrifice, how the sacrificial
altar should be constructed, and which transgressions require
which sacrifices. These are interwoven with laws which we
consider fundamental to this day, such as those regarding
marriage, property, and crime.

It seems then that attitudes regarding legislation change with
time. Certainly no modern western state would legislate in
minute detail how one should worship or make amends to God. Yet
we have kept many of the laws regarding marriage, property, and
crime. Are these laws truly fundamental? Or are they just as
arbitrary as the price and consumption of food? 

Marriage
--------

``Minimizing Marriage&#x27;&#x27; is a book by Elizabeth Blake where she
explores the various dimensions which marriage occupies.
Marriage can simultaneously be a romantic commitment, a legal
contract, a driver of moral legitimacy, and a religious act. The
question remains whether marriage *should* occupy all of these
dimensions, or whether certain ones are arbitrary. Blake writes
extensively on decoupling romance and ethical/legal legitimacy.
I similarly would like to ask the question whether states
should be in the marriage business at all.

Several European countries do not recognize marriage between two
people of the same sex. In some of these countries, such couples
can enter into a civil union, which is the same in all but name
legally speaking. Acceding to some however, civil unions lack
the moral legitimizing force associated with marriage. Even
outside of same-sex unions, I know of religious people who speak
of ``common-law marriage&#x27;&#x27; as opposed to ``christian marriage&#x27;&#x27;,
where only the later is legal in the eyes of God.

Food, Drink, and other consumables
----------------------------------

Many modern states regulate what substances citizens are and are
not allowed to put in their bodies. No alcohol or tobacco before
16/18/21/ever, no marijuana, LSD, MDMA, etc. You are allowed to
eat contaminated or expired food, but you are not allowed to
sell it. Certain foods are out-right deemed to dangerous by
certain counties, such as unwashed eggs and raw milk in the
United States. Others are deemed immoral: human flesh, foie
grass, veal, etc, and are legislated against accordingly.

To some this seems sensible, other such as Joel Salatin (author
of ``everything I want to do is illegal&#x27;&#x27;), argue that ``the
right to eat what you want&#x27;&#x27; should be a constitutional
guarantee on-par with the right to free-speech. Many of my
friends and associates who do not write books but do consume,
sell, or produce illicit substances, are of the opinion that, if
everyone involved in the procurement process consents, then the
government should ``stay out of it&#x27;&#x27;.

Private property
----------------

Private property is named such because it is yours. It opposes
public property which is owned by the state, or similar
entities. If you are not on your own private property, you have
to follow the rules of its rightful owner. Yet you are not
entirely free to choose what you do with your property either.

The most obvious example is zoning regulations. These laws
dictate which pieces of property are to be used for agriculture,
commerce, or residential purposes. You may be the sole rightful
owner of a piece of land, but that does not mean you may build a
house on it. Even if you are allowed to do so however, the house
must conform to certain standards set by the government. While
these laws (and indeed all the ones mentioned in this post) are
clearly designed to keep to populace safe, they also restrict
our freedoms. So I ask once again, should the lawmakers be in
the business of deciding what spaces you are allowed to live in?

----------------------------------------------------------------

I could keep going but I think my point has been made. There are
various areas of legislation which at some point in the past
were deemed sensible and important enough to be included in
major legal texts. Today, there are various areas of legislation
which seem sensible, but where an argument can be made that the
lawmakers should have nothing to say about them. Attitudes
surrounding these topics will change, and thinking about your
stances on these topics is important if you wish to anticipate
said change. What you consider fundamental today, may be
unlegislated tomorrow. Likewise, freedoms which we currently
enjoy in un(der)regulated areas may disappear some day soon,
when governments decide that, yes; this too is our business.
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://tilde.club/1/~user18130814200115/posts/0023-project-typewriter-2-0.txt</link>
<title>0023-project-typewriter-2-0.txt       2024-Jul-23 13:45     4.7 KB</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
Project Typewriter 2.0
Wed, 10 Jul 2024
Technology, Programming
=======================

I have, for some time now, been interested in developing some
sort of machine which is only capable of writing. Those who have
read my the previous iterations of this blog may remember the
typewriter which onto which I wired a USB output. The typewriter
itself is also such a system, one which allows me to record my
tough&#x27;s onto paper without the possibility for further
distractions. Today, I have developed a new system. It is by-far
the most usable one, which I am proving by writing this very post
on it (excuse the above-average amount of typos).

Before getting into how exactly this system works, let me outline
what it needs to be capable of doing. Any system on which I write
must of course have an input method as well as some sort of
feedback to the user. A screen, a piece of paper, potentially
even sound. Secondly, the system must be able to store the
written files in some digital manner. Lastly, I want to keep the
system as minimal as possible, preferably being able to run it
off a battery ban. It goes without saying that the system also
needs to be accurate and fast enough to keep up with my
(admittedly modest) typing speed.

Having outlined the requirements, let us get in to the latest
addition to my typing repertoire. This post is currently being
written on a raspberry pi 400 with a 2*16 LCD character display
attached. The raspberry pi 400, for those who do not know, is a
small fanless computer built entirely inside of a keyboard. I
will not go over all the specifications regarding the raspberry
pi, but what is important to note is how you can use the device
to driver various electronics The pi has access to 40 GPIO pins
which can be connected to motors, sensors, lights, etcetera,
which can then be controlled by software.

In this case, the object connected to the pi is an LCD character
display, which is capable of displaying a total of 30 characters
in beautiful black-on-green text. The display is driven by a
small python script which is indeed so simple, that calling it a
text-editor probably counts as a direct insult for anyone who has
ever actually worked on one. The script is divided into two parts
which operate independently of one another. This asynchronous
nature of the script is perhaps its most complicated feature,
which says a lot about how minimalist its feature set is. The
first part simple listens for key presses and stores the keys in
memory. If the backspace is pressed, the latest character is
removed from memory. When the return key is pressed, the current
line is saved to a file, at which point the program will proceed
to forget about it.

The second part of the program updates the display. The display
is rather slow and the driver will by-default wait for the
display to finish drawing before continuing with the script. This
is exactly why this part must be handled separately from the key
recording. If these were handled on the same thread, then
keystones would not be registered while the display was updating.
The display code therefore simply looks at the current working
string, formats it to fit on the 2*16 display, and sends it off
to the drawn.

That is really the extent of the editor. I added in a slight
quality-of-life addition in the ability to exit the program by
simply writing EXIT on an empty line. After doing so, a new file
will be created (its name determined by the date and time), and
the user&#x27;s input will now be written onto that file instead.

Obviously, these files must be taken off the internal SD card of
the pi and put onto an actual computer for editing and
publishing. Alternatively, you can attach a full monitor to the
pi itself and do all the work from there. It is after all a fully
functioning computer running Linux. This current iteration of my
``typewriter project&#x27;&#x27; will probably be the host of a number of
other blog posts. Writing on it gives a fun atmosphere, and the
entire setup is light, power efficient, and even usable in bright
daylight (unlike laptops or tablets). Unlike the actual
typewriter which I gave a usb port; this version actually
registers keystrokes consistently, is carry able with without a
briefcase, requires neither ink nor paper, and is not loud enough
to keep everybody in a 100 meter radius awake. I will miss the
typewriter somewhat, though with the improvements OCR is making
these days, I suppose I could just use it without the USB port.

Code as always is available on my GitHub [1], though keep in mind
that this is largely untested, unoptimized, and uncommented code.
If you have interest in building a system like this yourself
though, feel free to send me an email at blog@wester.digital.

-----------------------------------------------------------------

1: https://github.com/user18130814200115-2/LineWriter
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://tilde.club/1/~user18130814200115/posts/0022-oslos-public-transport-is-unfriendly-to-forgeiners.txt</link>
<title>0022-oslos-public-transport-is-unfr   2024-Jul-23 13:45     6.5 KB</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
Oslo&#x27;s public transport is unfriendly to foreigners
Sun, 07 Jul 2024
Travel, Opinion
===================================================

I have been living in Oslo for the past two years and there are
many good things I can say about the city. It is generally clean,
the people will largely not bother you, and it has great access
to many nature areas for recreation. These nature areas are best
reached by the public transport system which is largely excellent.

There are no gates, no complicated ticket types, subscriptions,
and discounts, the metro, bus, and tram drive rather frequently,
and you can even take the ferry with the same card. There are
however also many, many aspects of Oslo&#x27;s public transport which
rub me the wrong way. Instead of just listing my issues with the
system however, I will highlight specifically why these matters
are particularly detrimental to foreigners.

1. Tickets
----------

Oslo&#x27;s public transport network does not have ticket machines.
Instead, tickets are can be bought at various kiosks from four
particular chains, or at the half a dozen official outlets. This
is a huge problem for foreigners coming into the city for several
reasons.

Firstly, it is confusing. Ticket machines are rather universal
across Europe and most of the world. My process of visiting
cities is simple. I go to the train or metro stop, buy a day
pass, check out the map, and get on the next available train. In
Oslo, you show up to the metro and see... well nothing. There is
a small sign at most stops describing to you where you can buy
tickets (only in Norwegian and English), though there is no map
nor written instructions of the closest outlet. If you don&#x27;t know
the city well, you might need to walk around for quite some time
before finding one of these stores.

This leads into my second point. The ticket sale locations are
not distributed uniformly across the city. In fact, you don&#x27;t
even need to go very far outside of the commercial center before
you are in a ticket-dead-zone. There are many places within the
city where you need to walk at least an hour before encountering
a point of sale, even assuming you take the shortest route.

At this point I should mention that there is an alternative: a
mobile app. While it is great that you *can* use a mobile app
instead of a physical ticket, it does not alleviate the problems
listed above. You cannot assume that your passengers have mobile
data plans to download and use the app (yes, you need an active
internet connection in case of a ticket inspection, and there are
no mobile hotspots on board the vehicles nor at the stations),
you cannot assume that everyone has a smartphone with either
google play or the apple app store, nor for that matter can you
assume that all of your users have a credit card using either
Visa or MasterCard to pay for these tickets. While all these
elements are nigh-universal amongst the Norwegians, they are not
universal worldwide, therefore placing a greater burden on
tourists and other foreigners.

2. Times
--------

The Oslo public transport system is very spotty when it comes to
service after midnight. The metro and tram lines stop entirely
around 1, and the regular buses switch to night buses. These
night buses operate on different lines, with different times,
and are usually overcrowded with drunk Norwegian partygoers.

This is of course especially problematic if you are making your
way to or from the airport, placing yet another increased burden
on tourists.

3. Where am I going again?
--------------------------

All stations and stops for the bus, train, tram, and metro use
recognizable enough Norwegian names. These are rather well
diminishable from another in most cases.

There are however some major accessibility concerns. Firstly, the
displays showing the coming stops are very frequently broken,
especially on the buses. This is a problem because you need to
request the driver to stop at the next station by pressing a
button for both the bus and the tram. If you do not know what the
next stop is (because you are unfamiliar with the city), this
obviously becomes more difficult.

The name of the next stop is also called out by over a speaker,
however this system also has two problems. Firstly, and most
obviously, those who are hard of hearing will have no idea where
they are when the screens are non-functional (or if they also
have poor vision). Secondly, for those not used to the Norwegian
language, it can be very hard to put the sounds to words. Add to
that the fact that there are plenty of people who did not grow up
with the Latin alphabet, nor even a Germanic language, and you
are -- once again -- putting an extra burden on foreigners.

4. Inconsistency and information sharing
----------------------------------------

It happens relatively often that the public transport network
shuts down, most often due to weather conditions. This is perhaps
unavoidable, but what makes this problematic is the sharing of
information in such events.

Firstly, the information is often not updated. Rather, the next
train will just be pushed back 10 minutes with every 10 minutes
that pass. Locals have figured out by experience how to tell when
a train is likely never arriving, but for tourists and
immigrants, this is not the case.

Secondly, smaller stations will usually have a display simply
reading: ``check our website for updates&#x27;&#x27;. I mentioned above
that you cannot assume everyone to be in the possession of a
smartphone and an active internet connection. Bigger stations
tend to have spoken announcements about the state of things,
though these are only given in Norwegian.

And even if you manage to translate these messages, they usually
only state something along the lines of ``look for alternative
transport&#x27;&#x27;. They do not broadcast the number for a taxi company,
they don&#x27;t tell you how long you should expect to wait, whether
you will be refunded, etcetera. Once again, these are things the
locals have figured out by themselves over the years, and the
companies in charge seem to use this acquired knowledge as a
crutch of sorts, a crutch which falls apart when foreigners come
in to the frame.

-----------------------------------------------------------------

I have many more complaints about the way Norway disadvantages
foreigner workers, tourists, and students, but I will leave
things here for now. A country with the size and wealth of Norway
should be concerned with matters of accessibility in public
transport, and while I by no means believe Norway to be the worst
country in the regard, she too fails to meet the mark of
acceptable accessibility, at least for non-Norwegian passengers.
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://tilde.club/1/~user18130814200115/posts/0021-oslo#047s-public-transport-is-unfriendly-to-forgeiners.txt</link>
<title>0021-oslo's-public-transport-is-unf   2024-Jul-23 13:45     0.1 KB</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
Error: File or directory not found! (null)
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://tilde.club/1/~user18130814200115/posts/0020-miss-american-pie.txt</link>
<title>0020-miss-american-pie.txt            2024-Jul-23 13:45     8.5 KB</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
Miss American Pie
Wed, 12 Jun 2024
Music, Religion, Non-serious
============================

In Scott Alexander&#x27;s boom `Unsong&#x27; [1], one of the protagonists
gives an insightful analysis of the song ``American Pie&#x27;&#x27; and
its relation to ``Christian soteriology’s claim to supersede the
Jewish conception of divine law&#x27;&#x27;.

While Alexander, through the proxy of a fiction character,
provides an important addition to our understating of this
ancient work, his analysis is ultimately left somewhat wanting.
While the concept of Christian law superseding the law of the
old testament is an obvious core theme, the work as a whole
relates the histological development of Christianity as a
religion.

Our story starts in the garden of Eden

	Well, I know that you&#x27;re in love with him
	&#x27;Cause I saw you dancin&#x27; in the gym

As Alexander already pointed out, `gym&#x27; is the Greek word for
`naked&#x27;. This is a reference to Adam and Eve `dancing&#x27; naked in
the garden. Now, according to Alexander, `dance&#x27; refers to
divine judgement though the Hebrew `dan&#x27;. However, we should not
understand this line as Adam and Eve dealing out divine
judgement in the nude. Rather, to dance (in the context of this
work) refers to the following of God&#x27;s commandment (his
judgement). This is shown to us in the opening stanza:

	And I knew if I had my chance
	That I could make those people dance
	And maybe they&#x27;d be happy for a while	

The refrain shows us Israel before the arrival of Jesus.

	Drove my Chevy to the levee but the levee was dry

`Shevet&#x27; is the Hebrew word for tribe, and `levee&#x27; is therefore
indicative of the tribe of Levi who constituted the Jewish
priesthood. The tribe is found to be `dry&#x27;, they were too
obsessed with law and thereby lost true faith. This is
contrasted by new testament writings such as John 7

	Anyone who is thirsty may come to me! Anyone who believes in
	me may come and drink! For the Scriptures declare, `Rivers
	of living water will flow from the heart of anyone who
	believes in me.&#x27;

We are also told in the very next line that

	And them good ole boys were drinking whiskey &#x27;n rye

`Whiskey&#x27; comes from the Irish ``water of life&#x27;&#x27;. The fact that
the ``good ole boys&#x27;&#x27; were still drinking this means that Israel
has not gone completely off course. Notable characters who still
held true faith were of course Jesus&#x27; mother Mary, and his
cousin John the baptist.

Now we get to the arrival of Jesus, and the song quickly moves
on to his death. Jesus is the `music&#x27;, as pointed out by
Alexander, the first three letters of `song&#x27; spell `son&#x27;, but we
also have lines like these:

	Now do you believe in rock and roll?
	Can music save your mortal soul?

The belief in `rock and roll&#x27; is the rolling away of the boulder
from Jesus&#x27; tomb, signifying his resurrection. This is one of
the most core beliefs of Christians, and the is heavily
contested by other faiths which believe in Jesus as a prophet,
but not as God. Hence the next line: can Jesus save our soul?

But Jesus is not just called `music&#x27; he is also the jester, the
one who sings (therefore begetting the song), and later also
`the voice&#x27; this is indicative of the trinity.

	When the jester sang for the king and queen
	In a coat he borrowed from James Dean
	And a voice that came from you and me

We are told how God took away the sins of the world in a line
that also references the crown of thorns worn by Jesus before
his crucifixion. The coat is a reference to Jesus immaculate
coat which he wore on the cross and which was looted from him
shortly after his death. James Dean refers to Jesus&#x27; brother
James the Just, as Dean comes from the Hebrew `din&#x27; as mentioned
earlier.

	Oh, and while the king was looking down
	The jester stole his thorny crown

This also refers to the fact that Jesus was called ``King of the
Jews&#x27;&#x27;, but also that he is not the Messiah the Jewish people
expected. He was in fact not a conquering king here to establish
a Jewish state, hence he `stole&#x27; the crown.

When Jesus dies on the cross, the sins of the world are
forgiven, paid for by the blood of one free of sin.

	The courtroom was adjourned
	No verdict was returned

However, the Apostles were distraught at Jesus&#x27; death at first.
They thought their teacher and messiah had died, and they did
not have faith in his resurrection. They though the devil had
won, working through the Jews and Romans.

	I saw Satan laughing with delight
	The day the music died

-----------------------------------------------------------------

The majority of the remaining stanzas are dedicated to the
development of Christianity after Jesus&#x27; death:

	Now for ten years we&#x27;ve been on our own
	And moss grows fat on a rollin&#x27; stone

Jesus has resurrected and we are now some time after his death,
Christians are uniting and canonizing the Bible. There is one
faith meant for all people, Jews and Pharisees alike (in the
strictest sense of the world, this is a catholic faith).

	Now the halftime air was sweet perfume
	While the sergeants played a marching tune
	We all got up to dance
	Oh, but we never got the chance

This period is referred as the halftime, because our story is
far from over, in fact, it is only halfway done. ``Sweet
perfume&#x27;&#x27; may be a reference to Mary&#x27;s anointing of Jesus&#x27; feet
with perfume in John 12:3. The people were ready for the day of
judgement to come, they git up to dance (to be judged), but they
never got the chance because the story is not done, the people
are not united in the true faith of Jesus, rather, they have
once again lost their way.

	&#x27;Cause the players tried to take the field
	The marching band refused to yield
	Do you recall what was revealed
	The day the music died?

The players, common everyday believers tried to take the field,
but the marching band (the church establishment) didn&#x27;t let
them. This is a reference to the protestant reformists wanting
to take biblical reading and contemplation to the common people,
and sermons in local languages.

The day Jesus died, the temple veil was torn, this is where God
reportedly resided, his face must remain unseen because gazing
upon it would spell death for any person not free from sin. But
when Jesus died, the face of God was revealed (it was the face
of Jesus), and all could gaze upon it because all sins were
forgiven. Thus, the face of God was no longer reserved for the
highest priest (who could occasionally journey behind the veil
to either emerge proven pure, or die trying), rather he could be
seen by anyone.

The reformists therefore want religion to belong to all the
players, not just to the marching band.

-----------------------------------------------------------------

Now we come to the discussion of the end times. The time when
Jesus will return to earth to judge everyone. Before this
happens however, there will be many fake prophets and people
promising salvation.

	Oh, and as I watched him on the stage
	My hands were clenched in fists of rage
	No angel born in Hell
	Could break that Satan&#x27;s spell

When judged by Jesus, there is no going back. According to the
Bible (at least to most common interpretations I am familiar
with), Jesus&#x27; return is the last chance to accept him. The
protagonist of American Pie seemingly does not do so, and is
thus left without music.

	I met a girl who sang the blues
	And I asked her for some happy news [gospel]
	But she just smiled and turned away
	I went down to the sacred store [Jerusalem]
	Where I&#x27;d heard the music years before
	But the man there said the music wouldn&#x27;t play

In the following stanza, we are described the people who do make
it into the kingdom of heaven, the great city described in the
bible.

	And in the streets, the children screamed
	The lovers cried and the poets dreamed

Jesus tells his followers that they must become like children in
Mathew 18:3, that they must love the lord with all their heart
in Mathew 22:37, and Jesus teaches us how to pray in the Gospels
as well, proclaiming the glory of God like poets. These are the
people who make their way into heaven.

	But not a word was spoken
	The church bells all were broken

In this city, the people won&#x27;t be called to church because God
will be amongst them. He will come to your house, not you to
his.

The song concludes with the departure of the tripartite God to
the kingdom, letting the meet inherit the earth.

	And the three men I admire most
	The Father, Son and the Holy Ghost
	They caught the last train for the coast
	The day the music died

Importantly, this all happened ``the day the music died&#x27;&#x27;, in
other words, as soon as the sins of the world were taken away,
the story was decided. Now we are just waiting for it to play
out the way it was meant to.


[1]: Accessible for free on the web at unsongbook.com
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://tilde.club/1/~user18130814200115/posts/0018-academic-references-to-icelandic-authors.txt</link>
<title>0018-academic-references-to-iceland   2024-Jul-23 13:45     3.2 KB</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
Academic references to Icelandic authors
Thu, 25 Apr 2024
Academia, LaTeX
========================================

Academic references and citations are notoriously finicky to
handle. This is exactly why systems like biblatex exist to
automate the process. For the uninitiated, biblatex allows you
to define a reference in a file like so:

	@book{key,
		author = {},
		title = {},
		date = {},
		publisher = {}
	}

This is a rather limited example, but there are more fields
available. Now, by simply writing \cite{key} in your latex
document, you get a nice inline citation according to your
chosen style -- for instance (author&#x27;s last name year) -- and a
bibliography entry containing all the relevant information at
the end of your document.

I recently ran into a problem with this system however exactly
because the author is cited by their last name, and Icelandic
people do not have last names in the same way as most people do.

On Iceland, it is typical for people to receive as their ``last
name&#x27;&#x27; the name of the parent matching their gender, plus the
suffix `son&#x27; or `dóttir&#x27; or a variation on these two (it get&#x27;s
more complicated, but this will do for now). Think of Lord of
the Rings, where Thorin (oakenshield)&#x27;s full name is Thorin, son
of Thror, son of Thrain. On Iceland he would be called Thorin
Throrson, and his father would be Thror Thrainson.

To refer to these people by their last name is a little strange.
``The king under the mountain is Thror&#x27;s son&#x27;&#x27;. Therefore, it is
somewhat common to cite Icelandic people by their first name(s)
instead.

Getting a citation like this in biblatex turned out to be a
little tricky, especially when you don&#x27;t want to write a custom
citation function. This post will detail what I did, for others
to copy.

-----------------------------------------------------------------

Firstly, In your .bib file you do the following:

	@book{key,
		author = {{Thorin Throrson}}, % Mind the double braces
		shorthand = {Thorin},
		keywords = {icelandic}
	}

The braces in the author field tell biblatex to cite the name in
full, rather than separating the first and last parts. The
shorthand tells it to use only `Thorin&#x27; for inline citations.
The keyword will be useful for separating out Icelandic names
from other abbreviations.

Usually, the shorthand field is often used when citing several
texts by the same author, especially if both texts are cited
frequently. In a paper about Kant, it is not particularly
helpful to constantly see (Kant 1781) and (Kant 1790). If on the
other hand, we use the abbreviated titles (KdRV) and (KdU), the
reader ends up much better informed. These abbreviations are then
listed at the end of the document using 

	\printbiblist{shorthand}

If this list is used then -- with the current setup -- this
would also include all of our Icelandic first names, which we
defined as abbreviations. This is where the defined keyword
comes in, which allows us to exclude these `abbreviations&#x27;

	\printbiblist[
		notkeyword=icelandic
	]{shorthand}

There may be better ways of doing this in Latex. In fact, I can
think of several ways to automate this process, but this is the
most simple and portable way I found of doing things, and it
importantly works with many versions of (bib)latex.
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://tilde.club/1/~user18130814200115/posts/0017-re-fierce-appetites.txt</link>
<title>0017-re-fierce-appetites.txt          2024-Jul-23 13:45     5.0 KB</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
RE: Fierce Appetites
Thu, 04 Apr 2024
Book review, Opinion
====================

``Fierce Appetites&#x27;&#x27; is a memoir written by Elizabeth Boyle, an
Irish historian who relates her experiences of the past 4
decades to various writings surviving from medieval times.

There... was that so hard to put on the cover of the book?

-----------------------------------------------------------------

This book was given to me by a friend when she had to move back
to her home country after an exchange year at my university.
This book, as I alluded to above, markets itself horribly.

The cover, which is what all of us judge a book on, contains
four main elements:
1. The title ``fierce appetites which does not really tell you
   much about the book at all.
2. A subtitle reading ``Lessons from my year of untamed
   thinking&#x27;&#x27;, this is both uninformative and wrong, more on
   that later.
3. A medieval-style drawing of a man and a woman in reclined
   embrace. Given this, one might expect a book akin to the kama
   sutra, but no. Hence: uninformative.
4. No less than thirteen exclamations of praise with another
   seven on the inside cover.


Let me start with this last point. The 20 sentences expressing
how much others enjoyed this book add absolutely no value.
Firstly, I don&#x27;t recognize any of the names on the cover, and I
would consider myself a moderately well-read person.
Furthermore, all of the listed people seemed to be in a
competition to write the least informative phrase possible while
also showing off their own erudition.

``Pure nectar for the imagination&#x27;&#x27; ... Uhm, okay. I wouldn&#x27;t
consider a memoir to be the thing to read if you want to let
your imagination loose, but I guess this is fine.

``Like nothing else you will ever read&#x27;&#x27; This one made me
think whether everyone listed on the cover even read the book.
This is such a cookie-cutter response (and furthermore in
all-likelihood just wrong, or at least over-the-top) that you
can say it about any book without even taking the time to read
it.

``I loved this luminous, radical book about bodies in time&#x27;&#x27;
This one made me wonder too. There is one chapter about bodies
yes, but that certainly is not what this book is about. Did you
do the homework Mr and Mrs EXAMINER

``Fiercely smart, strange, surmising, unsettling, and
unflinching&#x27;&#x27; Yeah, lets just cover all bases here, one of them
has to apply right?

Other quotes contain words as informative as `interesting&#x27;,
`good&#x27;, `intriguing&#x27;, and `wonderful&#x27;.


Let&#x27;s move to the title and subtitle. Firstly ``fierce
appetites&#x27;&#x27;, is that what this book is about? The first few
chapters deal with the loss of a loved one... Nothing appetizing
there. Substance abuse is covered, I suppose addiction is a type
of appetite at least. Religion... If I squint this fits. But
parenting, lockdowns, academia and war?

The subtitle is inaccurate. This book is in fact not ``lessons
from a year of untamed thinking&#x27;&#x27;. The book is laid out in
twelve chapters with names matching the months of the year, but
that about as far as the connection goes. Some months do
correspond to events that actually happened in that year in that
month, but most of them are just random events that occurred
throughout the author&#x27;s life. `Untamed thinking&#x27;&#x27; is not
mentioned once, in fact the author reveals that she wasn&#x27;t
approached about the book until later on in the year, even
though the book starts in January. Lastly, there are no
`lessons&#x27;. In fact, the author seems intent on not teaching any
life lessons, but rather to point out how her life is falling
apart and being held together only by medication, alcoholism,
and unrestrained sexual behaviour.


So... The cover is not useful. The layout of the book is
strange, and does not correspond with the content. The title and
subtitle are just plain wrong (though the subtitle was changed
to a more informative phrase in later editions). But why get so
upset over it? I will tell you why: because this is a good book.
Not a great book, but certainly worth a quick read. And I feel
as though this is a great example of good writing being held
back by horrible editing.

Clearly the editor had an idea. They read the book and the
drafts and extracted from it `lessons&#x27; about ``fierce
appetites&#x27;&#x27;. They decided to layout the book in a diary-format,
with each chapter being one month, and fit the subtitle to that
idea (or even worse: the other way around). I don&#x27;t feel as
though these editorial decisions were made with the style of the
author in mind. There are so many ways in which the content of
the book and the editing could be made to fit better, but as it
stands, the book is held back by the person in charge of selling
the story inside.

-----------------------------------------------------------------

It is a few days later now and I check some of the books I have
with me for similar patterns. Certainly the proclamations by
other authors often lack substance, but I would still say that
Fierce Appetites is a particularly bad example. Not least
because of the sheer number of quotations on the cover.
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://tilde.club/1/~user18130814200115/posts/0016-consult-your-physician.txt</link>
<title>0016-consult-your-physician.txt       2024-Jul-23 13:45     5.4 KB</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
Consult your Physician
Fri, 15 Mar 2024
Opinion
======================

I keep occasionally running into disclaimers that profess
something along these lines:

&gt; Before partaking in this exercise, please consult a physician
&gt; ... It requires both mental and physical strength ... Ensure
&gt; you are in good health ... Know your limits ... You are at
&gt; risk of personal injury ... COMPANY NAME is not liable for any
&gt; damages ... etcetera

Pretty intense right? The above is paraphrased from a 142 word
disclaimer at the start of an exercise video on YouTube. What
exercise was the video instructing on? Was it skydiving? Free
solo rock climbing? Perhaps it wasn&#x27;t exercise in a traditional
sense, but activities such as skin-hooking. Or maybe this was
some insane strongman routine, including deadlifts, atlas
stones, and other high-risk motions.

The truth is much more mundane. This video described a 10 minute
stretching routine designed to be performed while laying down in
bed. Excuse me? This required such a scary build up?

Another example:
&gt; Before making any dietary changes consult your doctor ...
&gt; Unintended side effects ... Potential miscarriage ...
&gt; Permanent health damage ... Is not liable for any damages ...
&gt; Continue at your own risk ... and so forth

What warning was this for you might ask? Steroids? Super
restrictive diets such as veganism or ketogentic diets? Foods
aimed at diabetics? Pregnant people?

No, this was a article overviewing some herbal teas, notably
nettle tea.

-----------------------------------------------------------------

I see these disclaimers relatively often, especially on
incredibly mediocre things. Whereas extreme exercise and diets
are promoted without medical backing. I feel as though these
disclaimers have lost track of reality, and in this post; I will
complain about them.

Now, let me start with a disclaimer of my own: I understand why
these walls of warning text are included in videos and articles.
They simply wish to void any liabilities for damage because
human stupidity knows no bounds, and because the United States
legal system knows fewer bounds still.

But come on... Ten minutes of stretching? Herbal tea? Meanwhile
there are no health labels on sodas or super processed foods
which are proven to have health aversive effects. A sedentary
lifestyle is *almost* guaranteed to be more damaging than one
which includes light exercise or stretching.

Now, if this was just independent bloggers and small companies
being overly cautious, that would be one thing, but
unfortunately this all goes much deeper. I do a lot of rock
climbing, mostly indoors. At all but one of the gyms I have been
to throughout Europe, I needed to sign a waiver stating that the
gym would not be responsible for injuries. Fair enough. In Italy
however, I needed a certificate signed by a doctor that I was
fit enough to exercise.

When I was asked to present this certificate I was baffled at
first. I was later assured by many people that this is common
for nearly all gyms in Italy, both climbing gyms and otherwise.
How backwards is this? ``You are not fir enough to exercise&#x27;&#x27;?
Meanwhile you can try your best at merging with your sofa
without any form of medical assessment as to the risk you are
exposing yourself to.

----------------------------------------------------------------

I feel as though this is a worrying symptom of a much wider
problem which can roughly be characterized as: ``people can no
longer take care of themselves&#x27;&#x27;. Simple, rather mediocre
decisions, such as what tea to drink, must be made for you. You
should never be within two meters of a body of water without a
trained professional nearby. Careful with those stretches, you
might just rip off your limbs altogether.

At the same time, everyone is self-medicating with actually
harmful medication such as melatonin and painkillers, knowing
nothing about how to actually use these drugs. When people grow
sedentary and fat, that is within their freedom to do, but if
you wish to live alternatively, you better ask the government
official nicely first.

I am reminded of Aldous Huxley&#x27;s wonderful work ``A brave new
world&#x27;&#x27;. Where the totalitarian government aims to keep its
citizens in a perpetually immature state. No one makes their own
choices, and everyone drugs themselves up before any discomfort
can reach them.

I hope that we can change our social-, and legal- structures in
such a way that we can assume that those around us are
responsible human beings capable of looking after themselves. So
that we can share simple things such as recipes and exercises
without needing to be afraid that someone manages to drown
themselves in the soup we instructed them to make, or get
horribly injured by following our closed-eye meditation
instructions while driving. Unfortunately, this does not seem to
be the direction we are heading in... so in that light:

========================== DISCLAIMER ==========================
I am not a lawyer, I am not a doctor, I am not a politician.
This is not legal/medical/social advice.  In the worst case
scenario, my writings may even induce some semblance of
independent thought which has been shown to lead to:
- Social extrication
- Political radicalization
- Migraines
- Death
- An aversion to pine cones
- A substantial drop in birth-rates
- Self-harm
- General life improvement and/or psychosis 
I am not to be held accountable for these -- or any other --
effects my writings inspire.
================================================================
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://tilde.club/1/~user18130814200115/posts/0015-the-material-analysis.ref</link>
<title>0015-the-material-analysis.ref        2024-Jul-23 13:45     0.1 KB</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
The material analysis
Autumn 2023
Academic papers, Philosophy of language
papers/language-1-1.pdf
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://tilde.club/1/~user18130814200115/posts/0014-climate-change-and-cultural-change.ref</link>
<title>0014-climate-change-and-cultural-ch   2024-Jul-23 13:45     0.1 KB</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
Climate change and Cultural Change
Autumn 2023
Academic papers, Ethics of Climate change
papers/climate-1-1.pdf
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://tilde.club/1/~user18130814200115/posts/0013-middle-english-exam.ref</link>
<title>0013-middle-english-exam.ref          2024-Jul-23 13:45     0.1 KB</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
Middle English Exam
Autumn 2023
Academic papers, Middle English, Dialectology and Manuscript studies
papers/middle-english-1-2.pdf
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://tilde.club/1/~user18130814200115/posts/0012-middle-english-localisation-of-piers-plowman.ref</link>
<title>0012-middle-english-localisation-of   2024-Jul-23 13:45     0.1 KB</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
Middle English localisation of Piers Plowman
Autumn 2023
Academic papers, Middle English, Dialectology
papers/middle-english-1-1.pdf
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://tilde.club/1/~user18130814200115/posts/0011-french.txt</link>
<title>0011-french.txt                       2024-Jul-23 13:45     5.5 KB</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
French
Fri, 16 Feb 2024
Academia
================

I studied French for five years (give or take one) in ``middle
school&#x27;&#x27; (Dutch middle school combines the American middle school
and high school into one, that is to say, I had French classes
from age 11 till 16). I was allowed to drop French in the fifth
year due to my dyslexia and would have otherwise had six years in
total.

I -- like most people how had any foreign language in school --
remember very little of my French classes. Most of them focussed
on grammar and literature, which are two aspects I know nothing
about even in my native languages. The only knowledge I retained
of French were the useful phrases picked up in the first year (my
name is, I don&#x27;t speak French very well, can you slow down, where
is the supermarket/hospital/pharmacy, etcetera).

Just in case anyone was wondering, this is the same for people
who dropped French after two years in favour of German, Latin, or
Greek, and for people who pursued French for the full six year
program.

After graduating, i spent some time in France, and most of my
actually useful French knowledge came from that brief period.
Needless to say, when I encountered a potential source of my
masters dissertation written in French, I was not exactly
ecstatic about translating it. The paper seemed at first glance
to be very useful however, so I made a cup of tea, grabbed my
notebooks and tablet, and set off towards the study room in my
village.

-----------------------------------------------------------------

The paper I was translating is titled ``Valeur critique de la
mystique plotienne&#x27;&#x27; by Jean Troulliard. This is a highly
specialized work containing lots of Neoplatonic jargon and a fair
amount of ancient Greek and Latin. Also, did I mention that
`translation&#x27; was a course reserved for 6th year Frech? The year
I happened to drop?

Luckily, there are many tools these days to facilitate
translation. Large language models are an order of magnitude more
adept at translation compared to traditional digital methods such
as google translate, and the availability of digital online
dictionaries further facilitates the process.

The first problem I had to solve however was getting the document
in a machine readable format. I possessed only a scan of the
document which I put through an Optical Character Recognition
(OCR) program to get the paper in text from. This was actually
fairly accurate. The program struggled slightly with the French
quotation marks &lt;&lt; and &gt;&gt;, and it completely botched the Greek,
footnote markers, and occasionally interpreted a speck on the
lens as a period or comma.

So I went through the entire document first in French, doing an
instal pass on the spelling, punctuation, and transcribing all
the Greek parts by hand.

I then fed this data in its entirety to Chat GPT (it is 2024
after all) and put that output into a latex document.

I went thought his document as I normally do, reading and
annotating important parts whist making notes in my physical
notebook for the sake of redundancy. Having already made a pass
on the original French, I felt as though this went a lot faster
than normal. While reading, I also improved the automatic
translation here and there, mostly breaking up sentence
structures which appeared rather obtuse in English, and fixing
some mistakes the LLM made with philosophical jargon. For this
step I was assisted by someone more versed in the romance
languages and French in particular, which proved not entirely
necessary, but certainly improved the translation at the end.

Whist reading, I noticed I was being a lot more critical.
Usually when reading paper like these, I just take what the
author says for granted while reading (unless it is particularly
outrageous) and reflect critically at a later date. Now however,
I found myself scrutinizing every line -- primarily for
translation errors, but therefore also picking out lines which
did not seem in-line with what I knew of the Neoplatonic
tradition.

At the end of the day, i spent nearly six hours reading 10 pages
of text, only ~12 times slower than my usual speed. Great
success.

What stood out to me most about this exercise is how enjoyable
and educative it was. Wanting to actually read the paper did
wonders for my motivation, whereas reading French ``high
literature&#x27;&#x27; in middle school was always a drag. Furthermore, I
learned more about French sentence structure in these six hours
than in five years of classes, and I doubt the sixth year would
have helped much either. Having to transcribe the Greek by hand
did wonders for my comprehension of the alphabet (which used to
be shoddy at best, but is now shoddy at worst), and the whole
project made me much more excited about reading French texts in
the Future.

-----------------------------------------------------------------

All of that is to say: (middle) school language classes (and
classes in many other areas for that matter) have failed me and
almost everyone I know. They both fail to actually teach, and
suck so much joy out of learning that people develop permanent
aversions towards certain topics. I was convinced by my teachers
that I was not good at languages. Now I am fluent in two, capable
in two others, and a beginner in yet another pair, whist knowing
phrases and basics for a handful of languages in various
families.

I sincerely hope that the educational system has improved since I
left, but given that its main focus currently seems to be
`modernizing&#x27; -- id est: giving 4 year olds personal laptops
and/or tablets, so they can stay glued to a screen even at school
-- I am not expecting much.
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://tilde.club/1/~user18130814200115/posts/0010-mr-trashman-bring-me-a-mac-mini.txt</link>
<title>0010-mr-trashman-bring-me-a-mac-min   2024-Jul-23 13:45     3.7 KB</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
Mr Trashman, bring me a... mac mini?
Tue, 06 Feb 2024
Environmentalism, Technology
====================================

Just the other day, I took a trip (less than 15 meters) to the
local e-waste disposal site. Unfortunately, the screen of my
ereader broke a while back. After letting my old friend collect
dust for a month or so, I decided to finally put him to rest and
commit him to the recycling bin.

While I was there however, something caught my attention from the
corner of my eye: an Apple mac mini. It looked in pretty good
condition, so I decided to take it home to see if I could repair
it, or otherwise strip it for parts. Luckily, the previous owner
had thrown away the power cord as well, so i took that too.

Upon getting home, I hooked the mac up to the only HDMI display
in my house: The living room TV and pressed the power button.
Much to my surprise, the machine started up straight away and I
was greeted by Mac OSX snow leopard. Yea... This thing was pretty
old, but I&#x27;ll get back to that later.

The system logged in automatically, and I was greeted by the
classic purple galaxy background and a desktop filled with
someone else&#x27;s personal files. I set my sights on factory
resetting the mac, as I felt it rather unethical to dig through
the other person&#x27;s accounts and files. Resting the mac proved
rather difficult, as I had no password, and the recovery
partition was missing.

No matter, I happen to know a little trick for breaking in to
macs from the time when I used to have a macbook (which, much
like this mac mini, was also from 2010). Simply enter the shell
during startup by holding command+S, mount the disk and remove
the file /var/db/.applesetupdone. This allows you to make a new
administrator account on the next startup. Which, may I just say,
is a stupidly easy way of bypassing password protections,
especially on a product made by a company which prides itself on
security. I will just assume that this exploit is fixed in later
versions of OSX.

Anyway, now that I had an admin account, I could start exploring
the OS. The first thing I noticed was that basically the entire
internet was not working. Or rather https was not working. Safari
gave me very helpful error messages such as ``failed to
establish a connection to ...&#x27;&#x27; while Chrome told me the clock
was set wrong (it wasn&#x27;t). The problem was of course that the
certificates expired, since the OS was not updated in over a
decade.

I managed to get the certificates from curl, and add to the
keycain using a little shell script. At this point I did realize
why the original owner thew the thing away though. This is not a
problem that is easy to diagnose for a non-tech-savvy person, let
alone fix.

Next, I started looking for a more up-to-date browser. The
version of safari on this thing could not render most modern web
pages (though of course my website and many other small-web
pages loaded just fine). I found a number of discontinued
projects before settling on Interweb. This one was also
discontinued, though it was the most recently updated one.

After all of that the OS works... Not great exactly. It is
remarkably snappy given how many animations and shaders the
desktop environment has, but the software stack from 2010 is just
not usable, at this point it is just a DVD player.

I will probably try to get Linux running, and I did see an some
DDR3 ram sticks for sale second hand for only around 10 euros, so
I might see if this could be a capable enough little media
server.  If not, a media server, I might set it up with ssh and
just run the thing headless. Having a non-cloud based wireless
backup for my thesis and other important documents would be nice,
even if it is on spinning rust. Now that I think about it, that
would be very simple to do, even under OSX.
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://tilde.club/1/~user18130814200115/posts/0009-what-no-one-told-me-about-veganism.txt</link>
<title>0009-what-no-one-told-me-about-vega   2024-Jul-23 13:45     3.9 KB</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
What no one told me about Veganism
Mon, 22 Jan 2024
Lifestyle
==================================

I became a pescetarian at age 11, following in the footsteps of
my older sister, who I though was rather cool for making the same
choice just a few months earlier. Years later, at age 22, I
followed in the footsteps of another rather cool woman and became
vegan.

Now, due to my long history of eating a somewhat
restricted diet, I do not have the problems most people report
when switching to veganism or vegetarianism. I do not struggle
with the desire to eat meat, nor do I consider vegan meals sad or
unsatisfying. Also, even while I was pescetarian, I enjoyed most
the flavours brought by the vegetables, though I did eat a
considerable amount of cheese and eggs.

Regardless, switching to veganism was not that difficult for me.
I couldn&#x27;t really afford to buy fish, this entire country is
devoid of actually flavourful cheese, I use soy milk for its
longer shelf-life, and I can live without eggs. Some difficulties
arose when it came to eating out, or getting ready-made meals
from the supermarket, though these were minor gripes compared to
the thing I will complain about today: Vegan foods, are not
energy dense.

-----------------------------------------------------------------

Ever since I became vegan, my meal sized have doubled in size,
and that is not an exaggeration. I try my best to include many
energy dense items such as nuts, oils, and legumes, but I still
find myself chewing down mountains of food.

All of this food is rather exhausting to prepare. For instance, I
went from egg-cheese-tomato sandwiches and alike for lunch to
cooked meals, as the only lunch-appropriate sandwich
accoutrements are humus and vegetables. Furthermore, the sheer
volume means more time spent chopping, frying, boiling, and
roasting. Which does not even address the fact that vegetables
generally just have longer cook times (you can of course eat them
raw though).

Aside from energy spent preparing, the energy and time I spent
eating and digesting has also increased quite drastically. And I
frequently end up with a full stomach, whist also knowing
full-well that I am not nutritionally satisfied.

At this point I should mention a few confounding factors.
Firstly, I am trying to gain weight, which definitely exaggerates
the portion problems. Secondly, I work out rather frequently and
I work a rather intense manual labour job. All of this is on top
of university work, and the brain is a rather calorie intensive
organ.

However, when I bring these matters up to other vegans I receive
many similar stories. At the end of the day, non-vegan foods are
just more dense, and their general lack of fiber allows for
easier digestion (and fewer toilet breaks) for better and for
worse.

-----------------------------------------------------------------

I will not be returning to Pescetarianism, not will I go full
omnivore or vegetarian, I am happy with my choice, and I do
generally feel better. I do however wish I knew about this
problem before I made the switch. As such, for any prospective
vegans out there: Consider how much time you have to cook,
consider how much time you have to eat, consider how many
bathroom breaks you can afford. Above all though, consider how I
had to increase my time budget for all of these threefold and how
I am still content with my decision.

Lastly, I will mention that there is a period of adjustment. In
the first few weeks of vegan weight gain at maximum exercise and
work, my body was destroyed and I could barely get up after a
meal, even if I spread it out over several hours. Now though, my
body seems much better adjusted to this way of life. I can eat a
meal without needing to sleep right after. I have gotten better
at cooking and incorporating energy-dense ingredients (boil your
rice with yellow lentils and almonds *game changer*), and my
digestive system seems to have adapted to the massive increase in
fiber without a massive increase in flatulence.
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://tilde.club/1/~user18130814200115/posts/0008-appeal-to-nature.txt</link>
<title>0008-appeal-to-nature.txt             2024-Jul-23 13:45     4.3 KB</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
Appeal to Nature
Thu, 11 Jan 2024
Opinion, Lifestyle
================

An appeal to nature is a argumentative fallacy where something is
assumed to be good because it is natural. For a long time as a
young child and early adolescent, I have been guilty of employing
this line of reasoning in many decisions regarding my lifestyle.
I suspect this mode of thinking is something I inherited form my
parents.

As I grew older and become a teenager, I started to question the
teachings of my parents, and one of the things which was
addressed were the many appeals to nature made in my
life-choices. Now that I am yet-again older, I decided that, at
age 14 -- wile pumping hormones and sleeping 11 hours
per afternoon -- I was likely not smarter than my parents,
teachers, government, etcetera. Since discovering this
ground-shaking fact, I have made an effort to try an rethink
every decision or pattern-of-thought which I started in that
period, and as-such, the appeal to nature reared its head again.

Let me use an example: getting a cold. My parents would address
this annual issue by making me take rest, hot-baths, much sleep,
and otherwise letting my body take care of itself. This approach
is contrasted by the alternative of using medication to squash
the disease. Of course, there are many grades between these two,
but that is not exactly relevant at the moment. As a child, I
would not be given medicine unless a cold was sufficiently bad, I
am sure my parents had various metrics for this, such as duration
or fever, and I do not question their judgement as they are both
smart people, and since my mother has extensive medical training.

As an adult, I am the one to decide whether I take medicine,
hot-baths, or whether I afford myself an afternoon off. This
problem is compounded by the fact that I have grown a lot more
sickly these past few years, likely due an increase in travel as
well as living in a student dorm with a rotating selection of
international viruses. Now, I have never been a fan of taking
medicine for minor illnesses like colds, though I am even less
inclined to being sick, and I cannot stand bed-rest for more than
24 hours.

One thing which still remains in the back of my mind as I am
deciding whether to opt for medicine or not, is the idea that I
can just let my immune system handle it ``naturally&#x27;&#x27;. The
supposedly fallacious appeal to nature still has a strong pull,
despite the fact that every learned person tells me this is
wrong. Upon revisiting my stance on this, I came to a conclusion:
an appeal to nature is not necessarily fallacious, though it must
be understood in the proper manner.

I came to this conclusion because relying on ``natural&#x27;&#x27; things
(as opposed to artificial ones) generally does a great job at
keeping me safe. The reason for this is, I believe, the fact that
natural things have stood the test of time. If research came out
tomorrow stating that vegetables such as zucchini or pumpkin
(which humans have eaten for generations) are actually
unequivocally harmful, then I would doubt that research before I
doubt the squash family. Likewise, I rather more distrust
medicines which were invented recently and tested ``only&#x27;&#x27; for
about a year, as opposed to natural remedies such as rest or
herbal medicines which have stood the test of time. Of course,
the artificial medicine is likely much more effective, though it
is statistically more likely to have negative side-effects too.

Looking at appeals to nature in this manner, where they are
really appeals to endurance, I think my choices become much more
clear. Natural remedies have proven themselves over time to deal
with colds just fine. At the same time, we cannot extend this to
more serious infections such as bacterial meningitis, which has
proven itself to be quite deadly when left to nature.

Taking this idea outside of medicine I think it also applies very
well. Every day, I hear new research come out about processed
foods, sugar, tobacco and about how damaging they are. While many
of these products supposedly had scientific backing with
peer-reviewed double-blind studies, we now know these studies are
basically bought-off by large corporations. Things which have
stood the test of time however such as vegetables, fruits, herbs,
and such are unlikely to have been bought-off by some ancient
conglomerate aiming to sell more nutrients.
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://tilde.club/1/~user18130814200115/posts/0007-christmas-bonus.txt</link>
<title>0007-christmas-bonus.txt              2024-Jul-23 13:45     4.7 KB</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
Christmas bonus
Mon, 15 Jan 2024
Opinion, Lifestyle
===============

Recently, I got a fairly sizable Christmas bonus from the
restaurant where I work part time. This bonus came in the form of
a so-called &quot;universal gift card&quot;.  This &quot;universal&quot; gift card
was in fact not universal in any meaningful sense of the word. I
know if the existence of actual universal gift cards which are
just prepaid VISA or MasterCards which you can use at any store
or even online. This gift card on the other hand is simply one
which can be used in roughly 6000 stores throughout the country.
They are not usable online, nor in other countries. To make long
story short: they are not universal in the slightest.

Given then, the small selectional stores, combined with the
fairly high value of the card, I started thinking about what to
spend this it on. At first my mind went to clothing. The card is
usable in H&amp;M and many other clothing stores, though I quickly
realized that most of my clothing is still quite adequate and I
do not need to buy anything new, though I could potentially use
another formal outfit. Secondly my mind went to home decoration.
There are quite a few places on the 6000 &quot;universal&quot; list where I
can buy candles, plants, picture-frames or any such items. Though
my apartment is already adequately decorated. The card is also
usable in various consumer electronic stores where I could buy
things like wireless headsets, wireless earphones, or an android
TV box for my living room. Once again, I realized that I would
not I bought these things under any other circumstance and
getting a gift card like this.

On the one hand that is rather nice. Getting this gift card
allowed me to treat myself in ways I wouldn&#x27;t usually. In this
regard the card is much the same as most other gifts I received
this season. My family gave me a set of books, which I would
usually not have bought, at the very least not in physical copy.
On the other hand, I feel like this card is encouraging needless
consumerism in much the same way as gift-giving holidays tend to
do. Historically, whenever Christmas, Valentines, or my birthday
came around, I set about the monumental task of coming up with a
gift for myself. In recent years I have stopped doing this under
the morale ``if I have to think long and hard about what I want,
then those are not things I need&#x27;&#x27;. I am lucky in the fact that
my partner agrees with me on this matter, and as-such, we don&#x27;t
give each other gifts at all, unromantic as that may seem to
people. The wider family is however not yet on board, making the
build-up to many holidays a question of what would be nice gifts
which are also things we already would buy regardless (socks and
underwear are frequent items).

Going back to the Christmas bonus then: If I had just received
value of the card as an addition to my paycheck I would have
spent the money in the more utilitarian manner. Though I don&#x27;t
think that would have felt very much like a gift. For the same
reason, I do not just want to sell the card for someone else and
save up the money earned or invest it; I am really rather at a
loss for what to to.

As a quick aside, I completely understand why my employer decided
to give the Christmas bonus this way. There’s always the slight
apprehension of people to give money. And furthermore I assume
that this method has many tax benefits as opposed to increasing
the paycheck for December.

While looking over all the eligible stores, I noticed that the
gift card is also usable at select supermarkets. Using the card
in this manner I can just use it to reduce my monthly expenses
while staying roughly equally utilitarian. The supermarkets are
of course the most expensive ones in town, rather than those I
typically go to. And besides, I think it would be rather more fun
to spend this gift on a singular big purchase which lasts some
time, rather than a few weeks of ever temporary groceries.

Currently, the approach that I feel most strong towards is using
the card itself for groceries while setting aside the value of
the card in actual money for a purchase of my choosing at a
store of my choosing in a country of my choosing. This would
basically translate the gift card into an actual universal one by
using it on something I would already spend money on. At that
point, many more appealing options open up to me, including using
the money to go out for dinner, take a vacation, or donate to
charity.

I am open to suggestions though. I am particularly curious how
others reconcile the notion that gifts must be ``something nice&#x27;&#x27;
in contrast to a usual pattern of frugal-, utilitarian- spending.
This goes for cards like these, but also for generic gifts such
as those given for Christmas and birthdays. All thoughts are
welcome: &lt;blog@wester.digital&gt; 
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://tilde.club/1/~user18130814200115/posts/0006-switching-to-python.txt</link>
<title>0006-switching-to-python.txt          2024-Jul-23 13:45     6.8 KB</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
Switching to Python
Mon, 08 Jan 2024
Technology, Opinion
===================

For the longest time (really since I started getting remotely
serious about writing my own software, my language of choice has
been POSIX shell. The shell is the environment through which one
interacts with a unix-like operating system, and shell-script are
simply combinations of interactions which combine to achieve
pretty monumental things.

I always knew that shell scripting had its limitations. Though it
was mostly fine for my purposes. After some recent issues with
the shell however, I have switched away from it. My scripting
language of preference is now python, though the transition is
strange, as the two languages are designed for entirely different
purposes. This post will detail the reasons I switched away from
shell as well as the difficulties I have had switching to python.

-----------------------------------------------------------------

The primary reason I moved away from shell scripting now, as
opposed to earlier is that I cannot reliably run shell scripts on
my current system. As I have mentioned in several previous posts
now, my main computer interface is currently an iPad app called
a-shell. a-shell uses dash for its shell processing, though the
port is extremely buggy and lacking in some fairly basic
features[1]. This is what finally propelled me away from shell
scripting, but there were many problems I was already
encountering beforehand, so let&#x27;s explore these too.

1. Standardisation
==================

POSIX is a set of standards for various pieces of software which
includes standards of how a POSIX-compliant shell should operate.
One major problem with these standards is that they are poorly
adhered to. The GNU project is particularly guilty of this, in
that it extends POSIX software with many non-POSIX features.
While these features are sometimes great, I cannot properly make
use of them because I do not know if a system I am targeting is
using the GNU-extended utilities or the base-POSIX ones.

This opens up to a wider point that I cannot write a shell script
and expect it to perform reliably on any given system. Minor
differences in the way a shell is implemented can cause an entire
script to fail or output wrong data. I actually had this problem
recently, where my shell wanted newline characters to be written
as follows &#x27;\\n&#x27; whereas the system I was targeting wanted &#x27;\n&#x27;.
This meant I could not test the software locally before pushing
it to the production server, which was of course highly
frustrating and time-consuming. A more common case is the use of
`echo`. Echo has various switches in various shell
implementations. Sometimes echo will interpret escape sequences,
sometimes it will just print them literally, sometimes the -n
switch makes it so echo does not terminate in a newline,
sometimes it just prints the string &#x27;-n&#x27;. Echo is virtually
unusable in shell scripting targeting multiple systems for this
exact reason and printf is often recommended instead.

2. Intended use
===============

Why does echo work in such varying ways? Well because the shell
was never intended for programming. It was intended for
interacting with your system. This is also why bare-POSIX shells
lack the functionality real programming languages have. At its
core, the shell is meant to interact with other programs on the
system, such as sed, grep, awk, cat, etcetera. GNU&#x27;s bash shell
makes an effort to push the shell closer towards being a proper
programming language by adding things like reading files and
processing substring directly in the shell without needing to
rely on cat and cut respectively.

3. External programs
====================

What about these programs the shell is meant to interact with
then? The way I see it, they are the greatest blessing and curse
of shell scripting. Basically, it is incredibly easy to call
upon a program installed on the system and equally easy to make
it interact with other programs. However, if you are targeting
multiple systems, you do not know exactly which programs are
installed, and which versions. Here we once again encounter the
problem of GNU-extended software and undefined behaviour.

Furthermore, because the shell can basically only do basic string
manipulations, your programs will likely heavily rely on calling
external programs (especially the core utilities) to achieve
anything noteworthy. Your shell script will act more as glue to
hold the various &#x27;real&#x27; programs together. With this being the
case however, if there is no program to perform the task you
need, you are basically out of luck. This once again goes to
show, that shell is not (and does not intoned to be) a
programming language.

-----------------------------------------------------------------

If these problems were already always present in the shell
however, then why did I choose to use it regardless? Well the
answer is simple: I needed a lot of glue. I often found myself in
situations where I had data of one format (usually given by a
program) and I needed that same data in a different format for
use in another program or for my own consumption. This is exactly
what shell script excel at. I would still use shell script for
this purpose if the dash port on a-shell was more stable.

Now I am using python for translating data in this manner, but
this is often much more complicated. Getting input data from a
command is doable in python, but nowhere near as easy as it is in
shell scripts (where you literally JUST write the command you
want the output from). Outputting data is also more difficult. In
shell, one can use pipes or redirects to pass data to a command
or file respectively, in python, there are several steps involved
in either of these processes, in addition to the need of
libraries. 

-----------------------------------------------------------------

The static site generator for this blog is now a little python
script rather than a shell script. Honestly the shell script
started out incredibly simple, relying really only on the
standard utility `head`. Things quickly grew complicated though,
with me using several dozen regex strings in sed to get both
html, gopher, and rss output working. While version 0.1 of my
site builder was mush more simple in shell, the monster it grew
into was much easier to understand in python, where it was also
more flexible. As such, translating the script to python allowed
me to make some quality of life changes, and it will also make
future development easier.

Most importantly though. The python implementation is stable, and
works in exactly the same way on any system running the same
version. If you wish to see my current implementation, it is
available on my GitHub page at
user18130814200115-2/plain.wester.digital.

[1] I do not, by any means, mean to accuse the author of a-shell
of doing a bad job. A shell is an incredibly complex piece of
software, and the fact that the shell works even this well is
nothing short of impressive.
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://tilde.club/1/~user18130814200115/posts/0005-housekeeping-fire-and-python.txt</link>
<title>0005-housekeeping-fire-and-python.t   2024-Jul-23 13:45     7.3 KB</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
Housekeeping, Fire, and Python
Tue, 2 Jan 2024
Lifestyle, Technology
==============================

For the past week or so, I have had a quite delightful morning
routine. Well I say routine, there is one particular item which
starts my day, and that is building a fire. I am currently
staying in Northern Italy, which is by no means as cold as my
home town (at the time of writing, there is a 15 degree
temperature difference, and the weekend there will reach around
-20 Celsius compared to +8 here), but it is nevertheless cold
enough to warrant heating the house. And in this particular
house, this is done trough two wood stoves.

As such, every morning starts with cleaning out the ashes,
brushing the hearth and wiping the glass. Afterwards, I head out
into the back yard to gather some firewood from our stores. I
have to pick a mix of sizes and types of wood: flash tinder,
kindling, smaller sticks, branches, and logs. The fist to get the
fire going, and the latter to keep it going without intervention
every few minutes. At this point, I start constructing the fire,
open up the vents for strong airflow and wait for some small
flames to form. By the time the branches are on, coffee will be
ready and the living room will slowly start heating up.

If all of this sounds incredibly tedious to you, well... in a
sense you would be correct. Building a fire like this is rather
more time-consuming on a day-to-day basis than a central heading
system using radiators, or a heat-pump-system for that matter.
Keeping the fire going also requires getting more wood from the
stores and stacking it on every two hours or so. However, both
building and marinating the fire are delightfully simple tasks,
perfect to get my body moving in the morning and keep my brain
snoozing for a little while. After the cleaning, I rouse my brain
and start what is essentially a process of creative problem
solving.  Every day, the kindling is different, the airflow, heat
of the stove, humidity of the tinder; there are simply too many
variables to keep in mind. So: You just light your kindling and
see if you can get and ember to turn into a flame. If something
is not working: check the airflow, maybe the chimney, and more
likely: the wood. 

A central heating system (which heats my apartment in the
freezing North) does not require such creative problem solving.
But what if the system breaks? Well, at that point the complexity
of the problem is likely so high that I cannot fix it on my own.
Calling a mechanic is essentially my only refuge, and this
becomes a tedious task, rather than a menial but enjoyable one as
with building the fire and maintaining the stove.

After I realized this link between simple systems and the joy I
have in using them, I started seeing these matters all around the
house. The dishwasher? Tedious, especially when it breaks. There
is a certain method to stacking the plates and bowls to ensure
maximum cleaning, which is somewhat enjoyable at the best of
times, but on the average day, it is just annoyingly
time-consuming and inefficient on space. Washing dishes by hand
in comparison is a largely mindless endeavour, but one I find
myself enjoying more than loading-, unloading-, and maintaining-
the dishwasher.

Nothing frustrates me quite as mush as a cold shower (when I want
a warm one), or a clogged drain while I am already in the shower.
On the other hand, in those cases where I have had to wash myself
using a bucket of water, the process has been enjoyable in much
the same way. A sort of rustic monotony where all problems are
ones I can solve in the moment without any particular skills.
Even those times where my bucket was filled with ice-cold water,
placed outside, in -15 degree weather, the process was more
enjoyable than those times that my shower refused to go those two
degrees higher to where I wanted it.

-----------------------------------------------------------------

At this point, I want to draw this idea of rustic monotony to
another endeavour of mine, that being programming. I have been
taking part in Advent Of Code 2023. For the uninitiated: Advent
of Code is a typical advent calender for the month of December
where each day introduces a new programming challenge which you
can solve using whatever methods you please. I joined in midway
through December, and as such am just on day 17 right now, though
I do not think I will finish the entire calendar.

You see, the early challenges in this calendar were rather
simple. I solved them using my usual tools (mostly sed actually)
and it was an enjoyable 15-30 minute practice to give my brain
something to chew on during winter break. As the days continued
however, the problems became more complex. Fairly quickly, the
performance and instability of shell scripts on my machine got in
the way of the programming. These shortcomings of the dash port
on my iPad are not problems I can solve, only ones I can work
around. Alternatively I can call a mechanic (send a GitHub issue
about my problem) and wait probably several month for it to be
fixed (if at all). Instead I switched to Python. At this point, I
was no longer solving little problems, I was writing full
programs. The days continued, and now I am here implementing full
scale algorithms such as Dijkstra&#x27;s, and troubleshooting each
program for up to a full hour. For some of the problems, if my
initial code did not work, I has literally no clue where to start
fixing the problem (or even diagnosing it for that matter).  It
usually involves writing a lot of code to get more verbose
output, slowing down that output to something manageable, and
then squinting and making minor adjustments for up to one hour.
What started as a 15-30 minute brain-teaser became a time sink
several hours deep. Most frustrating where there problems where I
got a working solution, only to be asked in part two, to run
those calculations 1 000 000 times, a task the efficiency of my
code was in no state to do.

I don&#x27;t find fixing problems like this fun, it is a frustrating
and time-consuming task. The same goes for optimizing code.
Whereas those first few days were building a fire, adding simple
steps together one at the time, ended with me building a central
heating system, drawing blueprints, researching algorithms,
optimizing piping, and a lot of headaches.

-----------------------------------------------------------------

I will be trying to make a greater effort to include rustically
enjoyable things in my life, and I will be trying to replace as
many painfully complex systems with human-sized ones. This likely
won&#x27;t be easy and even making such transitions will be
time-consuming and difficult (watch out for a future post titled
&quot;Make and effort to make it effortless&quot;), but I think such
transitions are worth it. Thinking back, this is the reason I
originally became interested in the command line interfaces, old
flip phones and feature phones.

This blog is in essence also a rustic-refuge. Writing post on
here is dreadfully simple. And while my site-builder script is
more complex than I would like (it was extended to deal with rss
and gopher aside from html, accounting for the extra size), the
writing of that script is now behind me. And I can focus on
writing in plaintext, wrapped to 65 columns and decorating it
with ASCII art and white space. Just what I need on an otherwise
uneventful evening where my only task is to keep the fire going
and the house heated.

</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://tilde.club/1/~user18130814200115/posts/0004-lecuring-politics-in-ficiton.txt</link>
<title>0004-lecuring-politics-in-ficiton.t   2024-Jul-23 13:45     9.3 KB</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
Lecturing politics in fiction
Sun, 10 Dec 2023
Fiction, Opinion
=============================

I tend to enjoy many different types of fiction written by a
variety of authors.  One of the most interesting aspects of any
fictional work is, in my opinion, the way it reflects the
character of the author. If there is something the author deeply
cares about, the it will undoubtedly show up somewhere in the
story they are crafting.  Likewise, if a character appears whose
ideals are strongly contrary to those of the writer, the
end-result is often that these characters feel shallow and dim.
Good authors can feel the same passion for a given subject as the
author does. An exceptional writer will also be able to arouse
these feelings for subjects which the author is not personally
invested in.

All of that is to say: Fiction can make one care about things
which one would otherwise be entirely unconcerned with. In doing
so, I think fiction can have an impact on the word at large that
is powerful and unique. Fiction does not affect our beliefs in
the same manner as a lecture, or an argument. Instead, it stirs
our emotions to make us care about new things, or bring to our
attention new perspectives which we previously had no emotional
investment in. It is for this reason that I include many
references to fictional works in my professional academic
writing. It is for this reason also that I cannot politics in
many works for fiction, let me explain.

In many works of fiction I consume, be they books, video games,
movies or other side, there is this trend to present political
opinions are a sort of lecture.  Whenever a particular political
viewpoint is brought up, the reader is assured of how
commonsensical or normal it is. I tend to find that liberal
authors are particularly persistent about this. Often lecturing
the audience that homosexuality, abortion, egalitarianism,
socialism, non-binary genders, sexual promiscuity, female power,
black power, and other such concerns are to be supported as the
entirely commonsensical and morally correct options. By telling
the audience these points instead of showing them, the work
becomes both less impactful and less realistic. I will first
cover the realm point, as this is -- by far -- the less important
of the two.

To demonstrate the point about realism, let me use an example:
There is a series of books which has been slowly releasing over
the past few years called: ``Tales of a new world&#x27;&#x27; by P.C. Cast.
One of the things which stood out to me in this book is the
treatment of homosexuality. In the first part of the series, a
big point is made by one of the characters about how normal
homosexual relationships are in their society, about how ``love
is love&#x27;&#x27;, and how the choice of one&#x27;s partner is only up to the
two people involved. These statements only really make sense in a
society where homosexuality is not yet full normalized. After
all, if you consider something truly normal, then one would not
really think to mention it.

For instance: I do not consider it exceptional enough to mention
that I use toilet paper, as this is normal in my corner of the
world. If I used a bidet, I would mention this as exceptional,
though perhaps not if I lived in some Asian countries, where
paper is the exception, and bidet&#x27;s the norm.  Imagine a work of
fiction where a character suddenly goes off on a two-page tangent
about how normal it is for them to be heterosexual. You would
find it strange that such an explicit mention would me made
right? In fiction you can even make use of this strangeness.

In the aforementioned book, there is a scene where two people of
different societies discuss relationships. We are told that their
respective societies accept homosexuality as nothing different
from heterosexuality, though homosexuality is given exceptional
treatment in the dialog. However, one can make use of the feeling
of surprise we feel when something we presume to be normal is not
considered such by someone else:

    ``With us it is customary for the male to present the female
    with a gift to start a relationship.&#x27;&#x27;

    ``Oh, but what if two females enter into a relationship? Is
    there any gift giving then? And what of two males?&#x27;&#x27;

    ---

    ``I tend to use toilet paper&#x27;&#x27;

    ``Of course! Is there any other option?&#x27;&#x27;

    ``Well, in my country it is customary to use bidets&#x27;&#x27;

By using the notion of being surprised at a statement, shows
that, for the relevant character, it is entirely normal that two
same-sex people might enter into a relationship, or that one
would use toilet paper. I bring up the example of homosexuality
mostly because I grew up in an environment where homosexuality
was considered very normal, and therefore did not warrant special
coverage.  Growing up, my mother would sometimes enquire whether
I had a boyfriend or girlfriend yet. At school, we would talk
about marriage; not gay-marriage and traditional-marriage, just
marriage.

-----------------------------------------------------------------

Now, let me cover the second problem: that lecturing your
audience works against your intentions and detracts from the
power of fiction.  I mentioned how fiction can make us *care* in
a way that other forms of media can not. When a story pauses to
affirm an stance, make an argument, or otherwise lecture the
reader, it takes away from this power, and to me it always feels
like such considerations are shoehorned into the narrative.

I lost count of the sheer number of fictional works I have read
which take time to affirm that the choice to terminate a
pregnancy is the inalienable right of the pregnant woman in
question. But simply affirming this will do nothing to convince
anyone opposed to your view, and those readers who already agree
will most likely just skip over this line. For me: I get annoyed
every time it rears its head in a story exactly because fiction
has the power to actually promote such beliefs!

Imagine if someone wrote a story which contained a young woman
who was struggling with an unwanted pregnancy (if I wanted to
convince as many pro-lifers as possible, I would make this a
sub-plot of a side-character). Use whatever narrative you like
here: she was young and did not oversee the consequences of her
actions, she was coerced into having sexual relations, she was
assured my a contraceptive agent which ended up failing, you name
it. If you show her personal struggle coming to terms with her
situation, allow the audience together with the character to
realize the fact that she is not ready to raise a child, and show
how this all impacts the girl&#x27;s physical and mental well-being,
you might actually get typically pro-life people to *care* about
the situation this girl finds herself in. You might show, with
another supporting character the impact it can have on one&#x27;s
well-being to have another person supporting them. This person
does not need to agree with the girl&#x27;s decisions or feelings, but
must simply refrain from judging or shaming her.

Such as story can bring to the eyes of the audience the real
struggles involved in complicated moral issues. Struggles which
-- due to being highly emotional in nature -- are often not
brought up in arguments, debates, or generalized statements.
Bringing to light the sheer complexity of the issue will, at the
very least, make some people think a little deeper and harder
about their stance. The recipe above can also easily be adapted
for a pro-life argument, which will have much more impact than
forcing a statement such as ``abortion is murder&#x27;&#x27; into a work of
fiction.

-----------------------------------------------------------------

I started writing this post because I was reading the final part
of Cast&#x27;s ``Tales of a New World&#x27;&#x27;. In this final book, I found
the lectured politics to be even more invasive than before. This
book preaches especially heavily about the superiority of women
as leaders. About how men caused the downfall of a society long
ago, how women are better because they are caring, calm, and
capable of bearing life, etcetera. Not only can I not detect any
actual passion behind the words of the various characters who
affirm these beliefs, I can in no way bring myself to care. If
the author instead showed a thriving society where women ruled,
one which thrives exactly because men are not allowed to rule,
then one might begin to entertain the idea.  In Cast&#x27;s book, one
it TOLD that various societies thrive because of their female
leadership, but Cast never SHOWS us this, thereby breeding no
investment in entertaining this idea.  Instead, I think lecturing
like this just affirms the believes of radical feminists, and
just angers conservatives and egalitarians, thus allowing more
discord to breed between them.

Before I finish, I want to make one quick point of clarification:
I realized why reading over what I have written so-far that this
post sounds a lot like: ``liberal politics are ruining fiction
and I am upset about it&#x27;&#x27;. In truth, I am upset, but not because
of the flavour of politics presented. I am upset exactly because
I care about many of the topics I am lectured about in the books
I read.  It is because I care about these topics that I am so
dissatisfied with the lecture-approach. Fiction has a real and
unique way of influencing the world at large, but this is not the
way to do it.  Instead, liberal authors are cementing people in
their beliefs, thus quite literally breeding conservative
sentiment. 
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://tilde.club/1/~user18130814200115/posts/0003-magic.txt</link>
<title>0003-magic.txt                        2024-Jul-23 13:45    13.4 KB</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
Magic in fiction and real life
Wed, 6 Dec 2023
Fiction, Opinion
==============================

Magic is a large part of very form of fiction, and -- for me at
least -- also a large part of getting enjoyment out of everyday
life.  `Magic&#x27;  in this case refers to a way of explaining
certain phenomena in the world. Bad explanations go along the
lines of: ``its magic, now be quiet&#x27;&#x27;. The other end contains
overly detailed explanations.  Bordering on the edge of science,
even if the science is fictional.  When magic is well done in a
work of fiction, it always fills me with the giddy sense of
excitement. The explanations given dance just at the border of
what I can understand, and this sets my imagination going like
nothing else.

So then, let us look at some examples of magical systems in
popular fiction, explain why must of them are terrible at
intriguing me, and follow all of this up with some real world
magic.

Harry Potter
------------

On of the most popular fictional works containing so-called magic
is probably Harry Potter. Love it or hate it, the Harry Potter
franchise has been extremely influential to fiction as a whole,
and I can think of few people who have not read at least one of
the books, or seen a single movie.

That being said, the magic system in Harry Potter is terrible,
truly amongst the worst, here is why: How does magic work in the
Harry Potter universe? You say a spell, you flick a sick around,
though sometimes you do not speak, and sometime you do not flick,
oh and you need to be born a wizard, which is a largely random
process. This system explains practically nothing, as most
spell-based magical systems do. Harry Potter goes the extra mile
in lack-of-explanation by not even explaining where the energy
used to perform magics comes from.

Let me first address spellcasting more generally. Spellcasting,
in its most basic form is the utterance of a phrase. The main
question that arises when you implement a system like this is:
Why that phrase? What is it about that combination of sounds that
causes the big magic to happen? Is someone or something
listening? If not, why must the sounds be vocalized at all?
Spellcasting can be implemented properly however, and the systems
that do are often among the most satisfying, but Harry Potter is
not one of them.

Then there are wands and their movements. Magic, in Harry Potter,
is seemingly an inherent trait you are born with, that much is
explained to us. We know that wizards and witches can perform
magic without a wand, though possession of a proper wand allows
for the focussing of energy like a lens. This much I can accept,
and I actually like about HP&#x27;s system. I would still like to know
where the energy comes from, but this is certainly a start.

Thus wizards have or use energy through their wands, and making
the right sounds either kills a guy, or makes him grow a bear. By
not explaining the spells at all, there is very little room for
the imagination to play. We know that mispronouncing the
levitation spell can cause you to spontaneously combust, but
there is not explanation as to why. Let us say we are speaking in
a language where float and explode sound very similar, then we
might have some room to fantasize. What if I used the hand
motions of float, but instead I said boat, would that summon an
aeroplane? That sort of thing.

Avatar the last airbender
-------------------------

Let&#x27;s look at a slightly better system: Avatar (the one with the
tattooed monk, not the blue aliens). In Avatar, it is presupposed
that every person has some sort of life force or energy flowing
through them. Some people, called benders know how to shape this
life force in order to manipulate the elements: water air, fire,
and earth. This manipulation functions by moving one&#x27;s body and
the energy within it, and we can see this in action both in the
comics and the television show. If a fire-bender moves their
weight forward and thrusts an open palm forwards, they might
generate a large cloud of fire, whereas the same movement with
two outstretched fingers generates a finely concentrated stream
of fire, or even lightning.

This system works so well at its core because it uses fairly
commonsensical concepts and combines them in a way you can grasp,
even though it is still fictional. We know a thing or two about
energy, we feel it when we become excited or angry, we feel its
absence when we are tired. We also know a thing or two about
manipulating the word through moving our limbs around. The fact
that Avatar borrows from Chinese folklore and martial arts only
aids in our understanding and the air of mystery surrounding it.

You can start to fantasise about certain motions combined with
certain elements.  The story even encourages this as certain
characters use the motions of water bending with the energy of
fire bending. You can envision your own moves and variations, you
can think of synergies and strategies, either borrowing from
martial arts, or simply letting your imagination run loose.

When it comes to explaining why only certain people can bend
certain elements however, the magic falls apart for me. In
essence, it has something to do with reincarnation and giant lion
turtles who granted certain people the ability to bend at some
time in their past lives.  But if the system is all about
learning to manipulate energy and moving your body, then why do
we need to be imbued with this gift? To me, some of the magic is
lost in this explanation, as it makes the whole bending idea much
more otherworldly then it otherwise was.

Unsong
------

Now, let us turn to one of my favourite implementations of magic
in all of fiction: Unsong. In the world of Unsong, there are two
forms of magic: names of God, and placebomancy. In order to
explain both of these, some background is needed. The world of
Unsong adheres to the biblical story of creation for the most
part. However, after a war between the hosts of heaven and the
hosts of hell, one angel: Uriel, decided to reprogram the world
into the probabilistic system of atoms and forces we know today.
Before this time, everything in existence was a direct expression
of God&#x27;s numerous faculties. After the restructuring of reality,
history progresses as we know it, up until the space race. During
one of the Apollo missions, humans attempt to orbit the moon and
end up crashing into the crystal sphere that surrounds the earth.
This sphere kept out the divine light and kept the world
functioning probabilistically and all that.

With the sphere cracked, a tiny amount to divine light is let
back in. This means that everything in existence is now a little
more an expression of God than it was before. Words previously
just expressed things in existence, but now they also express
God. The things in existence these words used to refer to also
express God, and so there is not a connection between the thing
and its expression, between the map and the territory. These two
influence each other in both directions. Founding a town will
cause it to be put on a map, but putting a town on a map may just
as well cause people to settle there.

In the world of Unsong, that certain phrases express God&#x27;s
faculties more clearly than others. These are the names of God,
and they have various effects, such as making you bulletproof,
walk on water, or become invisible. They do so by clearly
expressing God&#x27;s indestructible nature, His weightless, His
obscurity, etcetera. A name of God is an expression of ultimate
reality, and an expression of reality is no different from
reality itself.  However, this is -- by far -- the less
interesting system of the two form of magic in Unsong.

The second system is called placebomancy and it neatly
encapsulates all forms of magic. Spells? got those, potions? got
those, Avatar-esque bending? yes sir.  A placebomancer attempts
to convince reality that a certain thing ought to happen.
Placebomancers use the entire narrative for their acts, carrying
a mystique, having mysterious backstories, and ensuring esoteric
places to perform their rituals. The reason this works is that,
since the sky cracked, reality is not as stable as it used to be,
and if you can convince it somehow that what you are doing ought
to make fire shoot from your fingers, then that is what will
happen.  The stories we tell each other are a part of reality,
therefore: wearing a robe and waving a wand helps to convince
reality that you are doing magic.

What is great about this system is that it simply uses a facet of
the fundamental functioning of Unsong&#x27;s world: the way we express
things is just as real as those things themselves. Furthermore,
it is inherently limited, which explains nicely why everyone is
not just placebomancing their way into paradise on earth. Sure
you MIGHT be able to convince reality that the devil never
existed, but the devil very strongly believes that he does, and
so do many others. Then again, if you can find a convincing
narrative, the world lies at your feet.

Both of these systems are things you can grasp, but not quite
fully comprehend, thus leaving space for your imagination to fill
in the blanks. This is the real magic at play here. No words on a
page can make magic to the same extent your own imagination can.
Thus, let us finally move on to real magic.

Magic in the real world
-----------------------

With real-word magic, I do not mean spells of ice and fire, nor
ritual magic or elemental bending. I simply refer to those things
which have a magical air about them. Things which we can
understand just well enough for them to instill a childlike
wonder in us and set our imaginations working. These things
excite and intrigue us.  Too-simple and they are not magical at
all, too complicated, and it is science.

Let&#x27;s start with a personal example: audio cassettes. Audio
cassettes work by putting air vibrations onto magnetic tape and
retrieving them in the reverse manner. Now: I understand air
vibrations, when listening to music (especially loud music) I can
feel the speaker and the ground shake, I understand that this is
the essence of sound. I also understand magnets. That is not to
say that I necessarily grasp magnetic fields and such, but I know
how magnets work, I have seen and felt them work. Expressing the
vibrations of air linearly as thousands of little magnets on a
tape, and spinning that tape to get the vibrations back is the
essence of an audio cassette. The fact that we can do this is
absolutely incredible to me, and, though I fully understand the
parts, I still find it amazing that we can bend reality in this
manner. In short, it is magical to me.

Staying on the topic of audio: I do not find digital music
players magical in the slightest. I simply do not grasp
flash-storage, digital-to-analogue converters, and transistors
well enough. These are all elements squarely in the realm of
science. You would not try to explain them to a child, and with
an adult you would use complex theories, and a lot a math. This
is neither exciting nor intriguing.  Sure it is impressive, but
impressive and magical are two entirely different things.

There are also systems which are too-simple to be magical. I find
nothing magical about a classic gas-stove. Propane moves from the
tank to the stove, it it seeps out slowly and constantly ignites
itself. It is too-simple. Induction stoves on the other hand are
too complicated. This also shows how subjective this magical
feeling can be. To you, maybe a propane torch is magical, or
maybe you grew up with so much magnetic field theory that
induction stoves occupy the same space for you as cassette tapes
do for me. 

I honestly believe that keeping some of this magic in your life
is a large part of being happy and curious about the world. These
`magical&#x27; things are the first places where you can learn more.
You can turn your basic grasp into full understanding, at which
point new magics open up to you. If you had to start your journey
into electronic by understanding  modern chip architecture, I am
almost certain your search would never lead anywhere, it would
simply be too-overwhelming. For me, magic can be found in audio
cassettes, chemical photography, fermentation, pregnancies, seed
germination, and so much more. For you the list might be
different, but I think the effect is the same.  Fiction is one
way of keeping magic in your life at least. And if it is done
well, it can instill a sense of wonder for the world as a whole,
not just for the fictional universe where the magic originated.

-----------------------------------------------------------------

I will close with one recommendation for a work of fiction, that
being ``The name of the Wind&#x27;&#x27; by Patrick Rothfuss. It is the
first book of a as-of-yet unfinished trilogy. And I enjoyed
reading it very much. It has a great an innovative system of
magic, which spiked my curiosity many time throughout the book,
and the general storyline is very engaging. Above all though, it
has been a while since a book managed to arouse my emotions so
well. There were times I got so upset and angry at the
main-character&#x27;s actions that I had to put the book down for a
few days to read a different novel. There were many many times
where I had to stifle a fit of giggling in the library or on
public transport.  And I even smiled on occasion, which is not
particularly something I am known to do. 

If you have any questions or comments, feel free to send me an
email at &lt;blog@wester.digital&gt;, I am especially interested in
your thoughts about real-world-magic, as well as any book
recommendations you might have, especially is they are works
containing ~good~ magical systems.
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://tilde.club/1/~user18130814200115/posts/0002-my-current-tech-setup.txt</link>
<title>0002-my-current-tech-setup.txt        2024-Jul-23 13:45    10.7 KB</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
My current tech setup
Wed, 6 Dec 2023
Technology, Travel
=====================

Over the period that this blog has been offline, my tech setup
has changed a lot. The devices I use, the software that runs on
them, and the interpretation of my personal technology guidelines
has all changed. What I think is very interesting to observe in
this change is that my background ideas have stayed consistent,
even though there are few similarities observable at first glance
between by tech now and December of last year.

Let me first outline my principles for using technology.
Electronics and I have a love-hate relationship, and we are only
staying together for the kids (id est: because you cannot
navigate modern society without electronics). My principles allow
me to use tech in such a way that I not tempted to go
full-Unabomber more than once a month (the live-in-the-woods
type, not the letterbomb type). So, without further ado, here are
my principles:

    - The tech I use works for me, I don&#x27;t work for it
    - Portability is key
    - Environmental concerns trump usability
    - Embrace digital minimalism

Now, I could go over every point in this list and explain exactly
what I mean by it, but I think it is more interesting to display
my application of these principles by looking at my old setup,
and by new one. Both of these setups adhere to the principles,
though to varying degrees, and with different interpretations.

The old setup
-------------

My old setup contained the following devices:
    
    - A non-smart mobile phone (sometimes two)
    - An android tablet
    - A Pinebook pro laptop
        - A USB webcam and Microphone
    - A Lomo instant square polaroid camera
    - A xDuoo 3II media player

There were some other items, such a set of cassette-walkmen
(walkmans?), but those are not remarkably important to cover
here.  All of the items above filled a specific niche. The phones
were in my pocket so I was reachable at all times by SMS and
call. The android tablet was for reading books and annotating
papers.  The laptop was my university machine, meaning that I
used it to run vim and LaTeX, follow online classes, hand in
assignments, download study materials, and stay in touch with
colleagues. The Lomo camera was to capture memories of various
trips, hikes, and events. Lastly, the media player was there for
my ever present love of music.

Now to cover the principles. With this setup, I interpreted the
first principle as follows: Use simple software or build your
own. If a piece of software worked against my way of doing things
too much, I would modify it, or build a different system from
scratch. During this period, I made various mobile apps for my
Nokias including: weather info, bible reading, sudokus, tertris,
Google authenticator, and other miscellaneous things. I wrote my
own set of macros for the Troff typesetting system. I designed a
plaintext to pdf calendar system.  Lastly, I wrote basically an
entire desktop environment for Linux, save for the window
manager.

For portability, and environmentalism, a large consideration was
battery life.  The Nokias needed to be charged once per week, the
xDuoo even less frequently.  The camera ran on two 1.5 v
batteries which lasted well over a year, and the laptop and
tablet had such low power draw that I could charge them with my
tiny 20w portable solar panel.

The setup was furthermore portable because I could decide exactly
what to bring for every trip, carrying no more or less than I
needed.  This was also how I embraced digital minimalism at the
time. Even though there were many devices in my daily rotation,
every device was itself minimalistic, aiming to do no more or
less than I required of it.

The new setup
-------------

As I said, my new setup has a very different daily rotation. I
now use:

    - A 6th generation iPad mini
    - A 2017 Samsung galaxy A7 smartphone

Quite a shorter list eh? So what happened? When I returned to my
home country over the summer, I met up with my grandparents who
expressed a wish to video call me on occasion, something which
was not possible with my devices at the time (because my
grandparents insisted on using WhatsApp). I noted that I would
consider getting an old smartphone for that purpose, though I
tried to convince them to just use signal, zoom, discord, skype,
or really anything that was not WhatsApp (even though I highly
dislike all of these platforms). At this point, my grandfather
pulled his `old smartphone&#x27; from the shelf. A device which is
still fully capable of performing the tasks a smartphone needs to
do. The only thing that is aged about is is the USB micro-B
charging port.

As such, I switched from my two beautiful Nokia flipphones to a
one dual-sim- smartphone. The primary reason I fully switched,
rather than just keeping the Samsung around for video calls, is
that I really did not want to add yet another device to my
rotation. The smartphone also came with some other benefits.
Here in Norway, many, many things work using apps: Loyalty cards,
public transport, banking, library cards, digital identification,
two factor authentication, etcetera. For most of these services
therefore, I had specific cards or devices issues by the bank,
government, university, and so forth.  Each of these cards and
devices lived in my wallet, though switching to apps for these
things, I have managed to completely get rid of my wallet, simply
carrying a few cards in my phone case (cash is not a thing in
Norway anyways). The smartphone also did away with the need for a
separate media player and camera.  Both of these devices still
have their uses, one as a powerful DAC, the other for vacation
pictures, but neither are now part of my daily rotation.

Thus far the story behind the smartphone, but what about the
other items? Well, the android tablet started misbehaving, and it
really was not suited anymore for everyday use. I decided to buy
an iPad because -- according to my experience with them -- they
last remarkably long, both in hardware and software. I
furthermore wanted to try out the apple pencil for annotations,
and perhaps even for notetaking during classes, rather than my
paper/pen setup from back then.

While shopping for this iPad, I considered getting a slightly
more capable one, such as the iPad air, and using it as my main
computing device, in essence replacing my laptop. My conclusion
from everything I read online at the time though, was that the
software ecosystem was simply not mature enough to do this.
Then, a few weeks after buying the iPad, my laptop broke down. It
was not a major issue, requiring at most a day work of repairs
and maybe 200 NOK in parts, but it was nevertheless annoying, and
I had neither the time nor energy for the repair at the time. I
decided then that I would try and see if I could get away with
just the iPad.

I started looking around for apps. As I mentioned in the _old
setup_ section, I used my laptop as a university device. The iPad
was already capable of running all of the university software for
assignments and communication, and I could access the library and
remote systems without problem. The main holdup however was my
writing setup. At this time, I was using LaTeX and vim. Luckily,
by this time, I had stopped modifying virtually all software I
used, and focused on portability by using standard and
widely-available software. Nevertheless, I still needed a LaTeX
compiler and a text editor for my iPad, preferably git as well,
and preferably free (both as in freedom and gratis). I looked
through the AppStore and tried nearly every free LaTeX app. Most
of them handed the compilation off to a server, which was not
suited for my purposes, and all of the ones I tried had VERY
barebone-editors, there was no good-, free- git app, and really,
I just wanted to go back to my comfortable tty.

It was while researching simply virtualising a Linux machine on
the iPad that I encountered an app called `a-shell&#x27;. Not a LaTeX
compiler, but a unix shell for iPad, which came with vim, git,
and LaTeX. I said it in the previous post, and I will say it
again: This app is THE SOLE REASON I can use the iPad as a laptop
replacement.  Over half of my daily screen time is spent on this
app alone, and while it is clunky an limited, it is good enough
for the work I need to do, that being writing. If you are a
programmer, you will not be able to live on iPad OS, but if you
are a writer comfortable with unix-like systems, then a-shell is
the place to go.

So that is the new setup. It embraces minimalism in the number of
devices (I see it as carrying around two multitools, rather than
having a full toolbox), and it embraces portability, because I
can bring all my tech everywhere as long as I have a small bag or
cargo pants. As far as the whole `the device works for me&#x27; thing,
this is something which my perspective changed a lot on over the
years.  Previously I wanted to control everything on my devices.
I did not want a single program to run without my knowledge and
consent. This lead to much frustration with virtually all devices
except for those running Linux, or single-purpose devices.
Nowadays, I just let the device to whatever it wants as long as
it does not get in my way. I use the skills I gathered in the
past to modify, and manipulate my tech (especially the
smartphone) to stay out of my way wherever necessary, but I
no-longer care enough to do a full sweep and really clamp the
device down.

That leaves us with the final principle: environmentalism. This
is always a difficult topic when talking about changing what
devices you use. The primary environmental problem with tech is
e-waste, and I am contributing to the problem. I try to minimize
my impact by giving most of my old devices new homes, and new
purposes, but not many people are interested these days in a
flipphone from 2005, with a glued-on keyboard and a broken
display. At the very least, I used these devices to their limit,
giving them use well after others had already thrown them away.

But after reuse and reduce, there is only recycle left, and I
know that much of the rare-earth metals in electronic devices
cannot be recycled. I hope to offset my damage a bit by donating
to wildlife conservation organisations such as Mossy Earth (and I
suggest you do the same), and other than that I will to keep my
current devices alive as long as possible. At least the
smartphone and keyboard were second-hand, though this seems a
small drop in the bucket for the overall e-waste problem. One day
I will likely write about the right-to-repair movement, and it
impact on environmental concerns, but that day is not today.

If you have any questions or comments regarding my old-or-new
setup, please send me an email. The address is
&lt;blog@wester.digital&gt;. I would be especially interested in
hearing your thoughts on breathing new life into my old devices,
especially the unstable android tablet, and the old Nokias.
</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://tilde.club/1/~user18130814200115/posts/0001-the-return-of-the-blog.txt</link>
<title>0001-the-return-of-the-blog.txt       2024-Jul-23 13:45     5.6 KB</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
The return of the blog
Tue, 5 Dec 2023
Meta content
======================

Hi, it has been a while hasn&#x27;t it?

For the uninitiated: I used to run a regular html/css blog on my
personal home server. This `server&#x27; was in fact just a raspberry
pi stuffed in a shoebox which lived underneath my parents&#x27;
ISP-provided modem/router. I always knew that this system would
fail some day, and living more than one thousand kilometers away,
I would have no way of fixing things. This happened way back in
May of 2023. I fixed the issue on a visit this summer, only for
the SD-card to break itself again not a month later. All this
time, I have add the itch to write, but there were two problems:
First, my server was fried, and second, my static site generator
was on that sever.

Yes you heard that right, I was a total [REDACTED] and kept the
only version of my software on a device prone to breaking. I
suffered and I learned. My old static site generator was an
incredibly efficient Makefile, consisting of less than 50 lines
of code. Despite its brevity, it handled: indexing, rss, styling,
special pages, and more.  Re-writing this system has been the
main holdup for me in terms of writing.

Now, I hear you thinking: `it was only 50 lines of code, it could
not take more than an afternoon to reproduce&#x27;. This is entirely
true, however there is one other little snag: my laptop gave up
life. For the record: I know what is wrong, and I know how to fix
it, but the process is rather too-involved for my current
schedule. As such, I have been reduced to my mobile, and the ipad
I historically only used for annotating pdf&#x27;s, and dealing with
modern society (in the form of banking apps, identification,
loyalty cards, etcetera).

As you may know: ipads are not exactly great for programming.
Granted, there are some really impressive apps out there such as
ish which emulates a full x86 alpine environment, and a-shell
which aims to bring a unix environment to the ipad (this is
actually what I am writing this post on). These apps are
incredibly impressive, and a-shell is the sole reason I can even
afford to leave my laptop unimpaired for now. Nevertheless, the
programmings-side-of-things is currently too clunky, making a
re-write of the static site generator a much greater effort than
it should be (For context, currently in a-shell, there is no way
to loop over a file in it&#x27;s port of dash...).

All of this nasty weather comes with a massive silver lining
though: not having access to my usual way of doing things has
exposed me to many new systems which I wish to write about. That,
and the fact that I have about one year worth of posts to catch
up on should make for an interesting year.

-----------------------------------------------------------------

With all of that preamble out of the way, let&#x27;s talk about the
new blogging system. It is INCREDIBLY simple, and very scuffed,
but I must say, I find it has a certain charm to it. Basically, I
have a folder containing plaintext files.  The first line is a
title, the second the date, and the third the tags (though not
even this is fixed, these three lines can contain whatever).
These files are pushed to a GitHub repository where a small
script is ran on them. I cannot stress enough: this script is
SMALL. All it does is list the files in reverse chronological
order, and grab the first three lines from each using unix head.
I use some sed magic to get urls working in html, but that is it.

    ls -rc posts/* | xargs head -n 3
    # the rest is commentary

I was inspired to do things this way largely from my explorations
of gopherspace. For those who do not know: Gopher is a very
simple internet protocol which was around before the modern web.
It essentially serves plaintext files much like this one, and has
some special syntax to deal with links and such things. Gopher
has been largely phased out by the growth of the web, though --
as with all things --  a bunch of stubborn nerds refuse to let it
go. In case it is not clear: those are terms of affects, and I am
such a suborn nerd.

I severely disliked gopher when I first learned of it. I saw no
reason to distribute information over protocols which required
specialized software to retrieve. That is not to say I liked the
modern web mind you, but gopher (and gemmini for that matter)
seemed like they would just require yet another application to
exist on my system. This was especially frustrating because I
read only one gopher phlog at the time, and I considered
switching to a different application just for that a waste of
time. I also hated that there were no RSS feeds (which I still
consider the only saving grace for the modern web), thus
separating these phlogs even more from my other content. (Just
before anyone asks: yes I will eventually get rss working on this
site as well, but writing is currently more important to me than
programming).

All of that is to say: things have changed, and I now spent a
significant portion of my internet time on gopher. I became
inspired by gopher phlogs such as hoi.st by Luxeferre, someone I
know from my days working on KaiOS -- and gopher.black by James
Tomasino, to create a very simple site so I could just focus on
getting some of my writing out there again.

I might mirror or migrate this blog to gopher some time in the
future. It certainly seems a lot better suited for that space,
but for now: I just want to write again, and this is the easiest
way to do that. Thus we have this weird https-plaintext, I assure
you that it is as confusing to me as it is to you.

---------------------------------------------------------------------

I will fill this blog with some actual content soon, now that it
is up again, I expect I will be writing frequently, we have a lot
to catch up on.
</pre>]]></description>
</item>





</channel></rss>
