<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>gopher://gopher.black/1/phlog</title>
<link>gopher://gopher.black/1/phlog</link>

<item>
<link>gopher://gopher.black/1/phlog/20250102-resolution</link>
<title>2025-01-02 - Resolution</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
----------------------------------------
Resolution
January 02nd, 2025
----------------------------------------

Be it resolved:

In the great year two thousand and twenty five I shall become the
official spokesperson for a brand of luxury toilet paper.

&lt;a href=gopher://gopher.black/1/phlog/20240102-resolution&gt;2024 Resolution&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=gopher://gopher.black/1/phlog/20221231-resolution&gt;2023 Resolution&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=gopher://gopher.black/1/phlog/20211230-resolution&gt;2022 Resolution&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=gopher://gopher.black/1/phlog/20201231-resolution&gt;2021 Resolution&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=gopher://gopher.black/1/phlog/20200101-resolution&gt;2020 Resolution&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=gopher://gopher.black/1/phlog/20181225-resolutions&gt;2019 Resolution&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=gopher://gopher.black/1/phlog/20180101-resolution&gt;2018 Resolution&lt;/a&gt;

</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://gopher.black/1/phlog/20250122-bye-bye-meta</link>
<title>2025-01-22 - Bye Bye Meta</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
----------------------------------------
Bye Bye Meta
January 22nd, 2025
----------------------------------------

I nuked most of the content from my Facebook account today, and
completely destroyed my Instagram account. But tomasino, why were
you on Facebook? Great question, nerds.

Iceland runs on Facebook. It&#x27;s really weird. Well, not really if
you consider that Iceland has been at the top of the charts of the
most online citizens in the world almost nonstop since gopher came
on the scene. It was number one for most of that time, but never
really lower than 4th on the list. People here are really, really
connected, and the circles are quite homogeneous. It&#x27;s estimated
that 91% of all Icelanders are on Facebook. And that causes some
problems (obviously).

Since they can assume you&#x27;re on there, most businesses don&#x27;t
bother with websites. Restaurants, coffee shops, all of them, just
a Facebook page. I can order Indian food over Facebook messenger.
I signed my kid up for the summer farm camp over messenger. Worse,
my son&#x27;s school communications come via Facebook group. It&#x27;s
really not a practical option to not participate.

So when we moved here I got sucked back in. My wife avoided it,
and I took one for the team.

But here we are in this darkest of timelines, and I can&#x27;t justify
giving Meta any more than they&#x27;ve already stolen. So what do I do?
I become a ghost.

I&#x27;ve deleted every bit of content I have on Facebook except a post
telling people why and where else to find me. But I kept the
account. I can see those school groups. I can book a table. I&#x27;ll
use end-to-end encryption when I need to use messenger, and then
delete the chats anyway. Minimum viable engagement.

Instagram though... there&#x27;s no reason to have it. Boom, gone.

I figured telling gopher was the best way to share. :)

</pre>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<link>gopher://gopher.black/1/phlog/20250211-moving-domains</link>
<title>2025-02-11 - Moving domains</title>
<description><![CDATA[<pre>
----------------------------------------
Moving domains
February 11th, 2025
----------------------------------------

I&#x27;m in the process of migrating away from Namesilo for my domain
hosting. They&#x27;ve been good for me for a long time, but it&#x27;s time
to break my remaining connections with the US. I&#x27;ve picked OVH
Cloud for the new registrar since they seem to have good TLD
support. But I&#x27;ll serve my DNS zones from 1984.is as I&#x27;ve been
doing. I like them. It&#x27;s very straight forward.

I need to go back over my other recurring services and cancel more
things. I used to have a big list, but I think I need to look at
credit card bills now to piece them together. I just get this
feeling that with the uncertainty in the US it&#x27;ll be smart to keep
myself lean.

What about you? Are you doing anything with your services?

</pre>]]></description>
</item>
</channel></rss>
